[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "Valence Bond Theory was developed in the year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1916",
            "b) 1927",
            "c) 1930",
            "d) 1932"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Valence Bond Theory was developed in 1927 by Heitler and London. "
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "According to VBT, the formation of a stable bond requires _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The electrons should have opposite spins",
            "b) The two atoms should be close to each other",
            "c) The greater overlapping of the electron clouds",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to VBT, when two atoms come closer to each other with opposite electron spins, due to mutual rearrangements (or overlapping) of their electron clouds, energy changes are produced.\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "The s-orbital does not show preference to any direction because _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is the smallest orbital",
            "b) It is present in every atom",
            "c) It is spherically symmetric",
            "d) It is the first orbital"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The s-orbital is spherically symmetric in shape so it does not show preference to any direction. It is the same from all the directions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "The p-orbital is in the shape of a _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sphere",
            "b) Dumbbell",
            "c) Pear-shaped lobe",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The p-orbital is in the shape of a Dumbbell. It has 2 lobes that are pointing in opposite directions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "According to VBT, the direction of a bond which is formed due to overlapping will be _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the same direction in which orbitals are concentrated",
            "b) In the opposite direction in which orbitals are concentrated",
            "c) Perpendicular to the direction in which orbitals are concentrated",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oxygen molecule is paramagnetic in nature, although it does not contain unpaired electrons which is not explained in VBT.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Which orbital would form a more stronger bond if both of them have identical stability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The one which is less directionally concentrated",
            "b) The one which is more directionally concentrated",
            "c) Both will be equally strong",
            "d) It differs from atom to atom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The direction of the bond formed will be in that direction in which the orbitals are concentrated. For Example: When two px orbitals overlap, the bond is formed along the x-axis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "Hybridisation of Acetylene is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sp",
            "b) sp2",
            "c) sp3",
            "d) dsp2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Acetylene molecule is C2H2. It is sp hybridised.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Shape of  PCl5 molecule is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tigonal Planar",
            "b) Linear",
            "c) Trigonal bipyramidal",
            "d) Tetrahedral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PCl5 is trigonal bipyramidal with its bond angle  equal to 1200 and 900.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Predict the shape of the H2O compound based upon concepts of hybridisation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tetrahedral",
            "b) Angular or bent structure",
            "c) Trigonal Planar",
            "d) Pyramidal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The water molecule has angular or bent structure due to the presence of two lone pairs which repels strongly.\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of sp3d2 hybridised molecule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HCHO",
            "b) ClO4–",
            "c) SF6",
            "d) PF5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The SF6 molecule is sp3d2 hybridised and the shape is regular octahedron.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Number of chlorine atoms which form equatorial bonds in PCl5 molecule are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In PCl5 molecule, three chlorine atoms which lie at an angle of 1200 in the same plane forms equatorial bonds and the other two atoms forms axial bonds at an angle of 900.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Due to unsymmetrical structure, the molecules having sp3d hybridisation are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) more stable and more reactive",
            "b) less stable and more reactive",
            "c) more stable and less reactive",
            "d) less stable and less reactive"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In sp3d hybridisation, due to its unsymmetrical structure the molecules are in the shape of trigonal bipyramidal which is less stable and more reactive.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "The bond angles in sp3d2 hybridisation is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 900",
            "b) 1200",
            "c) 109.50",
            "d) 1800"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the bond angles are equal in sp3d2 hybridisation i.e., 900.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "The percentage p-character in sp3  hybridisation is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 75%",
            "d) 66.67%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In sp3 hybridisation, s-character is 25% and p-character is 75%.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The hybridisation of BeF3- is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sp3",
            "b) sp",
            "c) sp2",
            "d) d2sp3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the hybridised orbital are equal in energy and shape. They are similar to each other and possess equal energy levels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "If the sign of the wave function is unchanged when the orbital is reflected about its centre, the orbital is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gerade",
            "b) Ungerade",
            "c) Gerade as well as Ungerade",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the sign of the wave function is unchanged when the orbital is reflected about its center (i.e., x, y and z are replaced by –x, -y and –z), the orbital is gerade.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "The filling of molecular orbital takes  place according to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The Aufbau Principle",
            "b) Pauli Exclusion Principle",
            "c) Hund’s  rule of maximum multiplicity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to these principles, molecular orbitals are filled in order of increasing energy. Two electrons in the same orbital cannot have the same set of all four quantum numbers identical."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Bond Order  of O2,  F2, N2 respectively are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) +1, +2, +3",
            "b) +2, +3, +1",
            "c) +2, +1, +3",
            "d) +3, +2, +1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bond Order=[[Number of electrons in bonding molecular orbital]-[Number of electrons in antibonding molecular orbital]]/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Arrange the following molecules in decreasing bond length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) O2  > O2–  > O2+  > O22-",
            "b) O22- > O2–  > O2 > O2+",
            "c) O22-  > O2–  > O2+  > O2",
            "d) O2–  > O2+  > O22-  > O2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bond length is inversely proportional to the bond order. Therefore, the correct is:\nO22-  > O2–  > O2  > O2+.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Arrange the following molecules in the order of increasing stability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) N2+ < N2 < N2– < N22-",
            "b) N22- < N2– < N2 < N2+",
            "c) N22-  < N2– = N2+ < N2",
            "d) N2 < N2+ = N2–  < N22-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The order of stability is directly proportional to the bond order. Therefore, the correct order of stability is N22-  < N2– = N2+ < N2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "On the basis of molecular orbital theory, select the most appropriate option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The bond order of O2 is 2.5 and it is paramagnetic",
            "b) The bond order of O2 is 1.5 and it is paramagnetic",
            "c) The bond order of O2 is 2 and it is diamagnetic",
            "d) The bond order of O2 is 2 and it is paramagnetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  d\nExplanation: Oxygen is paramagnetic in nature and its bond order is 2. It is an exceptional case.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which of the following molecule does not exist due to its zero bond order?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H2+",
            "b) He2+",
            "c) He2",
            "d) H2–"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Molecular orbital electronic configuration of He2 molecule = (σ1s)2 (σ*1s)2. Bond order = 0, so He2 molecule does not exist.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "According to Molecular Orbital Theory, the shape and size of a molecular orbital depends upon _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape and size of the combining atomic orbitals",
            "b) Numbers of the combining atomic orbitals",
            "c) Orientation of the combining atomic orbitals",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relative energies of molecular orbitals in increasing order have been found to be (σ1s) < (σ*1s) < (σ2s) < (σ*2s) < [(π2py)(π2pz)] < (σ2px) < [(π*2py)(π*2pz)] < (σ*2px) for H2 to N2 only.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) In bonding molecular orbital, electron density is low in the region between the nuclei of bonded atoms",
            "b) The energy of antibonding molecular orbital is higher than that of atomic orbitals from which it is formed",
            "c) Every electron in bonding molecular orbital contributes toward stability of the molecule",
            "d) Antibonding takes place when lobes of atomic orbitals have different signs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The shape and size of a molecular orbital depend upon the shape,  size, number and orientation of the combining atomic orbitals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Which of the following molecule is not homonuclear?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H2",
            "b) N2",
            "c) NO",
            "d) O2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: NO is Heteronuclear diatomic molecule in which atomic number of nitrogen is 7 and that of oxygen is 8 i.e., total number of electrons = 15.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Bond order of NO+ molecule is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2.5",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bond order = (10-4)/2 = 3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which of the following molecule is least stable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NO+",
            "b) N2",
            "c) NO",
            "d) O2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: In NO molecule there is a significant difference of about 250 kJ/mol in the energy of atomic orbitals involved.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "The molecular orbital electronic configuration of HF molecule is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1s2 2s2 σspx2 [2py2 2pz2] σspx*",
            "b) 1s2 2s2 σspx2 [2px2 2py2] σspx*",
            "c) 1s2 2s2 σspx2 [2px2 2pz2] σspx*",
            "d) 1s2 2s2 σspx2 [2px4] σspx*"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: HF molecule has 10 electrons and its electronic configuration is 1s2 2s2 σspx2 [2py2 2pz2] σspx*.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "From the following options, choose the heteronuclear diatomic molecules which are paramagnetic in nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HF and NO",
            "b) HF and O2",
            "c) NO and O2",
            "d) Only NO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: HF is diamagnetic in nature and O2 is homonuclear molecule. So, only NO is a heteronuclear diatomic molecule that is paramagnetic in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Calculate the number of σ and π bonds in cyclohexadiene. (C6H8)",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ bond =  2, π bond = 14",
            "b) σ bond =  14, π bond = 2",
            "c) σ bond =  12, π bond = 2",
            "d) σ bond =  12, π bond = 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cyclohexadiene molecule has two double bonds(hence two π-bonds) and one ring.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "The combination of H (1s1) and F (2px1) gives _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bonding orbital",
            "b) Antibonding orbital",
            "c) Both bonding and antibonding orbital",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The combination of H (1s1) and F (2px1) gives both bonding (σspx) and antibonding (σspx*) orbitals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Choose the incorrect  option from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Valence bond theory does not explain the paramagnetic nature of O2",
            "b) Molecular orbital theory explains the extra stability of O2+  cation over O2",
            "c) Valence bond theory explains the ionization or gain of electrons, giving O2+ and O2–  ions, if O2  has the stable octet",
            "d) Resonance has no role in Molecular orbital theory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Valence bond theory does not explain the ionization or gain of electrons, giving O2+ and O2–  ions, if O2 has the stable octet.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Which of the following molecules have bond order equal to 1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NO, HF, HCl, Li2, CO",
            "b) H2, Li2, B2, HF, HCl",
            "c) Li2, B2, CO, NO,He2+",
            "d) B2, CO, He2+, NO, HF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: He2+ = 0.5, H2, Li2, B2, HF, HCl = 1, NO = 2.5, CO = 3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "The interaction between a pair of orbitals of the same type is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attractive",
            "b) Repulsive",
            "c) There is no interaction",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The interaction between pair of orbitals of the same type is repulsive like between σ2s  and σ2p orbitals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "What are Stereoisomers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isomers having a same molecular formula and same configuration",
            "b) Isomers having a same molecular formula but different configuration",
            "c) Isomers having a different molecular formula but the same configuration",
            "d) Isomers having a different molecular formula and different configuration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stereoisomerism is exhibited by isomers having the same molecular formula but different configuration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "What are diastereomers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molecules with non-superimposable mirror images",
            "b) Molecules with superimposable mirror images",
            "c) Molecules which do not have non-superimposable mirror images",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Diastereomers are those stereomers which do not have non-superimposable mirror images.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which type of compounds cannot exhibit geometrical isomerism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Singly Bonded",
            "b) Doubly Bonded",
            "c) Triply Bonded",
            "d) Cyclic Compounds"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Triply bonded compounds cannot exhibit geometrical isomerism as the -C=C- bond in these molecules is linear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Choose the correct option from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A group gets priority if its atomic number is high",
            "b) When atoms attached to a double bond have same atomic number, the first atoms are considered",
            "c) A group gets priority if its atomic number is low",
            "d) Lone pair gets more priority and is ranked above hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: A group gets priority if its atomic number is high and When atoms attached to a double bond have same atomic number, the second atoms are considered.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "In which type of projection we can get staggered and eclipsed conformations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Newman Projection",
            "b) Sawhorse Projection",
            "c) Fischer Projection",
            "d) Wedge Projection"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: A sawhorse projection can reveal staggered and eclipsed conformations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Which of the following compounds have Z-configuration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CH3CH3CH2>C=C<HCH3",
            "b) HPh>C=C<COOHPh",
            "c) H2NCl>C=C<COOHBr",
            "d) CH3Ph>C=C<CH2CH3Br"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Trans-2-butene has two geometric isomers and this is E-configuration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect option from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fischer projections are two dimensional representations of three dimensional molecules",
            "b) A molecule is achiral if it cannot be superimposed on its mirror reflection",
            "c) E and Z notations are based on Cahn, Ingold and Prelog priority system",
            "d) Chiral molecules which are non-superimposable mirror images of each other are enantiomers"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: All the other options are in E-configuration. Only the second option shows the Z-configuration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "The cis-trans nomenclature is not applicable when _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The different groups attached to the carbon atom of double bond are same",
            "b) Atleast one of the group attached to each carbon atom is same",
            "c) The different groups attached to the carbon atom of double bond are not same",
            "d) The cis-trans nomenclature is applicable for all compounds"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: A molecule is achiral if it is superimposable on its mirror reflection. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "In glyceraldehydes, the complete sequence of priority is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) –OH > -CH2OH > -CHO > -H",
            "b) –H > -CH2OH > -CHO > -OH",
            "c) –H > –OH > -CH2OH > -CHO",
            "d) –OH > CHO > -CH2OH > -H"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The cis-trans nomenclature is applicable when the different groups attached to the carbon atom of double bond are same or atleast one of the group attached to each carbon atom is same.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a priority rule for R, S-Configuration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) If the four atoms attached to the chiral centre are all different, priority depends on atomic number, with the atom of lower atomic numbers getting lower priority",
            "b) If the two atoms attached to chiral centre are same, the atoms attached to each of these first atoms are compared",
            "c) When there is a double bond or triple bond, both atoms are considered to be duplicated or triplicated",
            "d) If the four atoms attached to the chiral centre are all different, priority depends on atomic number, with the atom of higher atomic numbers getting lower priority"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the four atoms attached to the chiral centre are all different, priority depends on atomic number, with the atom of lower atomic numbers getting lower priority.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "If our eyes travel in counter clockwise direction from the ligand of highest priority to the ligand of lowest priority, the configuration is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R-Configuration",
            "b) S-Configuration",
            "c) E-Configuration",
            "d) C-Configuration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In S-Configuration, our eyes travel in counter clockwise direction from the ligand of highest priority to the ligand of lowest priority.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "According to the selection rules, the decreasing order of preference is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) –NH2 > -C6H5 > -CH(CH3)2 > -H",
            "b) –CH(CH3)2 > -C6H5 > -H> -NH2",
            "c) –NH2 > -CH(CH3)2 > -C6H5 > -H",
            "d) -C6H5 > -CH(CH3)2 >–NH2 > -H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The atom of higher atomic numbers gets higher priority. So, –NH2 group has the highest priority of all.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "The process of removal of hardness of water, irrespective of whether it is temporary or permanent is termed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cleansing action of water",
            "b) Hardness of water",
            "c) Softening of water",
            "d) Purity of water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The process of removal of hardness of water, irrespective of whether it is temporary or permanent is termed as softening of water. This process includes both temporary as well as permanent hardness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "The external treatment of water does not include __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lime-soda process",
            "b) Sequestration",
            "c) Zeolites",
            "d) Ion-exchange process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The external treatments of water include lime-soda, zeolites and ion-exchange processes. It does not include sequestration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditioning method is not used in internal treatment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Colloidal",
            "b) Calgon",
            "c) Carbonate",
            "d) Bicarbonate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Colloidal, calgon, phosphate and carbonate conditioning methods are used in internal treatment. Bicarbonate is not used for this purpose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal treatment is carried out outside the boiler before water enters into the boiler",
            "b) Internal treatment methods are followed by blow-down operations",
            "c) Internal treatment is required in low pressure boilers",
            "d) Internal treatment is a corrective method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Internal treatment is carried out inside the boiler. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Potable water treatment does not involve __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disinfection",
            "b) Demineralisation",
            "c) Coagulation",
            "d) Sedimentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: External treatment is a preventive method and it is required in high pressure boilers. External treatment is carried out outside the boilers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "The exhausted anion exchangers can be regenerated by working with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acid solution",
            "b) Alcohol solution",
            "c) Alkali solution",
            "d) Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Potable water treatment does not involve demineralisation. It involves disinfection, coagulation and sedimentation processes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Chiral molecules are those which are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shows geometrical isomerism",
            "b) Superimposable on their mirror images",
            "c) Not superimposable on their mirror images",
            "d) Unstable molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chiral molecules are those which are not superimposable on their mirror images. The presence of an asymmetric carbon atom is one of several structural features that induce chirality in organic and inorganic molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of chiral object?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cylindrical helix",
            "b) Square box",
            "c) Sandal or shoe",
            "d) Glove"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A square box is not chiral as it gives super-imposable mirror image. All the other mentioned options does not give the super-imposable mirror images.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "For any given substance, the amount of rotation does not depends upon _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wavelength of light used",
            "b) Nature of the solvent",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For any given substance, the amount of rotation depends upon the concentration, nature of solvent, temperature, length of layer traversed and the wavelength of light used. It does not depend upon the pressure conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "The specific rotation is inversely proportional to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Observed rotation",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Concentration of solution",
            "d) D-line of sodium vapour light"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the rotation of the plane is clockwise, the substance is dextro rotatary. And if the rotation of the plane is anti-clockwise, the substance is leavo rotatary.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "0.5 g of an optically active compound was dissolved in 2mL of solvent at 250C. The solution was kept in a cell of length 10 cm and observed rotation was +100. What is the specific rotation of its enantiomer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -400",
            "b) +400",
            "c) -100",
            "d) +100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specific rotation is inversely proportional to the concentration of solution and length of sample tube.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "To avoid excessive high value of molecular rotation, concentration is taken as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 centi-mole/mL",
            "b) 1 milli-mole/mL",
            "c) 1 mole/mL",
            "d) 1 kilo-mole/mL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: [α] = α/lC = +100/(1*0.5/2) = +400.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Chiral molecules which are non-super-imposable mirror images of each other are called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diastereomers",
            "b) Meso compounds",
            "c) Racemic mixture",
            "d) Enantiomers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To avoid excessive high value of molecular rotation, concentration is taken as 1 centi-mole/mL.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enantiomer rotate plane of polarised light in opposite direction and to different extent",
            "b) Enantiomer rotate plane of polarised light in same direction but to different extent",
            "c) Enantiomer rotate plane of polarised light in same direction and to same extent",
            "d) Enantiomer rotate plane of polarised light in opposite direction but to same extent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chiral molecules which are non-superimposable mirror images of each other are called enantiomers. Enantiomer members often have different chemical reactions with other enantiomer substances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Enantiomerism is the phenomenon of existence of enantiomers in a single structural formula, in _________ configuration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same",
            "b) Opposite",
            "c) Same as well as opposite",
            "d) Initially opposite and then same"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Enantiomer rotate plane of polarised light in opposite direction but to same extent. Enantiomer members often have different chemical reactions with other enantiomer substances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The physical properties of enatiomers are identical",
            "b) In symmetrical environment, the chemical properties of enantiomers are identical",
            "c) The enantiomers react at same rate and form products in same amounts in assymetrical environment",
            "d) Enantiomers have different solubilities in the same chiral solvent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enantiomerism is the phenomenon of existence of enantiomers in a single structural formula but in opposite configuration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "The plane which divides the molecule into two equal parts so that each half is the mirror image of other half is called _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centre of symmetry",
            "b) Plane of symmetry",
            "c) Axis of symmetry",
            "d) Angle of symmetry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The enantiomers react at different rate and form products in different amounts in assymetrical environment. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "When a molecule has a plane of symmetry, it will be ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optically inactive",
            "b) Optically active",
            "c) Both optically active & inactive",
            "d) Enantiomer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Optical activity can also result from the lack of molecular symmetry in molecules which do not have chiral carbon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "A centre of symmetry is equivalent to _________ fold alternating axis of symmetry.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The plane divides the molecule into two equal parts so that each half is the mirror image of other half is called plane of symmetry. Centre of symmetry is the central point about which the molecule is symmetrical.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "Diastereomers are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geometrical isomers",
            "b) Mirror images",
            "c) Non-mirror images",
            "d) Unstable molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a molecule has a plane of symmetry, it will be optically inactive, even though it might contain chiral carbon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "A plane of symmetry is equivalent to _________ fold alternating axis of symmetry.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A centre of symmetry is equivalent to two-fold alternating axis of symmetry.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Racemic modification is an equimolar mixture of dextrorotatory and levorotatory isomers",
            "b) Meso compounds contain more than one chiral carbon centre",
            "c) Meso compounds are externally compensated",
            "d) Racemic mixture is designated as dl-pair"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Optical activity is the property in which a substance is able to rotate the plane of polarisation of plane polarised light.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meso compound possess both plane of symmetry and centre of symmetry",
            "b) Meso compound possess either plane or centre of symmetry",
            "c) Meso compound does not possess either plane or centre of symmetry",
            "d) Meso compounds are externally compensated form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Meso compounds are internally compensated form whereas racemic mixtures are externally compensated modification. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "How many optical isomers are possible in a compound with one chiral carbon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Meso compound possess either plane or centre of symmetry. They do not possess both plane of symmetry and centre of symmetry and also they are internally compensated form.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Which of the following compound would show optical isomerism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CH3 – CH(OH) COOH",
            "b) H2N CH(CH3)2",
            "c) (CH3)2 CHCHO",
            "d) H2N CH2 COOH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A compound with one chiral carbon has three optical isomers (+), (-) and (±).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "The number of configurational isomers of molecules having (n) different chiral carbons is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2n",
            "b) 2n",
            "c) 2n-1",
            "d) 2n+1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CH3 – CH(OH) COOH will show optical isomerism as it possess chiral carbon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "The number of racemic forms of molecules having (n) different chiral carbons is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2n",
            "b) 2n",
            "c) 2n-1",
            "d) 2n+1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of configurational isomers of molecules having (n) different chiral carbons is 2n. It is calculated mathematically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "For a molecule with two like chiral carbon atoms, the number of optically inactive form is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The number of racemic forms of molecules having (n) different chiral carbons is 2n-1 whereas the number of configurational isomers of molecules having (n) different chiral carbons is 2n.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "For a molecule with two like chiral carbon atoms, the number of optically active form is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a molecule with two like chiral carbon atoms, the number of optically inactive form is one. This is always used for the calculation of optically inactive forms.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Find the number of stereoisomers for CH3 – CHOH – CH = CH – CH3.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a molecule with two like chiral carbon atoms, the number of optically active form is two. This is always used for the calculation of optically active forms.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "The sufficient condition for showing optical activity is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molecule should have measurable amount of optical activity only",
            "b) Polarimeter should have capacity of recording low-degree optical activity only",
            "c) Chirality of molecule as a whole only",
            "d) Both, the molecule should have measurable amount of optical activity and polarimeter should have capacity of recording low-degree optical activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The number of stereoisomers for CH3 – CHOH – CH = CH – CH3 is four. This is calculated by the formula 2n+1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of optically active compounds without chirality?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tartaric acid",
            "b) Sulfhonium salt",
            "c) Diphenic acid",
            "d) Glyceraldehyde"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The necessary condition for showing optical activity is the chirality of a molecule as a whole. It is the most important condition for showing optical activity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not optically active compound?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1,7- Dicarboxylic spirocycloheptane",
            "b) 1,3- Diphenyl propadiene",
            "c) Meso-tartaric acid",
            "d) Glyceraldehyde"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The molecule should have measurable amount of optical activity and polarimeter should have capacity of recording low-degree optical activity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "The reaction which gives exclusively one of several possible isomeric products is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamicselective",
            "b) Stereoselective",
            "c) Regioselective",
            "d) Stereospecific"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reaction which gives exclusively one of several possible isomeric products is called regioselective reaction. Regioselectivity is the preference of one direction of chemical bond making or breaking over all other possible directions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "The reaction that yields predominantly one enantiomer of a possible pair is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamicselective",
            "b) Stereoselective",
            "c) Regioselective",
            "d) Stereospecific"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reaction that yields predominantly one enantiomer of a possible pair is called stereoselective reaction. Stereoselectivity is the property of a chemical reaction in which a single reactant forms an unequal mixture of stereo isomers during the non-stereo specific creation of a new stereo center or during the non-stereo specific transformation of a pre-existing one.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "The reaction in which stereochemically different molecules react differently is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamicselective",
            "b) Stereoselective",
            "c) Regioselective",
            "d) Stereospecific"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stereoselectivity can be exhibited in various degrees like completely stereoselective, highly stereoselective, moderately stereoselective and so on.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of regioselective reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Debromination of 2,3- dibromobutane",
            "b) 2-bromo octane with sodium hydroxide",
            "c) Addition of HI to propylene",
            "d) Debromination of meso dibromobutane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reaction in which stereochemically different molecules react differently is called stereospecific reaction. Stereospecificity is the property of a reaction mechanism that leads to different stereo isomeric reaction products from different stereo isomeric reactants, or which operates on only one of the stereo isomers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Reaction of (±) 2,3- dibromobutane is slower than meso in which the two methyl groups are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skew",
            "b) Anti",
            "c) Gauche",
            "d) Partially eclipsed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Addition of HI to propylene is an example of regioselective reaction. Regioselectivity is the preference of one direction of chemical bond making or breaking over all other possible directions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "R – C = C – R reacts in the presence of lindlar catalyst to give a syn product. This is an example of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamicselective",
            "b) Stereoselective",
            "c) Regioselective",
            "d) Stereospecific"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reaction of (±) 2,3- dibromobutane is slower than meso due to higher transition state in which the two methyl groups are partially eclipsed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Under SN2 conditions, on reaction with NaOH, (R)-2-bromo octane gives ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (S)-2-octanol",
            "b) (R)-2-octanol",
            "c) Trans-2-butene",
            "d) Cis-2-butene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dynamic stereochemistry helps in correlating conformation and reactivity and in stereoselective synthesis. Stereoselectivity is the property of a chemical reaction in which a single reactant forms an unequal mixture of stereo isomers during the non-stereo specific creation of a new stereo center\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Under SN2 conditions, on reaction with NaOH, (S)-2-bromo octane gives (R)-2-octanol. This is an example of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamicselective",
            "b) Stereoselective",
            "c) Regioselective",
            "d) Stereospecific"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The above mentioned reaction is an example of stereoselective reaction. Stereoselectivity is the property of a chemical reaction in which a single reactant forms an unequal mixture of stereo isomers during the non-stereo specific creation of a new stereo center\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Optical purity is defined as the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ratio of rotation of pure enantiomer to rotation of mixture",
            "b) Ratio of rotation of mixture to rotation of pure enantiomer",
            "c) Product of rotation of mixture and rotation of pure enantiomer",
            "d) Sum of rotation of mixture and rotation of pure enantiomer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under SN2 conditions, on reaction with NaOH, (R)-2-bromo octane gives (S)-2- octanol. In SN2 mechanism, one bond is broken and one bond is formed synchronously.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "The formula of enantiomeric excess is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) [(d+l)/(d-l)]*100",
            "b) [(d)/(d+l)]*100",
            "c) [(d-l)/(d)]*100",
            "d) [(d-l)/(d+l)]*100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Under SN2 conditions, on reaction with NaOH, (S)-2-bromo octane gives (R)-2-octanol. This is an example of stereospecific reaction. In SN2 mechanism, one bond is broken and one bond is formed synchronously.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Conformations are different arrangements of atoms that can be converted into one another by rotation about ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Covalent bond",
            "b) Double bond",
            "c) Single bond",
            "d) Triple bond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Conformational isomerism is a form of stereoisomerism in which the isomers can be interconverted exclusively by rotations about formally single bonds. Such isomers are generally referred to as conformational isomers or conformers and, specifically, as rotamers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "The energy required to rotate n-butane molecule about the carbon-carbon bond is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotational energy",
            "b) Torsional energy",
            "c) Enantiomeric energy",
            "d) Potential energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The energy required to rotate n-butane molecule about the carbon-carbon bond is called torsional energy. Torsion energy can be used to solve problems of general relativity especially the singularity problem.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "The rotation about the (C2 – C3) carbon-carbon bond of n-butane requires the energy of about ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 kJ/mol",
            "b) 50 kJ/mol",
            "c) 10 kJ/mol",
            "d) 3 kJ/mol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rotation about the (C2 – C3) carbon-carbon bond of n-butane requires the very less energy of about 3kJ/mol. It requires very less amount of energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "The infinity of intermediate conformations are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skew conformations",
            "b) Staggered conformations",
            "c) Eclipsed conformations",
            "d) Gauche"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The infinity of intermediate conformations are called skew conformations. Three conformations of cyclohexane, designated as chair, boat, and skew (or twist), are essentially free of angle strain.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "The potential energy of n-butane is minimum for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skew conformations",
            "b) Staggered conformations",
            "c) Eclipsed conformations",
            "d) Gauche"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The potential energy of n-butane is minimum for staggered conformations. It is because of no steric hindrance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "The potential energy of n-butane is maximum for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Skew conformations",
            "b) Staggered conformations",
            "c) Eclipsed conformations",
            "d) Gauche"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The potential energy of n-butane is maximum for eclipsed conformations. It is because of overlapping of functional groups.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "The relative instability of any of the intermediate skew conformations is due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lateral strain",
            "b) Shear strain",
            "c) Longitudinal strain",
            "d) Torsional strain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The relative instability of any of the intermediate skew conformations is due to torsional strain. Torsion energy can be used to solve problems of general relativity especially the singularity problem.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "In gauche conformations, the methyl groups are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600 apart",
            "b) 900 apart",
            "c) 1800 apart",
            "d) 3600 apart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In gauche conformations, the methyl groups are 600 apart. In general a gauche rotamer is less stable than an anti-rotamer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Gauche conformation is less stable due to _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen bonding",
            "b) Covalent bonding",
            "c) Vander Waal’s repulsion",
            "d) Torsional strain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both anti and gauche conformations are free of torsional strain. In general, a gauche rotamer is less stable than an anti-rotamer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which of the following is least stable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anti conformation",
            "b) Gauche conformation",
            "c) Staggered conformation",
            "d) Eclipsed conformation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gauche conformation is less stable due to Vander Waal’s repulsion. Vander Waal’s are weak forces of attraction which results in lesser stability of gauche conformer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "Based on the important category, concrete and fibre glass are the examples of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ceramics",
            "b) Polymers",
            "c) Composites",
            "d) Semi-conductors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Example of ceramic are Al2O3 and ZrO2, Polymers are Thermoplastic and Thermosets, Composites are Fibre glass and Concrete and Semi-conductors are Silicon and Germanium.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an inorganic functional material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ferroelectric",
            "b) Reverse micelles",
            "c) Magnetic field sensor",
            "d) Light detectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reverse micelles is an organic functional material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an aerospace material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plastics",
            "b) Silica",
            "c) Aluminium alloys",
            "d) Polymers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Polymers are not categorized under aerospace materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metals are extremely good conductors of heat and electricity",
            "b) The properties of metal degrade rapidly with temperature",
            "c) Metals have poor corrosion resistant",
            "d) A polished metal surface has a dull appearance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A polished metal surface has a lustrous appearance. All the other options are correct. Metals are extremely good conductors of heat and electricity, its properties degrade rapidly with temperature and have poor corrosion resistance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is the best heat and corrosion resistant material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metals",
            "b) Ceramics",
            "c) Polymers",
            "d) Semi-conductors"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ceramics materials generally consist of oxides, nitrides, carbides, silicates or borides of various metals. Their heat and corrosion resistance is best compared to metals and polymers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Polymers are used in the chemical industry because of their ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inert nature",
            "b) Light weight",
            "c) Low cost",
            "d) Easiness in fabricability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polymers are used in the chemical industry because of their inert nature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Composites are optically opaque materials",
            "b) Carbon fiber reinforced composite materials are not used in space vehicles",
            "c) Re-cyclability of composite material is poor",
            "d) Processing of composite material is difficult"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbon fiber reinforced composite materials are used in space vehicles. All the other options are correct. Composites are optically opaque materials, re-cyclability of composite material is poor and its processing is difficult.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which type of material expands and contract in response to an applied electric field?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Advanced material",
            "b) Smart material",
            "c) Biomaterial",
            "d) Nanomaterial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Smart materials(Piezoelectric) expand and contract in response to an applied electric field(or voltage).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is non-linear material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zirconium oxide",
            "b) Magnetite",
            "c) Maghemite",
            "d) Lithium niobate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lithium niobate is a non-linear material used for telecommunication.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of nanomaterials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TV and computer monitors",
            "b) Cardiology",
            "c) Magnetic  Resonance Imaging (MRI)",
            "d) Sunscreens and fuel cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cardiology is not an application of nanomaterials. TV and computer monitors, Magnetic  Resonance Imaging (MRI) and sunscreens and fuel cells are some of the applications of nanomaterials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Which type of cement possesses hydraulic qualities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Natural",
            "b) Puzzolona",
            "c) Slag",
            "d) Portland"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Natural cement possesses hydraulic qualities. The fast-setting Rosendale natural cement mortars proved to be more efficient than the mortars based on lime and sand.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Puzzolona is the oldest cement invented by Romans",
            "b) Natural puzzolona is deposit of volcanic ash",
            "c) Puzzolona was used in making concrete for the construction of walls and domes",
            "d) Puzzolona is quite setting cement and posses relatively low strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Natural cement is quite setting cement and posses relatively low strength. All the other options are correct. Puzzolona is the oldest cement invented by Romans, used in making concrete for the construction of walls and domes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Blast furnace slag is the mixture of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slaked lime and calcium silicate",
            "b) Aluminium silicate and hydrated lime",
            "c) Calcium silicate and aluminium silicate",
            "d) Silica, alumina and calcium oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blast furnace slag is the mixture of Calcium silicate and aluminium silicate. Ground-granulated blast-furnace slag is obtained by quenching molten iron slag (a by-product of iron and steel-making) from a blast furnace in water or steam, to produce a glassy, granular product that is then dried and ground into a fine powder.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Portland cement is made by calcining at temperature equals to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30000C",
            "b) 15000C",
            "c) 18000C",
            "d) 20000C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Portland cement is made by calcining at temperature equals to 15000C. It is manufactured from chalk and clay which hardens under water and when hard resembles Portland stone in color.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "Why Gypsum is added after calcination in the manufacture of Portland cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To prevent flash setting",
            "b) To improve the quality of cement",
            "c) To increase the lime saturation factor",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gypsum is added after calcination to prevent the flash setting and it acts as a retarder.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "Who is recognized as the “Father of the modern Portland cement industry”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emil Abderhalden",
            "b) Richard Abegg",
            "c) Peter Agre",
            "d) William Aspdin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: William Aspdin is recognized as the “Father of the modern Portland cement industry”. Portland cement is the most common type of cement in general use around the world, used as a basic ingredient of concrete, mortar, stucco, and most non-speciality grout.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "All portland cements are hydraulic cement because they ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set and harden in the absence of water",
            "b) Set and harden in the presence of water",
            "c) Do not harden after mixing water",
            "d) None of the mentioned option"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All portland cements are hydraulic cements because they set and harden under water. This cement not only hardens by reacting with water but also forms a water-resistant product. Portland cement is the most common type of cement in general use around the world, used as a basic ingredient of concrete, mortar, stucco, and most non-speciality grout.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "The percentage composition of alumina in Portland cement is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60-69",
            "b) 17-25",
            "c) 3-8",
            "d) 2-4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The percentage composition of alumina in portland cement is 3-8 %. Portland cement clinker is a hydraulic material which shall consist of at least two-thirds by mass of calcium silicates, the remainder consisting of aluminium and iron-containing clinker phases and other compounds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which compound causes the cement efflorescent, if present in excess?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron oxide",
            "b) Alkali oxide",
            "c) Sulphur trioxide",
            "d) Lime"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Alkali oxides causes cement efflorescent if present in excess. The alkali metals react with oxygen to form several different compounds: suboxides, oxides, peroxides, superoxides, and ozonides.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Which compound imparts grey color, strength and hardness to the portland cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Iron oxide",
            "b) Alumina",
            "c) Magnesium oxide",
            "d) Silica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Iron oxide imparts grey color, strength and hardness to the portland cement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitinol is a non-magnetic material",
            "b) It has a shape memory strain of about 8.5%",
            "c) It has lower ductility than other shape memory alloys like Au-Cd",
            "d) It possess excellent corrosion resistant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nitinol has a higher ductility than other shape memory alloys like Au-Cd and can freely revert back to its original shape. All the other options are correct. It is a non-magnetic material and possess excellent corrosion resistant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "The materials which offer no resistance to the passage of electricity are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superconductors",
            "b) Semiconductors",
            "c) Optical fibre",
            "d) Smart material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Superconductors offer no resistance to the passage of electricity. Semi-conductor is a substance, usually a solid chemical element or compound, that can conduct electricity under some conditions but not others, making it a good medium for the control of electrical current.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "The critical temperature for the cuprate La2CuO4 is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 K",
            "b) 90 K",
            "c) 125 K",
            "d) 35 K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The critical temperature for the cuprate La2CuO4 is 35 K. Cuprate loosely refers to a material that can be viewed as containing copper anions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Identify the class of the superconductor to which TiO and NbO belong.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simple compounds",
            "b) Nonstoichiometric crystals having defects",
            "c) Charge-transfer compounds",
            "d) Molecular crystals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TiO and NbO are the examples of non-stoichiometric crystals having defects class of superconductors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "The dielectric material that shows spontaneous and reversible dielectric polarisation are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Piezoelectrics",
            "b) Pyroelectrics",
            "c) Ferroelectrics",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Piezoelctrics are those dielectric materials in which pressure can produce an electrical response and electrical forces produce a mechanical response. Pyroelectrics are those dielectric in which polarisation changes with temperature. Ferroelectrics are those dielectric materials that show spontaneous and reversible dielectric polarisation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "What is the principle on which an optical fibre works?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total internal reflection",
            "b) Farraday’s law of induction",
            "c) Doppler Effect",
            "d) Hooke’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to total internal reflection, light can be transmitted over many kilometers without any appreciable decrease in the intensity by optical fibres.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Optical fibre can be safely used for signal transmission near the nuclear installation because ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) There is no leakage of signals",
            "b) Plastic cladded silica fibres are resistant to nuclear radiations",
            "c) Plastic cladded silica fibres are not resistant to nuclear radiations",
            "d) There is no electromagnetic interference"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Optical fibre can be safely used for signal transmission near the nuclear installation because the plastic cladded silica fibres are resistant to nuclear radiation. Due to total internal reflection, light can be transmitted over many kilometers without any appreciable decrease in the intensity of optical fibres.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "The correct sequence for the procedure adopted for making a pure elemental semiconductor consist of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preparation of ultrapure Si or Ge >> Doping >> Preparation of single crystals of Si or Ge",
            "b) Doping >> Preparation of ultrapure Si or Ge >> Preparation of single crystals of Si or Ge",
            "c) Preparation of ultrapure Si or Ge >> Preparation of single crystals of Si or Ge >> Doping",
            "d) Preparation of single crystals of Si or Ge >> Preparation of ultrapure Si or Ge >> Doping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct sequence for the procedure adopted for making a pure elemental semiconductor consist of: Preparation of ultrapure Si or Ge>>  Preparation of single crystals of Si or Ge>> Doping\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of a transistor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tunnel diodes",
            "b) Thermistors",
            "c) Amplifiers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the mentioned options are the applications of a transistor. A transistor is a semiconductor device used to amplify or switch electronic signals and electrical power. It is used for tunnel diodes, thermistors and amplifiers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The amplification factor for transistor when used as an amplifier will be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 75",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The amplification factor for transistor when used as an amplifier will be 50. Modern transistor audio amplifiers of up to a few hundred watts are common and relatively inexpensive.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a microscopic property?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reactivity",
            "b) Inter-molecular force",
            "c) Boiling point",
            "d) Kinetic energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Inter-molecular force is a microscopic property and all others are the macroscopic property. A macroscopic property describes the characteristics or behaviour of a sample which is large enough to see, handle, manipulate, weigh, etc. A microscopic property describes the behaviour of a much smaller sample of matter, an atom or molecule for instance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the highest bond dissociation energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Covalent bond",
            "b) Vander Waals forces",
            "c) Dipole-dipole",
            "d) Hydrogen bond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Covalent Bond has the highest dissociation energy (400 kJ/mol) among the following options. Vander Waal’s forces are the weakest among the following.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "The strength of Vander Waals forces depends upon ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size of the molecule",
            "b) Molecular structure",
            "c) Number of electrons present in the molecule",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The strength of Vander Waals forces depends upon the size of the molecule, molecular structure and the number of electrons present in the molecule.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Arrange the following molecules in the order of increasing boiling point.",
        "Options": [
            "a) I2 < Br2 < Cl2 < F2",
            "b) F2 < Cl2 < Br2 < I2",
            "c) F2 < Br2 < Cl2 < I2",
            "d) Cl2 < F2 < I2 < Br2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct order of boiling point is F2 < Cl2 < Br2 < I2.\nIt is due to the highest electronegativity of fluorine atom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Hydrogen bonding is maximum in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diethyl ether",
            "b) Ethyl chloride",
            "c) Ethanol",
            "d) Triethylamine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hydrogen bonding is maximum in Ethanol. It is a volatile, flammable, colorless liquid with a slight chemical odor. It is used as an antiseptic, a solvent, a fuel, and due to its low freezing point, the active fluid in many alcohol thermometers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a necessary condition for the formation of intra-molecular hydrogen bonding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A 5 or 6-membered ring should be formed",
            "b) The ring should be planar",
            "c) There should be minimum strain during the ring closure",
            "d) There should be maximum strain during the ring closure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The necessary conditions for the formation of intra-molecular hydrogen bonding are:  5 or 6-membered ring should be formed, the ring should be planar and there should be minimum strain during the ring closure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the consequence of hydrogen bonding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abnormal boiling point",
            "b) Solubility and Viscosity",
            "c) Azeotropic behavior",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The consequences of hydrogen bonding are: Abnormal boiling point, solubility, viscosity and azeotropic behavior.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "O-nitrophenol is more volatile than p-nitrophenol due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductive effect",
            "b) Electromeric effect",
            "c) Inter-molecular hydrogen bonding in O-nitrophenol",
            "d) Intra-molecular hydrogen bonding in O-nitrophenol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: O-nitrophenol is more volatile than p-nitrophenol due to Intra-molecular hydrogen bonding in O-nitrophenol. Intra-molecular hydrogen bonding occurs within different parts of a single molecule.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Which of the following possess lowest energy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NO",
            "b) O2",
            "c) N2",
            "d) CO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: N2 possesses the lowest bond energy among the following options.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "At what temperature does the water molecules contract?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At 00C",
            "b) Below 00C",
            "c) At 40C",
            "d) Between 00C and 40C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Water contracts when heated between 00C and 40C. In this range of temperature, all the water molecules breaks down to change its state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "The main cause of molecular aggregation is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conduction",
            "b) Induction",
            "c) Inter-molecular interactions",
            "d) Resonance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The main cause of molecular aggregation is inter-molecular interactions. Inter-molecular interactions stem from the electric properties of atoms. Being the cause of molecular aggregation, inter-molecular forces are at the roots of chemistry and are the fabric of the world.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "From where does the inter-molecular interaction originate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) From the electric properties of atoms",
            "b) From the cohesive properties of atoms",
            "c) From the magnetic properties of atoms",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inter-molecular interactions originate from the electric properties of atoms. Inter-molecular interactions stem from the electric properties of atoms. Being the cause of molecular aggregation, inter-molecular forces are at the roots of chemistry and are the fabric of the world.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a state of aggregation of matter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid",
            "b) Liquid and Gas",
            "c) Plasma",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Solid, liquid, gas and plasma are the four states of aggregation of matter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "The process by which individual molecules form the defined aggregate is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Self-aggregation",
            "b) Self-assembly",
            "c) Aggregation",
            "d) Assembly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The process by which individual molecules form the defined aggregate is called self-assembly. Molecular self-assembly is the process by which molecules adopt a defined arrangement without guidance or management from an outside source.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "In water, non-polar molecules tend to aggregate because they are forced to come into close proximity with each other due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrophobic  interactions",
            "b) Hydrophilic  interactions",
            "c) Vander Waals  interactions",
            "d) Electrovalent  interactions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In water, non-polar molecules tend to aggregate because they are forced to come into close proximity with each other due to hydrophobic interactions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "Which type of molecules forms aggregate through a self-assembly process that is driven by the hydrophobic effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrophilic",
            "b) Nucleophilic",
            "c) Ambiphilic",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ambiphilic molecules form aggregate through a self-assembly process that is driven by the hydrophobic effect. Molecular self-assembly is the process by which molecules adopt a defined arrangement without guidance or management from an outside source.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Why metallic bonds are non-directional?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because there is a uniform distribution of mobile valence electrons around the kernels",
            "b) Because there is a non-uniform distribution of mobile valence electrons around the kernels",
            "c) There is no change in inter-kernel distance",
            "d) There is a change in inter-kernel distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Metallic bonds are non-directional because there is a uniform distribution of mobile valence electrons around the kernels, provided there is no change in inter-kernel distance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "The number of molecules in a conduction band ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases with fall in temperature",
            "b) Decreases with a rise in temperature",
            "c) Increases with a rise in temperature",
            "d) Does not depend upon the temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The number of molecules in the conduction band increases with the rise in temperature. At high temperatures, randomness increases and more molecules move towards the conduction band.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "What is the molecular formula of stearate ion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C17H35COO–",
            "b) C35H17COO+",
            "c) C35H17COO–",
            "d) C17H35COO+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sodium stearate ionises to form stearate anion(C17H35COO–) and sodium cation(Na+).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "Which part of the stearate ion is hydrophilic in nature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tail",
            "b) Hydrocarbon chain",
            "c) Head",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The end of the hydrocarbon chain is having a polar group (head) which is hydrophilic in nature and represented by a hollow circle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which of the following is water insoluble?",
        "Options": [
            "a) COO–",
            "b) Na+",
            "c) C17H35",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: C17H35 is hydrophobic in nature and hence it is water insoluble.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The number of stearate ions required to form a micelle of colloidal size is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 60",
            "c) 70",
            "d) 80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: About 70 stearate ions aggregate to form a micelle of colloidal size.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the micelle formation, the water soluble heads are directed towards the centre",
            "b) In the micelle formation, the water soluble heads are on the surface in contact with the water",
            "c) In the micelle formation, the water insoluble tails are directed towards the centre",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the micelle formation, the water insoluble tails are directed towards the centre, and the water soluble heads are on the surface in contact with water. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The soap micelle is unstable due to positive charge on its head",
            "b) The soap micelle is stable due to positive charge on its head",
            "c) The soap micelle is unstable due to negative charge on its head",
            "d) The soap micelle is stable due to negative charge on its head"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The soap micelle is stable due to the negative charge on its polar head. In the micelle formation, the water insoluble tails are directed towards the centre, and the water soluble heads are on the surface in contact with water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "The transition of ions to micelle is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reversible",
            "b) Irreversible",
            "c) All of the mentioned",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transition of ions to micelle is a reversible process. In the micelle formation, the water insoluble tails are directed towards the centre, and the water soluble heads are on the surface in contact with water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "What is Critical Micelle Concentration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The maximum amount of concentration that is required for the formation of micelle",
            "b) The minimum amount of concentration that is required for the formation of micelle",
            "c) The maximum amount of concentration that is not required for the formation of micelle",
            "d) The minimum amount of concentration that is not required for the formation of micelle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum amount of concentration that is required for the formation of the micelle is termed as Critical Micelle Concentration (CMC). It is defined as the concentration of surfactants above which micelles form and all additional surfactants added to the system go to micelles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Micelles behave as colloids only when?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration is less than CMC",
            "b) Concentration is equal to CMC",
            "c) Concentration is greater than CMC",
            "d) They always behave as colloids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Micelles behave as colloids only when its concentration is greater than CMC. The CMC is an important characteristic of a surfactant. Before reaching the CMC, the surface tension changes strongly with the concentration of the surfactant. After reaching the CMC, the surface tension remains relatively constant or changes with a lower slope.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "The conductivity of micelles is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher than a colloidal solution",
            "b) Lower than a colloidal solution",
            "c) Equals to colloidal solution",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conductivity of micelles is higher than the colloidal solution. And hence they can conduct more electric charges through them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of top-down approach for the preparation of nanomaterials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas phase agglomeration",
            "b) Molecular self-assembly",
            "c) Mechanical grinding",
            "d) Molecular beam epitaxy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mechanical grinding is an example of top-down approach for the preparation of nanomaterials. All the other options are the example of bottom-up approach.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of bottom-up approach for the preparation of nanomaterials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Etching",
            "b) Dip pen nano-lithography",
            "c) Lithography",
            "d) Erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dip pen nanolithography is an example of bottom-down approach for the preparation of nanomaterials. All the other options are the example of top-down approach.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The properties like melting point, solubility, color, etc changes on varying the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size",
            "b) Composition",
            "c) Surface properties",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The properties like melting point, solubility, color, etc changes on varying the size of the particles. These all are the physical properties and depends upon the physical characteristics of the particle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "The properties like dispersibility, conductivity, etc changes on varying the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size",
            "b) Composition",
            "c) Surface properties",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The properties like dispersibility, conductivity, etc changes on varying the surface properties of the nanoparticle. These all are the chemical properties and depend upon the surface characteristics of the particle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Quantum confinement results in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy gap in semiconductor is proportional to the inverse of the square root of the size",
            "b) Energy gap in semiconductor is proportional to the inverse of the size",
            "c) Energy gap in semiconductor is proportional to the square of size",
            "d) Energy gap in semiconductor is proportional to the inverse of the square of size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The energy gap in a semiconductor is proportional to the inverse of the square of the size. This effect is a result of quantum confinement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the principal factor which causes the properties of nanomaterials to differ significantly from other materials?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Size distribution",
            "b) Specific surface feature",
            "c) Quantum size effects",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Size distribution, specific surface feature and quantum size effects are the principal factor which causes the properties of nanomaterials to differ significantly from other materials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Self-assembly is a top-down manufacturing technique",
            "b) In self-assembly, weak interactions play very important role",
            "c) Self-assembling molecules adopt an organised structure which is thermodynamically more stable than the single, unassembled components",
            "d) Compared to the isolated components, the self-assembled structure has a higher order"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Self-assembly is a bottom-down manufacturing technique. All the other options are correct. In self-assembly, weak interactions play very important role, self-assembling molecules adopt an organised structure which is thermodynamically more stable than the single, unassembled components.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the application of nanotechnology to food science and technology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agriculture",
            "b) Food safety and biosecurity",
            "c) Product development",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The application of nanotechnology to food science and technology are agriculture, food safety and biosecurity, product development, food processing and ingredient technologies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "What are the advantages of nano-composite packages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lighter and biodegradable",
            "b) Enhanced thermal stability, conductivity and mechanical strength",
            "c) Gas barrier properties",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The advantages of nano-composite packages are-Lighter and biodegradable, enhanced thermal stability, conductivity, mechanical strength and gas barrier properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "The efficiency of today’s best solar cell is about ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15-20%",
            "b) 40%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The efficiency of today’s best solar cells is about 40%. A solar cell or photovoltaic cell is an electrical device that converts the energy of light directly into electricity by the photovoltaic effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a common method used for purification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sublimation",
            "b) Crystallisation",
            "c) Electrolysis",
            "d) Chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sublimation, crystallisation, distillation, differential extraction and chromatography are some of the common methods used for purification. Electrolysis process is not used for this purpose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Crystallisation is based on the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference in melting point",
            "b) Difference in boiling point",
            "c) Difference in pressure",
            "d) Difference in solubility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Crystallisation is based on the difference in the solubility of the compound and the impurities in a suitable solvent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the example of crystallisation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purification of alum",
            "b) Purification of sea water",
            "c) Separation of gases from air",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: An impure sample of alum or copper sulphate is purified by crystallisation process. Purification of sea water is example of distillation process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "At room temperature, the impure compound in crystallisation is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soluble",
            "b) Sparingly soluble",
            "c) Insoluble",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The impure compound is sparingly soluble in a solvent at room temperature but appreciably soluble at higher temperatures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as mother liquor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solvent",
            "b) Solute",
            "c) Solution",
            "d) Filtrate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The filtrate is also known as mother liquor. A mother liquor is the part of a solution that is left over after crystallization. It is encountered in chemical processes including sugar refining.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "The solution of impure compound and solvent is concentrated to get ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unsaturated solution",
            "b) Undersaturaed solution",
            "c) Saturated solution",
            "d) Oversaturated solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The solution of impure compound and solvent is concentrated to get a saturated solution. The solution is filtered to remove insoluble impurities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Insoluble impurities from solution during crystallization are removed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drying",
            "b) Filtration",
            "c) Heating",
            "d) Cooling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Insoluble impurities from solution during crystallization are removed by filtration. The solution is filtered to remove insoluble impurities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "The solution which is obtained after filtration is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Suspended solution",
            "b) Clear solution",
            "c) Colloidal solution",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The solution which is obtained after filtration is a clear solution. The solution is filtered to remove insoluble impurities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Crystal phases can be inter-converted by varying ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Size",
            "d) Viscosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Crystal phases can be inter-converted by varying factors such as temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "The nature of the crystallization process is governed by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermodynamics",
            "b) Kinetic factors",
            "c) Thermodynamics and Kinetic factors",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The nature of the crystallization process is governed by both thermodynamic and kinetic factors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "The unit of surface tension in the CGS system is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) N/m",
            "b) Kg/cm",
            "c) Dynes/cm",
            "d) Dynes/m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The unit of surface tension in CGS system is dynes/cm. It is N/m in S.I. system. Surface tension is the elastic tendency of a fluid surface which makes it acquire the least surface area possible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "The apparatus used for the determination of surface tension of a liquid is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oedometer",
            "b) Stalagmometer",
            "c) Consolidometer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The apparatus used for the determination of surface tension of a liquid is called stalagmometer. It is equivalent to force per unit length.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Stalagmometer is cleaned to remove grease with the help of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromic acid",
            "b) Sulphuric acid",
            "c) Distilled water",
            "d) Tartaric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Stalagmometer is cleaned to remove grease with the help of chromic acid. It is used for the determination of surface tension.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "The surface tension of water at 250C is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90.0 dynes/cm",
            "b) 45.63 dynes/cm",
            "c) 82.5 dynes/cm",
            "d) 72.14 dynes/cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The surface tension of water at 250C is 72.14 dynes/cm. It is a standard value.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "On increasing the temperature, the kinetic energy of the liquid molecules ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains constant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On increasing the temperature, the kinetic energy of the liquid molecules also increases. At high temperatures, randomness increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "In case of water and glass, we get a concave meniscus because the adhesive force between water and glass are _______________ than the cohesive forces between water molecules.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weaker",
            "b) Stronger",
            "c) Same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of water and glass, we get a concave meniscus because the adhesive force between water and glass are stronger than the cohesive forces between water molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Shapes of drops of liquid are spherical because of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity",
            "b) Conductivity",
            "c) Absorption",
            "d) Surface tension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Shapes of drops of liquid are spherical because of surface tension as it reduces the surface area to a minimum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) In case of mercury and glass, we observe a convex meniscus",
            "b) Surface tension is responsible for the rise and fall of the capillary tubes",
            "c) If two drops encounter each other, they tend to repel each other",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If two drops encounter each other, they tend to coalesce into a large drop. All the other options are correct. In the case of mercury and glass, we observe a convex meniscus and Surface tension is responsible for the rise and fall of the capillary tubes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "On increasing the temperature, the surface tension of the liquid ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains constant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On increasing the temperature, the surface tension of the liquid decreases. It is inversely proportional to the temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of surface tension?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Use of soaps and detergents as cleansing agents",
            "b) Molecular structure can be elucidated by surface tension measurements through parachor values",
            "c) Surfactants are incorporated in preparations like toothpaste",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Use of soaps and detergents as cleansing agents, molecular structure can be elucidated by surface tension measurements through parachor values and surfactants are incorporated in preparations like toothpaste are the applications of surface tension.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The process of heating a liquid mixture to form vapours and then cooling the vapours to get pure component is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crystallisation",
            "b) Distillation",
            "c) Chromatography",
            "d) Sublimation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of heating a liquid mixture to form vapours and then cooling the vapours to get pure component is called distillation. Distillation is a process of separating the component substances from a liquid mixture by selective evaporation and condensation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Porcelain pieces are put into the distillation flask to avoid ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overheating",
            "b) Uniform boiling",
            "c) Bumping of the solution",
            "d) None of the mentioned options"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Porcelain pieces are put into the distillation flask to avoid bumping of the solution due to uneven heating.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The boiling point of chloroform is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 334 K",
            "b) 286 K",
            "c) 350 K",
            "d) 298 K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The boiling point of chloroform is 334 K. Chloroform is an organic compound with formula CHCl3. It is a colorless, sweet-smelling, dense liquid that is produced on a large scale as a precursor to PTFE and refrigerants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "The boiling point of aniline is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 438 K",
            "b) 370 K",
            "c) 338 K",
            "d) 457 K"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The boiling point of aniline is 457 K. Aniline is a toxic organic compound with the formula C6H5NH2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "How aniline and chloroform can be separated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sublimation",
            "b) Condensation",
            "c) Distillation",
            "d) Evaporation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Aniline and chloroform can be separated through the distillation process. Aniline is a toxic organic compound with the formula C6H5NH2. Chloroform is an organic compound with formula CHCl3. It is a colorless, sweet-smelling, dense liquid that is produced on a large scale as a precursor to PTFE and refrigerants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not separated through distillation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetone and water",
            "b) Aniline and chloroform",
            "c) Impurities in Sea water",
            "d) Milk and water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Milk and water are not separated through the distillation process. All the other options can be separated through a distillation process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "Which of the following will vaporize faster?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aniline",
            "b) Chloroform",
            "c) Water",
            "d) Kerosene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chloroform will vaporize faster than aniline and water. Chloroform is an organic compound with formula CHCl3. It is a colorless, sweet-smelling, dense liquid that is produced on a large scale as a precursor to PTFE and refrigerants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "The distilled water is collected in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Receiver",
            "b) Adapter",
            "c) Condenser",
            "d) Round bottom flask"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The distilled water is collected in the receiver. An installation for distillation, especially of alcohol, is a distillery. The distillation equipment is still.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "The process of distillation is used for the liquids having ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sufficient difference in their boiling point",
            "b) Sufficient difference in their melting point",
            "c) Sufficient difference in their solubility",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of distillation is used for the liquids having a sufficient difference in their boiling point. Distillation also permits the separation of air into its components.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The residue in the round bottom flask is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volatile",
            "b) Non volatile",
            "c) None of the mentioned",
            "d) Volatile & Non volatile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The residue salt int he round bottom flask is non volatile in nature. The process of distillation is used for the liquids having a sufficient difference in their boiling point. Distillation also permits the separation of air into its components.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Fractional distillation is a process of separation of  ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 miscible liquids",
            "b) 2 immiscible liquids",
            "c) 1 miscible and 1 immiscible liquid",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fractional distillation is a process of separation of 2 immiscible liquids. Fractional distillation is the separation of a mixture into its component parts, or fractions, separating chemical compounds by their boiling point by heating them to a temperature at which one or more fractions of the compound will vaporize.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The difference in boiling point of 2 liquid in fractional distillation is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than 25 K",
            "b) Less than 25 K",
            "c) Equal to 25 K",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Difference in the boiling point of 2 liquid in fractional distillation is is less than 25 K. Fractional distillation is the separation of a mixture into its component parts, or fractions, separating chemical compounds by their boiling point by heating them to a temperature at which one or more fractions of the compound will vaporize.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "A simple fractional tube is packed with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wooden beads",
            "b) Plastic beads",
            "c) Metal beads",
            "d) Glass beads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A simple fractional tube is packed with glass beads. The fractional distillation column is set up with the heat source at the bottom on the still pot.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "Fractional distillation is different from distillation because of the presence of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fractionating column",
            "b) Condenser",
            "c) Distillation flask",
            "d) Conical flask"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fractional distillation is different from distillation because of the presence of fractionating column. A laboratory fractionating column is a piece of glassware used to separate vaporized mixtures of liquid compounds with close volatility.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "The beads are provided in fractional column for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vapours to generate",
            "b) Vapours to condense",
            "c) Vapours to evaporate",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The beads are provided in fractional column for vapours to condense. The fractional distillation column is set up with the heat source at the bottom of the still pot.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fractionating columns are available in various design and size",
            "b) Fractionating columns are available according to one fixed standard",
            "c) A simple fractionating column is a tube packed with glass beads",
            "d) Fractional distillation is the process of separation of different gases from air"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fractionating columns are available in various design and sizes and not according to one fixed standard.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases cannot be separated from air using fractional distillation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Argon",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) Helium",
            "d) Nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Helium gas cannot be separated from air using fractional distillation. Fractional distillation is used in air separation, producing liquid oxygen, liquid nitrogen, and highly concentrated argon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Initially, the temperature at the top of the column is _______________ than at its bottom.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater",
            "b) Lesser",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The temperature at the top of the column is lesser than at its bottom. The two major types of distillation columns used are tray and packing columns.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Which of the following is more suitable for fractional distillation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oil bath",
            "b) Water bath",
            "c) Glycerine bath",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oil bath is the most suitable option for the fractional distillation process. Vacuum distillation systems operate at reduced pressure, thereby lowering the boiling points of the materials. Anti-bumping granules, however, become ineffective at reduced pressures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Number of steps required for the separation of two liquids in fractional distillation is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Number of steps required for the separation of two liquids in fractional distillation is 2. Vacuum distillation systems operate at reduced pressure, thereby lowering the boiling points of the materials. Anti-bumping granules, however, become ineffective at reduced pressures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "In steam distillation, the liquid boils when the sum of vapour pressure due to organic liquid and due to water becomes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than atmospheric pressure",
            "b) Lesser than atmospheric pressure",
            "c) Equals to atmospheric pressure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In steam distillation, the liquid boils when the sum of vapour pressure due to organic liquid and due to water becomes equal to the atmospheric pressure. It is a type of distillation of a liquid in a current of steam, used especially to purify liquids that are not very volatile and are immiscible with water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "The organic liquid in steam distillation vaporizes at ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower temperature than its boiling point",
            "b) Higher temperature than its boiling point",
            "c) At its boiling point",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The organic liquid in steam distillation vaporizes at lower temperature than its boiling point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Steam distillation process is used to separate substances which are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Steam volatile",
            "b) Steam volatile and immiscible with water",
            "c) Steam volatile and miscible with water",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Steam distillation process is used to separate substances which are steam volatile and immiscible with water. It is a type of distillation of a liquid in a current of steam, used especially to purify liquids that are not very volatile and are immiscible with water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "What type of mixture is collected in round bottom flask after passing through a steam generator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixture of volatile organic compound and water",
            "b) Mixture of nonvolatile organic compound and water",
            "c) Mixture of nonvolatile inorganic compound and steam",
            "d) Mixture of volatile organic compound and steam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mixture of volatile organic compound and steam is collected in round bottom flask after passing through steam generator.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following property is not possessed by the organic solvent required to separate organic compound with water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is immiscible with water",
            "b) It is less volatile than water",
            "c) It is easily vaporisable",
            "d) Organic compound is more soluble in it"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Organic solvent required to separate organic compound with water is more volatile liquid than water. All the other mentioned properties are possessed by the organic solvent required to separate organic compound with water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the upper layer in differential extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solvent layer",
            "b) Solute layer",
            "c) Aqueous layer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Solvent layer is the upper layer in differential extraction. Differential extraction refers to the process by which the DNA from two different types of cells can be extracted without mixing their contents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "When does the organic compound be present in the upper solvent layer in differential extraction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Before the extraction",
            "b) During the extraction",
            "c) After the extraction",
            "d) It is always present in the upper layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The organic compound is present in the solvent layer after the extraction. Differential extraction refers to the process by which the DNA from two different types of cells can be extracted without mixing their contents\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "The organic compound in differential extraction is recovered from the organic solvent by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distillation",
            "b) Fractional crystallisation",
            "c) Steam crystallisation",
            "d) Sublimation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The organic compound in differential extraction is recovered from the organic solvent by distillation by evaporation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Aniline is separated from aniline-water mixture using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fractional distillation",
            "b) Fractional crystallisation",
            "c) Steam distillation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pure solvent after the differential extraction can be used again for the extraction because it remains unaltered.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "Chromatography is the process for identification, purification and separation of components of a mixture on the basis of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Difference in their boiling point",
            "b) Difference in their melting point",
            "c) Difference in their affinity for mobile and stationary phase",
            "d) Difference in their solubility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Chromatography is the process for identification, purification and separation of components of a mixture on the basis of difference in their affinity for mobile and stationary phases. The mixture is dissolved in a fluid called the mobile phase, which carries it through a structure holding another material called the stationary phase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Chromatography involves two mutually ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immiscible phases",
            "b) Miscible phases",
            "c) Soluble phases",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chromatography involves two mutually immiscible phases (stationary and mobile phases). The mixture is dissolved in a fluid called the mobile phase, which carries it through a structure holding another material called the stationary phase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "There is no need of support if packed into a column when the stationary phase is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gas",
            "b) Liquid",
            "c) Solid",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the stationary phase is solid, there is no need of support if packed into a column. In solid phase, all the molecules are already in closed packing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a stationary phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Liquid-liquid chromatography",
            "b) Gas-liquid chromatography",
            "c) Gas-solid chromatography",
            "d) Solid-solid chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Solid-solid chromatography is not a stationary phase because solid-solid phase cannot provide any fluidity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "Liquid chromatography is a technique for separating ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ions that are not dissolved in a solvent",
            "b) Ions that are dissolved in a solvent",
            "c) Ions that are dissolved in a solute",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Liquid chromatography is a technique for separating ions that are dissolved in a solvent. Solute is the material which is dissolved and solvent is the solution in which it is dissolved.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "In exclusion chromatography, solute molecules are separated based on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molecular geometry and size",
            "b) Molecular composition",
            "c) Molecular phase",
            "d) Molecular formula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In exclusion chromatography, solute molecules are separated based on molecular geometry and size. These two physical characteristics have a significance role in exclusion chromatography.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "The gas-solid  chromatography is ______________  chromatography as per basic principle involved.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exclusion",
            "b) Ion-exchange",
            "c) Adsorption",
            "d) Absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gas-solid chromatography is adsorption chromatography as per basic principle involved as the gas molecules are adsorbed on the solid surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "A proper solvent that is passed through the column for elution so that separated components can be collected is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adsorbent",
            "b) Buffer solution",
            "c) Mobile phase",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A proper solvent that is passed through the column for elution so that separated components can be collected is called buffer solution. The eluate is the mobile phase leaving the column. The eluent is the solvent that carries the analyte.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "The relative solubility of solute in both the phases determines the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rate of movement of solvent",
            "b) Rate of disappearance of solvent",
            "c) Rate of movement of solute",
            "d) Rate of disappearance of solute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The relative solubility of solute in both the phases determines the rate of movement of solute as solute is added to the solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "If the mobile phase is gas, movement of solute is determined by its ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boiling point",
            "b) Melting point",
            "c) Solubility",
            "d) Volatility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the mobile phase is gas, movement of solute is determined by its volatility because gas is always measured as volatility not as solubility or melting point or boiling point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Column chromatography is based on the principle of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion-exchange",
            "b) Exclusion principle",
            "c) Differential adsorption",
            "d) Absorption"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Column chromatography is based on the principle of differential adsorption. It means different compounds have different tendencies to get adsorb on a particular surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Arrange the following compounds in order of their increasing adsorption tendencies.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cellulose >> starch >> calcium carbonate >> alumina",
            "b) Cellulose >> starch >> alumina >> charcoal",
            "c) Charcoal >> cellulose >> alumina >> starch",
            "d) Calcium carbonate >>; alumina >> starch >> cellulose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cellulose >> starch >> calcium carbonate >> charcoal >> alumina is the correct order of increasing adsorption tendencies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "What is the factor responsible for the separation in column chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polarity differences between the solvent",
            "b) Polarity differences between the solute",
            "c) Polarity indifference between the solvent",
            "d) Polarity indifference between the solute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polarity differences between the solute molecules are responsible for the separation in column chromatography.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The lesser the polarity of solute, more strongly it will be adsorbed on a polar surface",
            "b) The greater the polarity of solute, more weakly it will be adsorbed on a polar surface",
            "c) The greater  the polarity of solute, more strongly it will be adsorbed on a polar surface",
            "d) All of the mentioned option"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The greater the polarity of solute, more strongly it will be adsorbed on a polar surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "The correct order of increasing strength of adsorption is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alkanes >>  Esters >> Aldehydes >> Phenols >> Ketones",
            "b) Aldehydes >> Phenols >> Ketones >> Esters >> Alkanes",
            "c) Aldehydes >> Ketones >> Esters >> Alkanes >> Phenols",
            "d) Alkanes >> Esters >> Ketones >> Aldehydes >> Phenols"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: the correct order increasing strength of adsorption is: Alkanes >> Esters >> Ketones >> Aldehydes >> Phenols.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "The components of the mixture in column chromatography are eluted in order of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing polarity and decreasing distribution ratio",
            "b) Increasing polarity and increasing distribution ratio",
            "c) Decreasing polarity and increasing distribution ratio",
            "d) Decreasing polarity and decreasing distribution ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The components of the mixture in column chromatography are eluted in order of increasing polarity and increasing distribution ratio.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The elution power of a solvent is determined by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its overall polarity",
            "b) The polarity of the stationary phase",
            "c) The nature of the sample components",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The elution power of a solvent is determined by its overall polarity, the polarity of the stationary phase and the nature of the sample components.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Which of the following is separated through column chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorophyll and carotenoids",
            "b) Inorganic cations or complexes",
            "c) Sugar derivatives",
            "d) Amino acids formed by hydrolysis of a protein molecule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main application of column chromatography is to separate plant pigment (Chlorophyll and carotenoids).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "The mixture of petroleum ether and benzene is used in the elution ratio of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 : 2",
            "b) 1 : 5",
            "c) 1 : 9",
            "d) 1 : 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mixture of petroleum ether and benzene is used in the elution ratio of 1:9 (V/V).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "Chloroform fraction is eluted from the column by passing  chloroform  through the column which acts as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eluter",
            "b) Eluant",
            "c) Elution",
            "d) None of the mentioned option"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chloroform fraction is eluted from the column by passing chloroform through the column which acts as eluant. The eluate is the mobile phase leaving the column. The eluent is the solvent that carries the analyte.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "The principle on which thin layer chromatography is based is that the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Different compounds are absorbed on an absorbent to different degrees",
            "b) Different compounds are absorbed on an absorbent to same degrees",
            "c) Different compounds are adsorbed on an adsorbent to different degrees",
            "d) Different compounds are absorbed on an absorbent to same degrees"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thin layer chromatography is based on the fact that different compounds are adsorbed on an adsorbent to different degrees. It is a chromatography technique used to separate non-volatile mixtures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "The size of a thin layer of adsorbent is about ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 mm",
            "b) 0.2 mm",
            "c) 0.3 mm",
            "d) 0.4 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The size of a thin layer of adsorbent is about 0.2 mm. TLC plates are usually commercially available, with standard particle size ranges to improve reproducibility.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "The chromaplate or thin layer chromatography plate is made up of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass",
            "b) Wood",
            "c) Fibre",
            "d) Metal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The chromaplate or thin layer chromatography plate is made up of glass. TLC plates are usually commercially available, with standard particle size ranges to improve reproducibility. They are prepared by mixing the adsorbent, such as silica gel, with a small amount of inert binder like calcium sulfate (gypsum) and water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "The eluant filled in the closed jar is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mixture of gases",
            "b) Mixture of a liquid and a gas",
            "c) Mixture of solids",
            "d) Mixture of liquids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The eluant filled in the closed jar is liquid or mixture of liquids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The spots of colorless compounds are invisible to the eyes",
            "b) These spots can be detected by putting the plate under ultraviolet light",
            "c) These spots can be detected by placing the plate in a covered jar containing iodine crystals",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the mentioned options are correct. The spots of colorless compounds are invisible to the eyes, can be detected by putting the plate under ultraviolet light and can be detected by placing the plate in a covered jar containing iodine crystals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "The relative adsorption of each component of the mixture is expressed in terms of its ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acceleration factor",
            "b) Retardation factor",
            "c) Both acceleration and retardation factor",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The relative adsorption of each component of the mixture is expressed in terms of its retardation factor (Rf).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paper chromatography is a type of partition chromatography",
            "b) A special quality paper is used in paper chromatography",
            "c) Chromatography paper contains water trapped in it, which acts as stationary phase",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Paper chromatography is a type of partition chromatography. A special quality paper is used in paper chromatography which contains water trapped in it, which acts as a stationary phase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "Amino acids detected by spraying the plate with ninhydrin solution is an example of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Column chromatography",
            "b) Thin layer chromatography",
            "c) Paper chromatography",
            "d) Liquid chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amino acids detected by spraying the plate with a ninhydrin solution is an example of paper chromatography. Paper chromatography is an analytical method that is used to separate colored chemicals or substances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Retardation factor is the ratio of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distance moved by substance from base line to distance moved by the solvent from base line",
            "b) Distance moved by solvent from base line to distance moved by the substance from base line",
            "c) Distance moved by substance from top line to distance moved by the solvent from top line",
            "d) Distance moved by solvent from top line to distance moved by the substance from top line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Paper chromatography is based on a continuous differential partitioning of components of a mixture between stationary and mobile phases. It is an analytical method that is used to separate colored chemicals or substances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "What are the uses of partition chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separation of amino acids",
            "b) Analysis of closely related aliphatic alcohols",
            "c) Separation of sugar derivatives",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The uses of partition chromatography are separation of amino acids, analysis of closely related aliphatic alcohols and separation of sugar derivatives.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Which type of chromatography is used for the structural analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Column chromatography",
            "b) Paper chromatography",
            "c) Partition chromatography",
            "d) Affinity chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Paper chromatography is used for structural analysis. Paper chromatography is an analytical method that is used to separate colored chemicals or substances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not done using column chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The identification of unknown compounds",
            "b) The determination of homogeneity of chemical substances",
            "c) Separation of inorganic cations or complexes",
            "d) Separation of geometric isomers"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Separation of inorganic cations or complexes is done using paper chromatography. Column chromatography is a method used to purify individual chemical compounds from mixtures of compounds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Affinity chromatography is used for the analysis and isolation of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insoluble starch substances",
            "b) Enzyme tyrosinase",
            "c) Antibodies bound with a covalently-attached antigen on cellulose column",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Affinity chromatography is used for the analysis and isolation of insoluble starch substances, enzyme tyrosinase and antibodies bound with a covalently-attached antigen on cellulose column.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Purification of enzymes and proteins is done using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Affinity chromatography",
            "b) Liquid chromatography",
            "c) Column chromatography",
            "d) Thin layer chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Affinity chromatography is used for the purification of enzymes and proteins. Affinity chromatography is also used for the analysis and isolation of insoluble starch substances, enzyme tyrosinase and antibodies bound with a covalently-attached antigen on cellulose column.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of high performance liquid chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Analysis of proteins, drugs and explosives",
            "b) Separation of pharmaceutical drugs",
            "c) Elimination of undesirable substances from blood",
            "d) Separation of lipids, fatty acids and steroids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Elimination of undesirable substances from blood is done using affinity chromatography. All the other options are the application of high performance liquid chromatography.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "The analysis and separation of industrial products like soap and synthetic detergents is done using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thin layer chromatography",
            "b) Gas chromatography",
            "c) Ion exchange chromatography",
            "d) Partition chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The checking of purity of samples is the application of thin layer chromatography. It is a chromatography technique used to separate non-volatile mixtures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the application of ion exchange chromatography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The softening of hard water",
            "b) The demineralisation of water",
            "c) The separation and determination of anions",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The analysis and separation of industrial products like soap and synthetic detergents is done using gas chromatography. It is a common type of chromatography used in analytical chemistry for separating and analyzing compounds that can be vaporized without decomposition.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "The quantitative analysis is done using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ion exchange chromatography",
            "b) Thin layer chromatography",
            "c) Gas chromatography",
            "d) Liquid chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The application of ion exchange chromatography is softening of hard water, demineralisation of water and the separation and determination of anions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "The purity of the compound is confirmed by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its melting point and boiling point",
            "b) Chromatographic technique",
            "c) Spectroscopy",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The purity of the compound is confirmed by its melting point and boiling point, chromatographic technique and spectroscopy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The transformation of solid to liquid is called melting and the reverse process is called freezing",
            "b) The transformation of solid to liquid is called freezing and the reverse process is called melting",
            "c) The transformation of liquid to solid is called melting and the reverse process is called freezing",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transformation of solid to liquid is called melting and the reverse process is called freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The temperature at which solid and liquid coexist in equilibrium is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melting point of liquid",
            "b) Freezing point of liquid",
            "c) Freezing point of solid",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The temperature at which solid and liquid coexist in equilibrium is called melting point of solid or freezing point of liquid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Every pure solid crystalline substance has a characteristic and unique melting point",
            "b) Impure sample of substance has different melting point",
            "c) Two different pure substances have same melting points",
            "d) Melting point serves as the criteria of purity of a solid substance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two different pure substances have different melting points. All the other options are correct. Every pure solid crystalline substance has a characteristic and unique melting point and impure sample of substance has different melting point. Melting point serves as the criteria of purity of a solid substance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "When the solid and liquid phase are in equilibrium, the temperature ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases gradually",
            "b) Decreases gradually",
            "c) Remains constant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  When the solid and liquid phase are in equilibrium, the temperature remains constant. The heat is absorbed in changing from one state to another, so no temperature change occurs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "The melting point of ice is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 00C",
            "b) 1000C",
            "c) 40C",
            "d) -40C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The melting point of ice at 1 atmosphere of pressure is very close to 0 °C (32 °F, 273.15 K); this is also known as the ice point. In the presence of nucleating substances the freezing point of water is the same as the melting point, but in the absence of nucleators water can supercool to −42 °C (−43.6 °F, 231 K) before freezing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Molar heat of fusion is defined as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Energy required to melt one gram of solid",
            "b) Energy required to melt one mole of solid",
            "c) Energy required to melt one kilogram of solid",
            "d) Energy required to melt ten moles of solid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Molar heat of fusion is defined as the energy required to melt one mole of solid at a given temperature. The molar heat of fusion refers to the enthalpy change per amount of substance in moles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "What is the molar heat of fusion (kJ/mol) of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.3",
            "b) 0.84",
            "c) 7.61",
            "d) 6.01"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The temperature remains constant during phase change because the increased kinetic energy is used to overcome the cohesive forces in the liquid. The heat is absorbed in changing from one state to another, so no temperature change occurs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "What is the melting point of mercury?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3570C",
            "b) -390C",
            "c) 00C",
            "d) 1000C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The molar heat of fusion of water is 6.01 kJ/mol. The molar heat of fusion refers to the enthalpy change per amount of substance in moles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "On increasing the temperature of a liquid, its vapour pressure ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Remain constant",
            "c) Increases",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The vapour pressure of a liquid increases with an increase in temperature. Vapour pressure or equilibrium vapor pressure is defined as the pressure exerted by a vapor in thermodynamic equilibrium with its condensed phases at a given temperature in a closed system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The boiling point of a liquid is the temperature at which the vapour pressure ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Is equal to the internal pressure",
            "b) Is equal to the external pressure",
            "c) Is greater than an internal pressure",
            "d) Is lesser than an internal pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The boiling point of a liquid is the temperature at which the vapour pressure is equal to external pressure. The boiling point of a liquid varies depending upon the surrounding environmental pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "The normal boiling point of a liquid is the temperature at which it boils when the external pressure is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 atm",
            "b) 2 atm",
            "c) 3 atm",
            "d) 5 atm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The normal boiling point of a liquid is the temperature at which it boils when the external pressure is 1 atm. The boiling point of a liquid varies depending upon the surrounding environmental pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "If the non-volatile impurities contaminate the liquid, its boiling point gets ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depressed",
            "b) Elevated",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the non-volatile impurities contaminate the liquid, its boiling point gets elevated. This is one of the most important colligative property. Example: salt water boils at a higher temperature than pure water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "The energy required to vaporize 1 mole of a liquid is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molar heat of fusion",
            "b) Molar heat of freezing",
            "c) Molar heat of boiling",
            "d) Molar heat of vaporisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The energy required to vaporize 1 mole of a liquid is known as the molar heat of vaporisation. It is the amount of heat necessary to boil (or condense) one mole of a substance at its boiling point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "At 1 atm pressure, the boiling point of water is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 0C",
            "b) 1000C",
            "c) -1000C",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The boiling point of water at 1 atm pressure is 1000C. The boiling point of a liquid varies depending upon the surrounding environmental pressure. A liquid in a partial vacuum has a lower boiling point than when that liquid is at atmospheric pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "The boiling point and molar heat of vaporisation is dependent on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength of the inter-molecular forces",
            "b) Composition of the liquid compound",
            "c) Size of the molecules",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The boiling point and molar heat of vaporisation is dependent on the strength of the inter-molecular forces. The boiling point of a liquid varies depending upon the surrounding environmental pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methane and argon have weak dispersion forces so their boiling point is low",
            "b) Diethyl ether has a dipole moment, and the dipole-dipole forces accounts for its moderately high boiling point",
            "c) Water and ethanol have strong hydrogen bonding and hence they possess high boiling point",
            "d) Mercury has weak metallic bonding which is responsible for its low boiling point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Mercury has strong metallic bonding which is responsible for its high boiling point. All the other options are correct. Methane and argon have weak dispersion forces so their boiling point is low. Diethyl ether has a dipole moment, and the dipole-dipole forces accounts for its moderately high boiling point. Water and ethanol have strong hydrogen bonding and hence they possess a high boiling point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "For a given substance, choose the correct statement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ΔHfus is greater than ΔHvap",
            "b) ΔHfus is equal to ΔHvap",
            "c) ΔHfus is smaller than ΔHvap",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a given substance, ΔHfus is smaller than ΔHvap.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "The molar heat of vaporisation (ΔHvap) for water is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40.79 kJ/mol",
            "b) 31.0 kJ/mol",
            "c) 59.0 kJ/mol",
            "d) 9.2 kJ/mol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The molar heat of vaporisation (ΔHvap) for water is 40.79 kJ/mol. Vapor pressures and boiling points of substances can be affected by the presence of dissolved impurities (solutes) or other miscible compounds, the degree of effect depending on the concentration of the impurities or other compounds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a method of particle size measurement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sieve analysis",
            "b) Microscopic examination",
            "c) Sedimentation analysis",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sieve analysis, microscopic examination and sedimentation analysis are the three methods of particle size measurement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "The minimum size of particle which can be separated through sieve analysis is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75 microns",
            "b) 100 microns",
            "c) 44 microns",
            "d) 20 microns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum size of particle which can be separated through sieve analysis is 44 microns. The results of sieve analysis are used to describe the properties of the aggregate and to see if it is appropriate for various civil engineering purposes such as selecting the appropriate aggregate for concrete mixes and asphalt mixes as well as sizing of water production well screens.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "The instrument used for the examination of particle size ≥ 0.5 micron is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microscope",
            "b) Electron microscope",
            "c) Telescope",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The instrument used for the examination of particle size ≥ 0.5 micron is a microscope. Microscope is an optical instrument used for viewing very small objects.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "Sedimentation techniques are particularly useful for the particle size ranging from ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50-10 µm",
            "b) 40-2 µm",
            "c) 100-50 µm",
            "d) 80-40µm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sedimentation techniques are particularly useful for the particle size ranging from 40-2 µm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Sedimentation analysis is generally applicable to liquid dispersions containing _______________ % solids.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-10",
            "b) 1-3",
            "c) 2-5",
            "d) 4-8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sedimentation analysis is generally applicable to liquid dispersions containing 2-5% solids. It is particularly useful for the particle size ranging from 40-2 µm.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the Coulter counter, a narrow orifice is immersed in an electrolyte",
            "b) The resistance across the orifice is continuously noted on an oscilloscope",
            "c) The pulses occurring on the oscilloscope are counted electronically",
            "d) The magnitude of the pulse is inversely proportional to the volume of the electrolyte displaced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnitude of the pulse is directly proportional to the volume of the electrolyte displaced and therefore to the volume of the particle. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "The current generated in photoelectric cell represents the measure of the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbidity",
            "b) Adhesivity",
            "c) Cohesivity",
            "d) Viscosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The current generated in photoelectric cell represents the measure of the turbidity of the suspension. Turbidity is the cloudiness or haziness of a fluid caused by large numbers of individual particles that are generally invisible to the naked eye. It is the capacity of water to disperse the light.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Adsorption method for measurement of total surface area involves the evaluation of quantity of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helium gas",
            "b) Oxygen gas",
            "c) Nitrogen gas",
            "d) Argon gas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adsorption method for measurement of total surface area involves the evaluation of quantity of nitrogen gas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "In photo-extinction method, a source of light is directed through a suspension of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerosene in cement",
            "b) Cement in kerosene",
            "c) Cement in water",
            "d) Water in cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In photo-extinction method, a source of light is directed through a suspension of cement in kerosene on to a photoelectric cell.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Fibrous fillers have a high capacity for absorbing energy because of their ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shape",
            "b) Size",
            "c) Composition",
            "d) Surface area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fibrous fillers have a high capacity for absorbing energy because of their shape. As a result, they impart excellent impart strength to the material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "The B.E.T. theory was proposed in the year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1940",
            "b) 1935",
            "c) 1938",
            "d) 1945"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Brunauer, Emmett and Teller proposed a theory in 1938 which is known as B.E.T. theory.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "The B.E.T. theory was based on the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single layer adsorption",
            "b) Multilayer adsorption",
            "c) Double layer adsorption",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The B.E.T. theory was based on the multilayer adsorption. It aims to explain the physical adsorption of gas molecules on a solid surface and serves as the basis for an important analysis technique for the measurement of the specific surface area of a material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an assumption for B.E.T theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The solid surface possess uniform, localised sites",
            "b) The adsorption at one site does not affect adsorption at neighbouring site",
            "c) Physical adsorption of adsorbate occurs resulting in the formation of multilayers",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The assumptions for B.E.T theory are – the solid surface possess uniform, localised sites, the adsorption at one site does not affect adsorption at neighbouring site and physical adsorption of adsorbate occurs resulting in formation of multilayers, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "The energy of adsorption in the first layer is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increasing",
            "b) Decreasing",
            "c) Constant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The energy of adsorption in the first layer is constant. It aims to explain the physical adsorption of gas molecules on a solid surface and serves as the basis for an important analysis technique for the measurement of the specific surface area of a material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The surface area available for the nth layer is equal to the coverage of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (n-1)th layer",
            "b) (n+1)th layer",
            "c) nth layer",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surface area available for the nth layer is equal to the coverage of (n-1)th layer. By application of the BET theory, it is possible to determine the inner surface of hardened cement paste.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "In the B.E.T. equation, what does p0 denotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pressure of the gas molecules",
            "b) Unsaturated vapor pressure of the gas molecules",
            "c) Saturated vapor pressure of the gas molecules",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the B.E.T. equation, p0 denotes the saturated vapour pressure of the gas molecules at the same temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "According to B.E.T. equation, the plot of P/V(P0-P) versus P/P0 will yield a ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straight line",
            "b) Parabola",
            "c) Hyperbola",
            "d) Eclipse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: According to B.E.T. equation, the plot of P/V(P0-P) versus P/P0 will yield a straight line. By application of the BET theory, it is possible to determine the inner surface of hardened cement paste.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "The B.E.T. theory is used in calculating the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface area of adsorbate",
            "b) Surface area of adsorbent only",
            "c) Surface area of adsorbents and catalyst",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The B.E.T. theory is used in calculating the surface area of adsorbents and catalyst. By application of the BET theory, it is possible to determine the inner surface of hardened cement paste.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "The surface area occupied by a single gas molecule is inversely proportional to the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molar mass of the gas adsorbed",
            "b) Density of the liquefied gas",
            "c) Volume of the gas",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The surface area occupied by a single gas molecule is inversely proportional to the density of the liquefied gas. Porous inorganic materials such as mesoporous silica and layered clay minerals have high surface areas of several hundred m2g−1 calculated by the BET method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "The total surface area covered by all the molecules of the adsorbed gas is given by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) S = nβ/NA",
            "b) S = βNA/n",
            "c) S = nβNA",
            "d) S = NA/nβ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The total surface area covered by all the molecules of the adsorbed gas is given by S = nβNA. The surface area occupied by a single gas molecule is inversely proportional to the density of the liquefied gas.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Conductivity is defined as the ability to carry ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Voltage",
            "b) Resistance",
            "c) Current",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conductivity is defined as the ability to carry current. It is measured by the flow of electrons and charges through a conductor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "The reciprocal of conductivity is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity",
            "b) Resistivity",
            "c) Turbidity",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reciprocal of conductivity is resistivity. It is the measure of resistance provided in the path of electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a specific conductivity reagent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) KCl",
            "b) HCl",
            "c) NaCl",
            "d) MgCl2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: KCl is a specific conductivity reagent. Specific conductance is a measure of the electric current in the water sampled carried by the ionized substances.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "The internationally recommended unit for conductance is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poise",
            "b) Dyne",
            "c) Ohm",
            "d) Siemens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The internationally recommended unit for conductance is Siemens (S). 1 siemen = 1 ohm-1\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "The cell constant is defined as the ratio of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Area of either electrodes to the length between the electrodes",
            "b) Length between the electrodes to the area of either electrodes",
            "c) Length between the electrodes to the volume of either electrode",
            "d) Resistivity to conductivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cell constant is defined as the ratio of length between the electrodes to the area of either electrodes. It only depends upon the physical dimension of the cell.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Choose the correct order of molar ionic conductivities of the following ions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Li+ < Na+ < K+ < Rb+",
            "b) Li+ < K+ < Rb+ < Na+",
            "c) Li+ < Na+ < Rb+ < K+",
            "d) Li+ < Rb+ < Na+ < K+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: the correct order of molar ionic conductivity is- Li+ < Na+ < K+ < Rb+.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "On which factor does the conductance of electrolytic solutions depend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature and pressure",
            "b) Number of charge carriers",
            "c) Dielectric constant of the solvent",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors on which conductance of electrolytic solution depends are- Temperature, pressure, number of charge carriers and dielectric constant of the solvent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "On dilution, the specific conductance ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Remains same",
            "c) Decreases",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On dilution, the specific conductance decreases because dilution decreases the concentration of the solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "The equivalent conductance of 0.1 H2SO4offering a resistance of 50ohms when placed in a conductivity cell whose electrodes are 1cm apart with a cross-sectional area of 2cm2 at 250C is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 S cm2 eq-1",
            "b) 1000 S cm2 eq-1",
            "c) 10 S cm2 eq-1",
            "d) 1 S cm2 eq-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The equivalent molar conductance is 100 S cm2 eq-1.\nConductivity = Conductance * cell constant\nCell constant = Length / Area\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Dilution means an increase in the amount of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solute",
            "b) Solvent",
            "c) Electrolyte",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dilution means an increase in the amount of solvent and hence it decreases the concentration of solute particles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "According to Newton’s law of viscosity, the maximum velocity of flow is at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top of the tube",
            "b) Bottom of the tube",
            "c) Middle of the tube",
            "d) It is same at all the places"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Newton’s law of viscosity, the maximum velocity of flow is at the middle of the tube. It states that for given shear stress acting on a fluid element, the rate at which the fluid deforms is inversely proportional to the viscosity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "The factor on which viscosity depends is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Area of contact of two adjacent layers",
            "b) Velocity difference between two adjacent layers",
            "c) The distance between two adjacent layers",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors on which viscosity depends are- Area of contact of two adjacent layers, velocity difference between two adjacent layers and the distance between two adjacent layers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "The viscosity of a fluid is inversely proportional to the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Area of contact of two adjacent layers",
            "b) Distance between two adjacent layers",
            "c) Velocity difference between two adjacent layers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The viscosity of a fluid is inversely proportional to the distance between two adjacent layers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "The Newton’s law of viscosity is not applicable to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Turbulent flow",
            "b) Laminar flow",
            "c) Streamline flow",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Newton’s law of viscosity is not applicable to turbulent flow. According to Newton’s law of viscosity, for a given shear stress acting on a fluid element, the rate at which the fluid deforms is inversely proportional to the viscosity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "What is the dimension of viscosity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MLT2",
            "b) M1L-1T",
            "c) ML-1T-1",
            "d) ML-2T1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dimension of viscosity is ML-1T-1. It’s unit is m2/s or stokes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "The absolute kinematic viscosity is the ratio of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density to absolute viscosity",
            "b) Absolute viscosity to density",
            "c) Kinetic energy to absolute viscosity",
            "d) Absolute viscosity to kinetic energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The absolute kinematic viscosity is the ratio of absolute viscosity to density for any fluid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "On increasing the temperature, the viscosity of the fluid __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Remains constant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: On increasing the temperature, the viscosity of the fluid decreases. This is because of the decrease in inter-molecular forces.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "How does viscosity gets affected on increasing the pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity increases",
            "b) Viscosity decreases",
            "c) Viscosity does not get affected by the pressure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At high pressures, the viscosity increases considerably. Zero viscosity is observed only at very low temperatures in superfluids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity helps in the selection of good lubricating oil",
            "b) Light oils have low densities and easy flowability",
            "c) Heavy oils are used on parts moving with high speed",
            "d) Light oils do not impose much drag on high-speed parts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Heavy oils are used on parts moving with slow speed under heavy loads. All the other options are correct. Viscosity helps in the selection of good lubricating oil, light oils have low densities and easy flowability and do not impose much drag on high-speed parts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "1 poise = ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 N sm-2",
            "b) 100 N sm-2",
            "c) 1/100 N sm-2",
            "d) 1/10 N sm-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: 1 poise = 1 dyne s cm-2 = 1/10 N s m-2.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "The analysis of electromagnetic radiation scattered, absorbed or emitted by the molecule is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kaleidoscopy",
            "b) Astronomy",
            "c) Spectroscopy",
            "d) Anatomy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The analysis of electromagnetic radiation scattered, absorbed or emitted by the molecule is called spectroscopy. Astronomy is the study of celestial objects and processes the physics, chemistry, and evolution of such objects and processes. A kaleidoscope is an optical instrument, typically a cylinder with mirrors containing loose, colored objects such as beads or pebbles and bits of glass. Anatomy is the branch of biology concerned with the study of the structure of organisms and their parts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "The energy level with lower energy is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ground state energy level",
            "b) Initial state energy level",
            "c) Excited state energy level",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lower energy level is called the ground state and the higher energy level is called excited state. The excited state of a system (such as an atom, molecule or nucleus) is any quantum state of the system that has higher energy than the ground state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "Absorption spectrum results when an electron in an atom undergoes a transition from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher energy level to a lower one",
            "b) Lower energy level to a higher one",
            "c) Intermediate levels",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Absorption spectrum results when an electron in an atom undergoes a transition from lower energy level to a higher one.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "The energy of a photon is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) h/ν",
            "b) ν/h",
            "c) 1/hν",
            "d) hν"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The energy of a photon is given by hν where ν is the frequency and h is plank constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emission spectrum results when an electron in an atom undergoes a transition from excited state to the ground state",
            "b) In the emission spectrum, transition takes place with the emission of a photon of energy hν",
            "c) In the emission spectrum, transition takes place with the absorption of a photon of energy hν",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the emission spectrum, transition takes place with the emission of a photon of energy hν. All the other options are correct. Emission spectrum results when an electron in an atom undergoes a transition from excited state to the ground state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "The spectra can be broadly classified into two categories. They are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atomic and molecular spectra",
            "b) Atomic and electronic spectra",
            "c) Molecular and electronic spectra",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The spectra can be broadly classified into two categories: atomic and molecular spectra. Atomic spectra are the spectrum of frequencies of electromagnetic radiation emitted or absorbed during transitions of electrons between energy levels within an atom. Molecular spectra arises from the transition of an electron between the molecular energy levels.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molecular spectra arises from the transition of an electron between the molecular energy levels",
            "b) In molecular transitions, electronic, rotational and vibration transitions occurs",
            "c) Molecular spectra is more complicated than atomic spectra",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In atomic spectroscopy, only electronic transitions are involved. It is the spectrum of frequencies of electromagnetic radiation emitted or absorbed during transitions of electrons between energy levels within an atom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "The necessary condition for absorption spectrum is that  __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hν should be greater than the energy difference",
            "b) hν should be smaller than the energy difference",
            "c) hν should be equal to the energy difference",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Molecular spectra arises from the transition of an electron between the molecular energy levels. In molecular transitions, electronic, rotational and vibration transitions occurs and molecular spectra is more complicated than atomic spectra.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "The different types of energies associated with a molecule are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronic energy",
            "b) Vibrational energy",
            "c) Rotational energy",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The different types of energies associated with a molecule are electronic energy, vibrational energy, rotational energy and translational energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "During the motion, if the centre of gravity of molecule changes, the molecule possess __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electronic energy",
            "b) Rotational energy",
            "c) Translational energy",
            "d) Vibrational energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During the motion, if the centre of gravity of molecule changes, the molecule possess translational energy. Translational refers to the movement in horizontal or vertical direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "The correct order of different types of energies is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eel >> Evib >> Erot >> E tr",
            "b) Eel >> Erot >> Evib >> E tr",
            "c) Eel >> Evib >> Etr >> E rot",
            "d) Etr >> Evib >> Erot >> E el"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct order is: Eel >> Evib >> Erot >> E tr. Electronic enrgy is the highest whereas translational energy is the lowest.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "The region of electromagnetic spectrum for nuclear magnetic resonance is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microwave",
            "b) Radio frequency",
            "c) Infrared",
            "d) UV-rays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The region of the electromagnetic spectrum for nuclear magnetic resonance is radio frequency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of molecular spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural investigation",
            "b) Basis of understanding of colors",
            "c) Study of energetically excited reaction products",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The various applications of molecular spectroscopy are- Structural investigation, basis of understanding of colors and study of energetically excited reaction products.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spectroscopic methods require less time and more amount of sample than classical methods",
            "b) Spectroscopic methods require more time and more amount of sample than classical methods",
            "c) Spectroscopic methods require less time and less amount of sample than classical methods",
            "d) Spectroscopic methods require more time and less amount of sample than classical methods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Spectroscopic methods require less time and less amount of sample than classical methods (1 mg).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "The transition zone for Raman spectra is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Between vibrational and rotational levels",
            "b) Between electronic levels",
            "c) Between magnetic levels of nuclei",
            "d) Between magnetic levels of unpaired electrons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The results obtained by spectroscopic methods are reliable, reproducible and correct than classical methods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "The criteria for electronic spin resonance is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Periodic change in polarisability",
            "b) Spin quantum number of nuclei > 0",
            "c) Presence of unpaired electron in a molecule",
            "d) Presence of chromophore in a molecule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The transition zone for Raman spectra is between vibrational and rotational levels. Raman spectroscopy is a spectroscopic technique used to observe vibrational, rotational, and other low-frequency modes in a system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "The electronic spectra in the visible range span is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25000-72000 cm-1",
            "b) 25000-50000 cm-1",
            "c) 12500-25000 cm-1",
            "d) 15000-30000 cm-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The electronic spectra in the visible range span 12500-25000 cm-1 and in the UV region span 25000-72000 cm-1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Which of the following transitions are of weak intensities and lie in the visible region?",
        "Options": [
            "a) n→n*",
            "b) σ→σ*",
            "c) π→π*",
            "d) n→σ*"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: n→n* transitions are of weak intensities and lie in the visible region.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Arrange the various electronic transitions in the order of increasing energy.",
        "Options": [
            "a) n→σ* <  π→π* <  n→π* < σ→σ*",
            "b) n→π* <  π→π* <  n→σ* < σ→σ*",
            "c) n→σ* < n→π* <  π→π* < σ→σ*",
            "d) σ→σ* <  π→π* <  n→π* < n→σ*"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The correct order is- n→π* <  π→π* <  n→σ* < σ→σ*.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "What is the position of the band of alkanes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 190 nm",
            "b) 185 nm",
            "c) 217 nm",
            "d) 150 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The position of the band of alkanes is ≈150 nm. Alkanes refer to any of the series of saturated hydrocarbons including methane, ethane, propane, and higher members.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of the following organic compound shows transition due to conjugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alkenes",
            "b) Saturated aliphatic ketones",
            "c) Conjugated dienes",
            "d) Alkanes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conjugated dienes shows the transitions of low energy and is due to conjugation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an auxochrome group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) –OH",
            "b) –SH",
            "c) –OR",
            "d) –O2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Auxochrome is the color enhancing group. –O2 is not an example of auxochrome. -OH, -SH and -OR are examples of auxochrome.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Which of the following shift leads to the decreased intensity of absorption?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hypochromic",
            "b) Hyperchromic",
            "c) Hypsochromic",
            "d) Bathochromic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hypochromic shift leads to the decreased intensity of absorption. Hypochromicity describes a material’s decreasing ability to absorb light. Hyperchromicity is the material’s increasing ability to absorb light.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of electronic spectroscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Detection of impurities",
            "b) Control of purification",
            "c) Study of kinetics of the chemical reaction",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Detection of impurities, control of purification, study of the kinetics of the chemical reaction, determination of molecular weight and determination of unknown concentration are the applications of electronic spectroscopy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "What will be the absorbance if %T = 80?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.05",
            "c) 0.097",
            "d) 0.97"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Absorbance (A) = log(1/T) = log(100/80) = 0.097\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a limitation of the Lambert-Beer’s law?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scattering of light due to particles",
            "b) Fluorescence of sample",
            "c) Non-monochromatic radiation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Scattering of light due to particles, fluorescence of the sample and non-monochromatic radiation are some of the limitations of Lambert-Beer’s law. It relates the attenuation of light to the properties of the material through which the light is traveling.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Vibrational spectroscopy involves the transitions falling in the spectral range of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-1000 cm-1",
            "b) 300-3000 cm-1",
            "c) 400-4000 cm-1",
            "d) 500-5000 cm-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vibrational spectroscopy involves the transitions falling in the spectral range of 400-4000 cm-1 (infrared region).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which of the region of IR spectra appears between (1400-600) cm-1?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Functional group region",
            "b) Fingerprint region",
            "c) Low-frequency region",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fingerprint region of IR spectra appears between (1400-600) cm-1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Infrared spectra can identify the unknown materials",
            "b) It can determine the amount of components in a mixture",
            "c) It can also determine the quality of a sample",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Infrared spectra can identify the unknown materials. It can determine the amount of components in a mixture and can also determine the quality of a sample.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following molecule have infrared active vibrations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NO",
            "b) CH4",
            "c) H2",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NO molecule have infrared active vibrations. Infrared spectra can identify unknown materials. It can determine the amount of components in a mixture and can also determine the quality of a sample.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot show a vibrational absorption spectrum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) OCS",
            "b) H2O",
            "c) CO2",
            "d) C H2 = C H2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: C H2 = C H2 cannot show vibrational absorption spectrum. OCS, H2O and CO2 can show a vibrational absorption spectrum.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of bending molecular vibration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twisting",
            "b) Stretching",
            "c) Wagging",
            "d) Rocking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Stretching is not a type of bending molecular vibration. Twisting, wagging and rocking are types of bending molecular vibration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "What is the absorption frequency(cm-1) of –C=N functional group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3610-3640",
            "b) 1690-1760",
            "c) 1180-1360",
            "d) 2850-2960"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The absorption frequency for –C=N group is 1180-1360 cm-1. Absorption spectroscopy refers to spectroscopic techniques that measure the absorption of radiation, as a function of frequency or wavelength, due to its interaction with a sample.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Presence of a functional group in a compound can be established by using _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chromatography",
            "b) IR spectroscopy",
            "c) Mass spectroscopy",
            "d) X-ray diffraction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Presence of a functional group in a compound can be established by using IR spectroscopy. It is the spectroscopy that deals with the infrared region of the electromagnetic spectrum, that is light with a longer wavelength and lower frequency than visible light.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect option from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) IR spectroscopy helps in the determination of purity",
            "b) IR spectroscopy helps in the determination of force constant from vibrational spectrum",
            "c) IR spectroscopy helps in identifying an unknown compound",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the options are correct. IR spectroscopy helps in the determination of purity, force constant from the vibrational spectrum and identifying an unknown compound.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "The nuclei with a spin quantum number greater than _______ can exhibit the NMR phenomenon.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 10",
            "d) -5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The nuclei with a spin quantum number greater than zero can exhibit the NMR phenomenon. Nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, NMR spectroscopy, is a research technique that exploits the magnetic properties of certain atomic nuclei.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The number of different orientations which a magnetic nucleus can take is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2I",
            "b) 2I-1",
            "c) 2I+1",
            "d) 4I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The number of different orientations that a magnetic nucleus can take is 2I+1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Number of NMR signals obtained in CH3COCH3  will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Number of NMR signals obtained in CH3COCH3 will be 1. Nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, is a research technique that exploits the magnetic properties of certain atomic nuclei.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) TMS stands for tetra methyl silane",
            "b) All the hydrogen in TMS have the same chemical shift",
            "c) TMS has a high boiling point, so it is not easily lost when holding the NMR sample",
            "d) TMS is relatively unreactive with most functional groups"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Propene as well as 2-Butene(cis) will not show equal number of signals in their NMR spectra.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "The NMR spectra of the functional isomers of the molecular formula C2H6O show _________ and _________ signals respectively.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1, 2",
            "b) 1, 3",
            "c) 1, 4",
            "d) 1, 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: TMS has a low boiling point so it can be easily removed from a recoverable sample of an organic compound. All the other options are correct. TMS is relatively unreactive with most functional groups.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "The number of signals in 1-propanol are _________ while those in 2-propanol are ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4, 3",
            "b) 4, 2",
            "c) 2, 4",
            "d) 3, 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The NMR spectra of the functional isomers of the molecular formula C2H6O show one and three signals respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "In how many ways –CH3 protons can couple with the protons on adjacent carbon atom relative to the external field.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of signals in 1-propanol are 4 while those in 2-propanol are 3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Which of the following is inversely proportional to the chemical shifts positions (δ)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency of unknown group of protons",
            "b) Frequency of TMS",
            "c) Operating frequency of the instrument",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the NMR spectrum, carbon tetra-chloride and water can be successfully used as a solvent. NMR is routinely used in advanced medical imaging techniques, such as in magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Electronegativity is defined as the power of an atom in a molecule to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Repel electrons towards itself",
            "b) Attract electrons towards itself",
            "c) Expand itself",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Electronegativity is defined as the power of an atom in a molecule to attract electrons towards itself. Fluorine is the most electronegative element.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "The factors on which electronegativity depends upon ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Valence state of atom",
            "b) Hybridisation",
            "c) Both valence state and hybridisation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The factors on which electronegativity depends upon is valence state of atom and hybridisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "How does the electronegativiy get affected with the negative oxidation state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It decreases",
            "b) It increases",
            "c) It remains constant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electronegativity decreases with the negative oxidation state since the tendency to attract an electron will decrease with the negative charge of the anion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "The electronegativity of sp2 hybridised atom will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.29",
            "b) 2.48",
            "c) 3.69",
            "d) 2.75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The electronegativity of sp2 hybridised atom will be 2.75. Fluorine is the most electronegative element.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a permanent electron displacement effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductomeric",
            "b) Electromeric",
            "c) Inductive",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inductive effect is the permanent electron displacement effect and inductomeric and electromeric are temporary electron displacement effects.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Arrange the following groups in the order of decreasing (+I) effect.",
        "Options": [
            "a) C6H5O– > COO– > CR3 > CHR2 > H",
            "b) C6H5O– > H > CR3 > CHR2 > COO–",
            "c) CR3 > C6H5O– > H > COO– > CHR2",
            "d) C6H5O– > COO– > CHR2 > CR3 > H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct order is- C6H5O– > COO– > CR3 > CHR2 > H.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Arrange the following groups in the order of decreasing (-I) effect.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CN > F > Br > Cl > COOH > I > H",
            "b) COOH > CN > F > Br > Cl > I > H",
            "c) H > COOH > CN > I > Cl > F > Cl",
            "d) CN > COOH > F > Cl > Br > I > H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The correct order is- CN > COOH > F > Cl > Br > I > H.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of inductive effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bond length",
            "b) Dipole moment",
            "c) Strength of carboxylic acids",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bond length, dipole moment and strength of carboxylic acids are some of the applications of inductive effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Relative basic strength of amines does not depend upon ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductive effect",
            "b) Mesomeric effect",
            "c) Steric effect",
            "d) Stabilisation of cation by hydration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Relative basic strength of amines does not depend upon mesomeric effect. This effect is used in a qualitative way and describes the electron withdrawing or releasing properties of substituents based on relevant resonance structures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Due to presence of C – X polar bond in alkyl halide, alkyl halides are ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) More reactive than corresponding alkane",
            "b) Less reactive than corresponding alkane",
            "c) Equally reactive as corresponding alkane",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Due to the presence of C – X polar bond in alkyl halide, alkyl halides are more reactive than corresponding alkane.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a temporary effect brought into play at the requirement of attacking reagent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductive effect",
            "b) Mesomeric effect",
            "c) Electromeric effect",
            "d) Inductomeric effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Electromeric effect is a temporary effect brought into play at the requirement of attacking reagent. Electromeric effect refers to a molecular polarizability effect occurring by an intra-molecular electron displacement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) When multiple bonds are present between two different atoms, electromeric shift towards the more electronegative atom takes place",
            "b) When multiple bonds are present between two similar atoms, the first possibility is symmetric alkenes or alkynes",
            "c) When multiple bonds are present between two similar atoms, the second possibility is asymmetric alkenes or alkynes",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: When multiple bonds are present between two different atoms, electromeric shift towards the more electronegative atom takes place. When multiple bonds are present between two similar atoms, the first possibility is symmetric alkenes or alkyne and the second possibility is asymmetric alkenes or alkynes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conjugate effect is stronger than (-I) effect",
            "b) Conjugate effect is weaker than (-I) effect",
            "c) Conjugate effect is same as (-I) effect",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Conjugate effect is stronger than (-I) effect. Conjugate effect (or delocalization) is an effect in which molecular orbitals (MOs) are conjugated to new molecular orbitals that are more delocalized and therefore generally lower in energy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "When the complete transfer of π-electrons take place away from the atom at the requirement of attacking agent, it is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (-E) effect",
            "b) (+E) effect",
            "c) (-I) effect",
            "d) (+I) effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the complete transfer of π-electrons takes place away from the atom at the requirement of attacking agent, it is called (+E) effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "The positively charged and electron deficient compounds which have a tendency to form a bond by accepting the electron pair are known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electrophiles",
            "b) Nucleophiles",
            "c) Homophiles",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The positively charged and electron deficient compounds which have a tendency to form a bond by accepting the electron pair are known as electrophiles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of lewis base?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ZnCl2",
            "b) BF3",
            "c) NH3",
            "d) FeCl2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: NH3 is an example of lewis base and ZnCl2, BF3 and FeCl2 are the examples of lewis acid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an incorrect statement about the nucleophiles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are electron rich",
            "b) They possess an empty orbital to receive the electron pair",
            "c) They attack electron deficient centres",
            "d) Examples are: OH–, NH3, H2O etc"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nucleophiles possess an unshared electron pair which is not firmly held to the nucleus. All the other options are correct. They are electron rich and attack on electron deficient centres. Examples are: OH–, NH3, H2O etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Those groups which are electron repelling and have lesser electron attracting power than hydrogen show __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (+E) effect",
            "b) (-E) effect",
            "c) (-I) effect",
            "d) (+I) effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lewis acids are the examples of electrophilic reagents and Lewis bases are the examples of nucleophilic reagents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Which of the following molecule will show highest dipole moment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CH3Cl",
            "b) CH3Br",
            "c) CH3F",
            "d) CH3I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Those groups which are electron repelling and have lesser electron attracting power than hydrogen show (+I) effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "In mesomeric effect, the electrons are transferred from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A multiple bonds to an atom",
            "b) A multiple bonds to a single covalent bond",
            "c) An atom with a lone pair to the adjacent single covalent bond",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the mesomeric effect, the electrons are transferred from multiple bonds to an atom, a multiple bond to a single covalent bond and an atom with the lone pair to the adjacent single covalent bond.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a resonance effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductive effect",
            "b) Electromeric effect",
            "c) Mesomeric effect",
            "d) Inductomeric effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mesomeric effect is also known as the resonance effect. The mesomeric effect is a permanent effect and operates in compounds containing at least one double bond.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "The phenomenon in which 2 or more structures, involving identical position of atoms can be written for a particular molecule, is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conjugation",
            "b) Resonance",
            "c) Hyper conjugation",
            "d) Vibration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The phenomenon in which 2 or more structures, involving the identical position of atoms can be written for a particular molecule, is called resonance. The mesomeric effect is a permanent effect and operates in compounds containing at least one double bond.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect option from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resonating structures have a real existence",
            "b) The actual structure lies between various possible resonating structures",
            "c) Resonating structures are useful as they allow us to describe molecules",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Resonating structures have no real existence. All the other options are correct. The actual structure lies between various possible resonating structures, resonating structures are useful as they allow us to describe molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "The resonance energy is defined as a difference in energy between __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two consecutive resonating structures",
            "b) Resonance hybrid and most unstable resonating structure",
            "c) Resonance hybrid and most stable resonating structure",
            "d) First and last resonating structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The resonance energy is defined as a difference in energy between resonance hybrid and most stable resonating structure. The resonance energy of a compound is a measure of the extra stability of the conjugated system compared to the corresponding number of isolated double bonds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of the mesomeric effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dipole moment",
            "b) Strength of acids and bases",
            "c) Bond length",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dipole moment, strength of acids and bases and bond length are some of the applications of the mesomeric effect.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benzene ring has two different types of bond length for single and double bonds",
            "b) All the bond length in benzene ring is equal due to hyperconjugation",
            "c) All the bond length in benzene ring is equal due to resonance",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dipole moment of CH3-CH2-Cl > CH2=CH-Cl. This is due to resonance in vinyl chloride.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Greater the number of resonating structures for a given intermediate __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less will be its stability",
            "b) More will be its stability",
            "c) It will not affect its stability",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All the bond length in the benzene ring is equal due to resonance. All the bond lengths are equal in benzene ring i.e. double bond as well as single bond due to resonance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Phenyl group show __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (+M) effect",
            "b) (+E) effect",
            "c) (+I) effect",
            "d) (-M) effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Greater the number of resonating structures for a given intermediate, more will be its stability. More resonating structure increases stability.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Which of the following is known as Baker-Nathan effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mesomeric effect",
            "b) Inductive effect",
            "c) Hyperconjugation",
            "d) Electromeric effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Hyperconjugation is also known as Baker-Nathan effect. Hyperconjugation is the stabilising interaction that results from the interaction of the electrons in a σ-bond (usually C-H or C-C) with an adjacent empty or partially filled p-orbital or a π-orbital to give an extended molecular orbital that increases the stability of the system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Hyperconjugation involves the delocalisation of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) σ bond orbital",
            "b) π bond orbital",
            "c) Both σ and π bond orbital",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hyperconjugation involves the delocalisation of σ bond orbital. It is the stabilising interaction that results from the interaction of the electrons in a σ-bond (usually C-H or C-C) with an adjacent empty or partially filled p-orbital or a π-orbital to give an extended molecular orbital that increases the stability of the system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Number of hyperconjugation structures in isopropyl radical is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Number of hyperconjugation structures in isopropyl radical is 6. Isopropyl is C3H7.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "The resonance energy (kCal/mol) of tertiary butyl is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 11",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The resonance energy of tertiary butyl is 12 kCal/mol. It is also called tert-butanol, is the simplest tertiary alcohol, with a formula of (CH3)3COH It is one of the four isomers of butanol.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Larger the number of hyperconjugation structures, the stability of free radicals will __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Larger the number of hyperconjugation structures, greater will be the stability of free radicals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a consequence of Baker-Nathan effect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is helpful in explaining the directive influence of alkyl groups in aromatic alkyl benzene",
            "b) It is helpful in explaining the relative stability of alkenes",
            "c) It is helpful in explaining the relative stabilities of alkyl carbocations",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Baker-Nathan effect is helpful in explaining the directive influence of alkyl groups in aromatic alkyl benzene. It is helpful in explaining the relative stability of alkenes and relative stabilities of alkyl carbocations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "On increasing the number of α-hydrogens, the number of hyperconjugation structures will __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease",
            "b) Increase",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On increasing the number of α-hydrogens, the number of hyperconjugation structures will increase. Hyperconjugation is directly proportional to the number of α-hydrogens. α-hydrogen is the hydrogen atom attached to the carbon which is attached to a functional group.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "When the contributing structure contains the same number of two-electron bonds as the normal lewis formula, it will be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heterovalent hyperconjugation",
            "b) Sacrificial hyperconjugation",
            "c) Isovalent hyperconjugation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When the contributing structure contains the same number of two-electron bonds as the normal lewis formula, it will be isovalent hyperconjugation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "The compound that can be most readily sulphonated is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benzene",
            "b) Toluene",
            "c) Nitrobenzene",
            "d) Chlorobenzene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The compound that can be most readily sulphonated is toluene. Toulene contains a methyl group with benzene ring and is a colorless, water-insoluble liquid with the smell associated with paint thinners.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "A covalent bond between two atoms may be broken in different ways depending upon __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nature of given organic compound",
            "b) Nature of attacking reagent",
            "c) Reaction conditions",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A covalent bond between two atoms may be broken in different ways depending upon nature of given organic compound, nature of attacking reagent and reaction conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fission of covalent bond leads to the generation of intermediate organic species",
            "b) They are stable and long-lived",
            "c) The presence of reactive intermediates is confirmed by their detection by spectroscopic methods",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The intermediate species are unstable and short-lived. All the other options are correct. Fission of covalent bond leads to the generation of intermediate organic species. The presence of reactive intermediates is confirmed by their detection by spectroscopic methods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "The breaking of a covalent bond in such a way that each atom separates with one electron of the shared pair is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homolytic fission",
            "b) Heterolytic fission",
            "c) Monolytic fission",
            "d) Morpholytic fission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The breaking of a covalent bond in such a way that each atom separates with one electron of the shared pair is called homolytic fission. Homo refers to same and in this fission every atom has same number of electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "The breaking of a covalent bond in such a way that both the electrons of shared pair are carried away by one of atom is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Morpholytic fission",
            "b) Monolytic fission",
            "c) Heterolytic fission",
            "d) Homolytic fission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The breaking of a covalent bond in such a way that both the electrons of shared pair are carried away by one of atom is called heterolytic fission. Hetero refers to different and in this fission every atom has different number of electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Heterolytic fission takes place between two atoms of widely different __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conductivity",
            "b) Viscosity",
            "c) Electronegtivity",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Heterolytic fission takes place between two atoms of widely different electronegativity. The more electronegative atom will not attract the electron as compared to less electronegative atom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heterolytic fission takes place generally in a polar solvent",
            "b) Heterolytic fission takes place usually at higher temperatures",
            "c) Cations and anions formed are generally carbon-based",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Heterolytic fission takes place usually at lower temperatures. All the other options are correct. Heterolytic fission takes place generally in a polar solvent and cations and anions formed are generally carbon-based.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Which of the following is intermediate organic species based on carbon formed by homolytic fission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbenes",
            "b) Carbo-cations",
            "c) Carbanions",
            "d) Free radicals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Free radicals are intermediate organic species based on carbon formed by homolytic fission. Free radicals are different from cations and anions. They do not carry any charge with them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following is intermediate organic species based on carbon formed by photolysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbenes",
            "b) Carbo-cations",
            "c) Carbanions",
            "d) Free radicals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Carbenes are intermediate organic species based on carbon formed by photolysis. A carbene is a molecule containing a neutral carbon atom with a valence of two and two unshared valence electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "The shape of carbanion is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Trigonal planar",
            "c) Pyramidal",
            "d) Bent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Triplet carbene is more stable than singlet carbene. A carbene is a molecule containing a neutral carbon atom with a valence of two and two unshared valence electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Stability of free radicals can be explained on the basis of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductive effect",
            "b) Electromeric effect",
            "c) Hyperconjugation",
            "d) Mesomeric effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Stability of free radicals can be explained on the basis of hyperconjugation effect and ease of formation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "The hybridisation of carbocation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sp",
            "b) Sp2",
            "c) Sp3",
            "d) Sp3d"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The hybridisation of carbocation is sp2. A carbocation is molecule in which a carbon atom bears three bonds and a positive charge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Arrange the following carbocations in the order of increasing stability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benzyl > 30 > 20 > 10",
            "b) Benzyl > 10 > 20 > 30",
            "c) 30 > 20 > 10 > Benzyl",
            "d) 10 > 20 > 30 > Benzyl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct stability order of carbocation is- Benzyl > 30 > 20 > 10. Benzyl carbocation is the most stable and 10 carbocation is least stable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "The shape of carbocation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyramidal",
            "b) Bent",
            "c) Linear",
            "d) Trigonal planar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The shape of the carbocation is a trigonal planar. It is sp2 hybridised. A carbocation is molecule in which a carbon atom bears three bonds and a positive charge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Carbonium ions are the intermediates in which the positive charge is carried by the carbon atom with ___________ electrons in the valence shell.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Carbonium ions are the intermediates in which the positive charge is carried by the carbon atom with six electrons in the valence shell. It is an organic cation in which the positive charge is located on a carbon atom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Positive charge of carbocations can be dispersed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (+I) effect of alkyl group",
            "b) Resonance in allyl or benzyl carbocation",
            "c) Hyperconjugation in 10, 20 and 30 carbocations",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Positive charge of carbocations can be dispersed by (+I) effect of alkyl group or by resonance in allyl or benzyl carbocation or by hyperconjugation in 10, 20 and 30 carbocations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "The formal charge at the carbocation is equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) -1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) +1",
            "d) +2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alkyl substitution at the carbon bearing positive charge stabilizes carbocations. Carbocation is a molecule in which a carbon atom bears three bonds and a positive charge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "The homolytic bond dissociation energy is inversely proportional to the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bond length",
            "b) Ease of formation",
            "c) Dipole moment",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The formal charge at the carbocation is equal to +1. A carbocation is molecule in which a carbon atom bears three bonds and a positive charge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Which of the following free radical has the maximum ease of formation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) CH3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The homolytic bond dissociation energy is inversely proportional to the ease of formation of free radicals. Free radicals do not carry any charge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbanion is the intermediate compound",
            "b) In carbanion, central carbon atom carries negative charge",
            "c) It possess an unshared pair of electron",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Carbanion is the intermediate compound in which central carbon atom carries a negative charge and it possess the unshared pair of electron. It is an anion in which carbon has an unshared pair of electrons and bears a negative charge usually with three substituents for a total of eight valence electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "The hybridisation of carbanion is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sp",
            "b) Sp2",
            "c) Sp3",
            "d) Sp3d"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hybridisation of carbanion is sp3. A carbanion is an anion in which carbon has an unshared pair of electrons and bears a negative charge usually with three substituents for a total of eight valence electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "The formal charge at the carbanion is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) +1",
            "b) -1",
            "c) 0",
            "d) +2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The formal charge at the carbanion is -1.  A carbanion is an anion in which carbon has an unshared pair of electrons and bears a negative charge usually with three substituents for a total of eight valence electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "The geometry of carbanion is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyramidal",
            "b) Linear",
            "c) Tetrahedral",
            "d) Trigonal planar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The geometry of carbanion is pyramidal.  A carbanion is an anion in which carbon has an unshared pair of electrons and bears a negative charge usually with three substituents for a total of eight valence electrons.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Negative charge of carbanion can be dispersed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) (+I) effect and resonance",
            "b) (-I) effect and resonance",
            "c) Hyperconjugation",
            "d) (+M) effect and resonance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The structure of carbanion is pyramidal but it undergoes rapid inversion similar to those of amines. The carbanion exists in a trigonal pyramidal geometry. Formally, a carbanion is the conjugate base of a carbon acid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which of the following carbanion is least stable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) CH3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Negative charge of carbanion can be dispersed by (+I) effect and resonance. A carbanion is a nucleophile. The stability and reactivity of a carbanion is determined by several factors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which of the following carbanion is most stable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) CH3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 30 carbanion is the least stable carbanion. The same factors that determine the stability of the carbanion also determine the order in pKa in carbon acids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "On increasing the number of alkyl groups, the stability of carbanions ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: CH3 carbanion is the most stable carbanion. The same factors that determine the stability of the carbanion also determine the order in pKa in carbon acids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The atom which defines the structure of a family of organic compounds and their properties is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resonating structure",
            "b) Homologous structure",
            "c) Functional group",
            "d) Nucleophile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The atom which defines the structure of a family of organic compounds and their properties is called a functional group.  Functional groups are specific groups of atoms or bonds within molecules that are responsible for the characteristic chemical reactions of those molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "The functional group in alkyl halide is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydroxyl group",
            "b) Halogen atom",
            "c) Inert gas",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The functional group in alkyl halide is a halogen atom. Halide refers to halogen. Halogens are a group in the periodic table consisting of five chemically related elements: fluorine (F), chlorine (Cl), bromine (Br), iodine (I), and astatine (At).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "The halide ion is an extremely ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weak base",
            "b) Weak acid",
            "c) Strong base",
            "d) Strong acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The halide ion is an extremely weak base because hydrogen halide are acidic as they release a proton."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "When the nucleophile :OR attacks the RX, the resultant product will be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R – OH",
            "b) ROR",
            "c) R:CN",
            "d) RNHR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When the nucleophile :OR attacks the RX, the resultant product will be ROR. X will be separated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Select the correct statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SN2 reaction follows second order kinetics",
            "b) No intermediate is involved in SN2 mechanism",
            "c) SN2 reactions are one-step reaction",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SN2 reaction follows second order kinetics and no intermediate is involved in it. So, SN2 reactions are one-step reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "The reactivity order of alkyl halides in SN2 is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CH3 X > 10 > 20 > 30",
            "b) CH3 X > 20 > 10 > 30",
            "c) CH3 X > 30 > 10 > 20",
            "d) CH3 X > 30 > 20 > 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct order of reactivity in alkyl halide is- CH3 X > 10 > 20 > 30. CH3 X is most reactive whereas 30 is least reactive.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Which step in SN1 reaction is a slow rate determining step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attack of nucleophile",
            "b) Formation of a racemic mixture",
            "c) Formation of a transition state",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SN1 reaction involves heterolysis to form the carbocation as an intermediate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "A low concentration of nucleophile favours the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SN2 reaction",
            "b) SN1 reaction",
            "c) Both SN1 and SN1 reaction",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first step of formation of the transition state is a slow rate determining step in SN1 reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of the following reactions are favoured by polar aprotic solvent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SN1 reactions",
            "b) SN2 reactions",
            "c) Both SN1 and SN1 reactions",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A low concentration of nucleophile favours the SN1 reaction but high concentration of nucleophile favours the SN2 reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "Arrange the following in the decreasing order of leaving group in nucleophilic substitution reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) H– > Cl– > HO– > Br– > CH3COO–",
            "b) Cl– > Br– > HO– > H– > CH3COO–",
            "c) Cl– > Br– > CH3COO – > HO– > H–",
            "d) HO– > CH3COO – > H– > Br– > Cl–"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: SN1 reactions are favoured by polar protic solvents whereas SN2 reactions are favoured by polar aprotic solvent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Reaction of alcohol with SOCl2 is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SN1",
            "b) SN2",
            "c) SNAr",
            "d) SNi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The correct order is- Cl– > Br– > CH3COO – > HO– > H–.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The nucleophilic substitutions do not occur in haloarenes because ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The carbon-halogen bond is much shorter",
            "b) The carbon-halogen bond is stronger compared to that in haloalkanes",
            "c) The lone pair of electrons on the halogen participates in delocalisation with the π-electrons of benzene ring",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reaction of alcohol with SOCl2 proceeds with retention of configuration via substitution nucleophilic internal (SNi) mechanism.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Which of the following drastic condition is required for the substitution in haloarenes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High temperature",
            "b) High pressure",
            "c) Strong concentrated reagent",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The nucleophilic substitutions do not occur in haloarenes because the carbon-halogen bond is much shorter and stronger compared to that in haloalkanes and the lone pair of electrons on the halogen participates in delocalisation with the π-electrons of benzene ring.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "The rate of nucleophilic substitution reactions are higher in the presence of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Electron withdrawing groups",
            "b) Electron releasing groups",
            "c) Both electron withdrawing and releasing groups",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Drastics conditions like high temperature, high pressure and strong concentrated reagents are used to carry substitution in haloarenes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "Which of the following is rate determining step in electrophilic substitution reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generation of electrophile",
            "b) Attack by an electrophilic reagent on benzene ring",
            "c) Formation of product",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Attack by an electrophilic reagent on benzene ring is a rate determining step in electrophilic substitution reaction. It is also the slowest step of the reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as catalysis in the nitration of benzene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conc. HCl",
            "b) Dil. HCl",
            "c) Conc. H2SO4",
            "d) Dil. H2SO4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conc. H2SO4 act as a catalysis in the nitration of benzene. Benzene is treated with a mixture of concentrated nitric acid and concentrated sulphuric acid at a temperature not exceeding 50°C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Fuming sulphuric acid is the solution of _________% SO3 in conc. H2SO4.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 9",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fuming sulphuric acid is the solution of 7% SO3 in conc. H2SO4. It is also called Oleum which is produced in the contact process, where sulphur is oxidized to sulphur trioxide which is subsequently dissolved in concentrated sulphuric acid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the necessary condition for desulphonation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Remove volatile hydrocarbon by steam distillation",
            "b) Low concentration of water",
            "c) High concentration of sulphonating agent",
            "d) A large excess of fuming sulphuric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The necessary condition for desulphonation is to Use dilute acid, high concentration of water and remove volatile hydrocarbon by steam distillation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as electrophile in halogenation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitronium ion",
            "b) Sulphonium ion",
            "c) Halonium ion",
            "d) Acylium ion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Halonium ion act as electrophile in halogenation. Nitronium ion is used in nitration. Sulphonium ion is used in sulphonation. Acylium ion is used in acylation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Aromatic bromination catalyzed by the Lewis acid thalium acetate gives ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Para isomer",
            "b) Ortho isomer",
            "c) Meta isomer",
            "d) Para and ortho isomer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aromatic bromination catalyzed by the Lewis acid thalium acetate gives only para isomer. It is not Ortho and meta directing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "The reaction in which benzene reacts with alkyl halide in the presence of a lewis acid as a catalyst to produce alkylbenzene is known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitration",
            "b) Halogenation",
            "c) Friedel-Crafts Acylation",
            "d) Friedel-Crafts Alkylation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The reaction in which benzene reacts with alkyl halide in the presence of a lewis acid as a catalyst to produce alkylbenzene is known as Friedel-Crafts Alkylation. With anhydrous ferric chloride as a catalyst, the alkyl group attaches at the former site of the chloride ion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a product of the reaction of benzene with CH3Cl and AlCl3?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toulene",
            "b) Isopropyl benzene",
            "c) O-xylene",
            "d) P-xylene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: p-xylene is not a product of reaction of benzene with CH3Cl and AlCl3. Toulene, isopropyl benzene and O-xylene are the products of such reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "The product of Friedel-Crafts Acylation reactions are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alkylbenzene",
            "b) Alkylamine",
            "c) Arylketone",
            "d) Halobenzene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The product of Friedel-Crafts Acylation reactions are Arylketone. The acylated products may easily be converted to the corresponding alkanes via Clemmensen Reduction or Wolff-Kishner Reduction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "How will you convert benzene into n-propyl benzene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Friedel-Crafts Alkylation",
            "b) Friedel-Crafts Acylation",
            "c) Friedel-Crafts Alkylation followed by clemmensen reduction",
            "d) Friedel-Crafts Acylation followed by clemmensen reduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Friedel-Crafts Acylation followed by clemmensen reduction of ketone will give n-propyl benzene. Clemmensen reduction is a chemical reaction described as a reduction of ketones (or aldehydes) to alkanes using zinc amalgam and hydrochloric acid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "An activating substituent group activates ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ortho position",
            "b) Para position",
            "c) Both ortho and para positions",
            "d) Meta position"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An activating substituent group activates the ortho and para positions. It does not activate the meta position.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "A deactivating substituent group directs ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ortho position",
            "b) Para position",
            "c) Both ortho and para positions",
            "d) Meta position"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A deactivating substituent group directs only meta position. It does not activate ortho or para positions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Which of the following is ortho-para directing group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) –NHCOCH3",
            "b) –NO2",
            "c) –CN",
            "d) –CHO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NHCOCH3 is ortho-para directing group. NO, CN and CHO are meta-directing groups.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a meta directing group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) –NHCOCH3",
            "b) –COOH",
            "c) –OH",
            "d) –OCH3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: -COOH is a meta directing group. All the other options are ortho-para directing groups.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "The most stable carbonium ion is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methyl carbonium ion",
            "b) 20 carbonium ion",
            "c) 10 carbonium ion",
            "d) 30 carbonium ion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most stable crbonium ion is 30 carbonium ion. The least stable is primary or 10 carbonium ion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the highest activation of the benzene ring?",
        "Options": [
            "a) – NHCOCH3",
            "b) –OH",
            "c) –NH2",
            "d) –C6H5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: –NH2 among the following has the highest activation of the benzene ring.  In cases where the substituents are esters or amides, they are less activating because they form resonance structure that pull the electron density away from the ring.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "HBr reacts fastest with ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-methylpropan-2-ol",
            "b) Propan-1-ol",
            "c) Propan-2-ol",
            "d) 2-methylpropan-1-ol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HBr reacts fastest with 2-methylpropan-2-ol. Hydrogen bromide is the diatomic molecule and a colorless compound.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "The compound that can be most readily sulphonated is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benzene",
            "b) Nitrobenzene",
            "c) Toluene",
            "d) Chlorobenzene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The compound that can be most readily sulphonated is toluene. Toulene contains CH3 group.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "In Cannizaro reaction, two molecules of aldehydes are reacted to produce ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol only",
            "b) Carboxylic acid only",
            "c) Alcohol and carboxylic acid",
            "d) Alcohol, carboxylic acid and ketone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Cannizaro reaction, two molecules of aldehydes are reacted to produce alcohol and carboxylic acid using a hydroxide base.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Reaction kinetics deals with the study of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rate of reaction",
            "b) Mechanism of reaction",
            "c) Factors which affects the rate of reaction",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reaction kinetics deals with the study of rate of reaction, their mechanism and the factors which affects the rate of reaction. It specifies all the general characteristics of a chemical reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "The reaction rate is defined as the rate at which the concentration of the reactants __________ with time or the concentration of products ___________ with time.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase, increase",
            "b) Decrease, decrease",
            "c) Decrease, increase",
            "d) Increase, decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reaction rate is defined as the rate at which the concentration of the reactants decreases with time or the concentration of products increases with time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "The unit of rate of reaction is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mol L-1 s-1",
            "b) Mol L s-1",
            "c) Mol L-1 s",
            "d) Mol L s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unit of rate of reaction is Mol L-1 s-1. The reaction rate is defined as the rate at which the concentration of the reactants decreases with time or the concentration of products increases with time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "The reaction rate constant may be defined as the rate of the reaction when the concentration of each reactants is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Unity",
            "c) Doubled the initial concentration",
            "d) Infinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The order of the reaction can be zero, fractional or integer and it is always experimentally determined. The order of reaction with respect to a given substance is defined as the index, or exponent, to which its concentration term in the rate equation is raised.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "The unit s-1 is the unit of rate constant for the reaction of the order is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reaction rate constant may be defined as the rate of the reaction when the concentration of each reactants is unity. A reaction rate constant or reaction rate coefficient, k, quantifies the rate of a chemical reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "The unit of rate constant for the second order reaction will be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) s-1",
            "b) L mol-1 s-1",
            "c) Mol0.5 L-0.5 s-1",
            "d) Mol L-1 s-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The unit s-1 is the unit of rate constant for the reaction of the order zero. It quantifies the rate of a chemical reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "The unit L mol-1 s-1 is the unit of rate constant for the reaction of the order is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The unit of rate constant for the second order reaction will be mol0.5 L-0.5 s-1.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "Molecularity of a reaction is equal to the total number of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Products formed in the elementary step",
            "b) Reactants taking part in elementary step",
            "c) Reactants and products in the elementary step",
            "d) Reactants and products in the final step"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Molecularity of a reaction is equal to the total number of reactants taking part in an elementary step. It is defined as the number of molecules or ions that participate in the rate determining step.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "The elementary processes with molecularity greater than ________ are not known.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The molecularity of a multi-step reaction does not make any sense. The molecularity of each step is different. And molecularity of one step can only be determined at a time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the molecularity of a reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is a theoretical concept",
            "b) Each step of a multi-step reaction has a unique molecularity",
            "c) It  is equal to the total number of reactants taking part in elementary step",
            "d) It can be zero, fractional or integer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The elementary processes with molecularity greater than three are not known. There is no such reaction which has the molecularity greater than three.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "Which of the following factor does not effect the rate of reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration of the reactant",
            "b) Temperature",
            "c) Pressure",
            "d) Effect of catalyst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Molecularity is always a whole number. It can be neither zero nor fractional. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "The effective collisions between the reactant molecules at higher temperatures ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) First increase then decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reaction rate does not depend upon the pressure. It only depends upon the concentration of the reactant, temperature and effect of catalyst.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Concentration of the reactants is __________ proportional to the number of collisions and _________ proportional to the reaction rate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Directly, inversely",
            "b) Directly, directly",
            "c) Inversely, directly",
            "d) Inversely, inversely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The effective collisions between the reactant molecules at higher temperatures increase. At higher temperature randomness increases and molecules moves with a faster velocity which results in more collision between the reactants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "The reaction rate is greatly influenced by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nature of bond in the reactant molecules",
            "b) Strength of bond in the reactant molecules",
            "c) Both nature and strength of the reactant molecules",
            "d) It does not depend on either nature or strength of the reactant molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Concentration of the reactants is directly proportional to the number of collisions and also directly proportional to the reaction rate. The more the collision, more will be the reaction rate and hence more will be the concentration of reactants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Select the correct option from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Catalyst is used to increase the rate of reaction by altering chemically during the course of reaction",
            "b) Catalyst is used to decrease the rate of reaction by altering chemically during the course of reaction",
            "c) Catalyst is used to increase the rate of reaction and remains unaltered chemically during the course of reaction",
            "d) Catalyst is used to decrease the rate of reaction and remains altered chemically during the course of reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reaction rate is greatly influenced by both nature and strength of the reactant molecules. Reactants are the major factor that affects the rate of the reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "For a zero order reaction, the rate of reaction is independent of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Nature of reactants",
            "c) Concentration of reactants",
            "d) Effect of catalyst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For a zero order reaction, the rate of reaction is independent of the concentration of reactants. The rate law for a zero order reaction is R = K.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "The half-life period of zero order reaction is directly proportional to the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rate constant",
            "b) Initial concentration of reactants",
            "c) Final concentration of reactants",
            "d) Concentration of products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The half-life period of zero order reaction is directly proportional to the initial concentration of reactants. It is given by:\nt1/2 = [A0] / 2K .\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of zero order reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photochemical combination of hydrogen and chlorine",
            "b) Decomposition of ammonia over molybdenum surface",
            "c) Thermal decomposition of HI on gold surface",
            "d) Inversion of cane sugar in the presence of mineral acids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Inversion of cane sugar in the presence of mineral acids is not an example of zero order reaction. All the other options are the example of zero order reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "For a first order reaction, the half life period is independent of the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initial concentration of the reactants",
            "b) Final concentration of the reactants",
            "c) Rate constant",
            "d) Concentration of products"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a first order reaction, the half life period is independent of the initial concentration of the reactants. t1/2 = ln2 / K .\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "The thermal decomposition of nitrogen pentaoxide in the gaseous phase is the example of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero order reaction",
            "b) Half order reaction",
            "c) First order reaction",
            "d) Second order reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The thermal decomposition of nitrogen pentaoxide in the gaseous phase is the example of first order reaction. A first order reaction depends on the concentration of only one reactant (a unimolecular reaction).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "A compound decomposes according to the first order rate law with a half life period of 30 min. What will be the fraction of the remaining compound after 120 min?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.625",
            "b) 0.0625",
            "c) 0.25",
            "d) 0.025"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  k = 0.693/t1/2\n  K = (2.303/t) log ([R0]/[Rt]).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "In a first order reaction, the time required for the completion of 99% is _______ for its 90% completion.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Same",
            "b) Negligible",
            "c) Thrice",
            "d) Twice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a first order reaction, the time required for the completion of 99% is twice for its 90% completion. ln [A] = -kt + ln [A0].\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "In a first order reaction, the time required for the completion of 99% is _______  times the time required for the completion of half of the reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a first order reaction, the time required for the completion of 99% is ten times the time required for the completion of half of the reaction. ln [A] = -kt + ln [A0].\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "The half life period of first order reaction is 15 min. Its rate constant will be equal to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0462 min-1",
            "b) 0.462 min-1",
            "c) 0.00462 min-1",
            "d) 0.562 min-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  k = 0.693/t1/2\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of second order reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxidation of hydrogen bromide",
            "b) Saponification of ester",
            "c) Acid catalyzed hydrolysis of ester",
            "d) Gaseous decomposition of hydrogen iodide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: For a second order reaction, the rate is proportional to the square of the concentration of the same reactant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "The half life period of nth order reaction varies inversely to ____________ th power of the initial concentration of the reactants.",
        "Options": [
            "a) n",
            "b) 2n",
            "c) (n+1)",
            "d) (n-1)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acid catalyzed hydrolysis of an ester is not an example of second order reaction. All the other options are examples of second order reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "The order of the reaction, if the time of half-completion is changed from 50 sec to 25 sec, when the initial concentration is changed from 0.5 to 1M will be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The half life period of nth order reaction varies inversely to (n-1) th power of the initial concentration of the reactants. The half-life of a reaction describes the time needed for half of the reactant to be depleted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "Reactions which are bimolecular yet following ___________ order kinetics are called pseudo unimolecular reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) First",
            "c) Second",
            "d) Third"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Reactions that are bimolecular yet following first order kinetics are called pseudo unimolecular reaction. Pseudo means pretentious. Inversion of cane sugar is an example of pseudo first order reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of pseudo first order reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saponification of ester",
            "b) Oxidation of hydrogen bromide",
            "c) Gaseous decomposition of hydrogen iodide",
            "d) Inversion of cane sugar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Inversion of cane sugar is an example of pseudo first order reaction. All the other options are not the example of pseudo first order reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Which concentration plot is linear for a first order reaction? (A is one of the reactant)",
        "Options": [
            "a) [A] versus time",
            "b) [A]2 versus time",
            "c) Ln[A] versus time",
            "d) √[A] versus time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ln[A] versus time plot is linear and other graphs are curved for a first order reaction. For a zero order reaction, [A] versus time concentration plot is linear. For a second order reaction, 1/[A] versus time concentration plot is linear.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Based on the collision model, the atoms at the top of the potential energy hill are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transition state",
            "b) Energetic atom",
            "c) Steric factor",
            "d) Activation energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based on the collision model, the atoms at the top of the potential energy hill are called transition state. The transition state is the state corresponding to the highest energy along the reaction coordinate. It has more free energy in comparison to the substrate or product; thus, it is the least stable state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "What does termolecular refer to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 molecules colliding",
            "b) 3 molecules colliding",
            "c) 4 molecules colliding",
            "d) 5 molecules colliding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Termolecular means a collision of three molecules. Ter refers to three.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "For a certain reaction, the rate = k[NO]2[O2], when the initial concentration of NO is tripled, the initial rate ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases by a factor of nine",
            "b) Increases by a factor of three",
            "c) Increases by a factor of six",
            "d) Decreases by a factor of nine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For a certain reaction, the rate = k[NO]2[O2], when the initial concentration of NO is tripled, the initial rate increases by a factor of nine. Here, the reaction is of the order 3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "In a series of reactions, the rate determining step is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simplest",
            "b) Fast and complex",
            "c) Fastest",
            "d) Slowest"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In a series of reactions, the rate determining step is the slowest step. The rate determining step is the slowest step of a chemical reaction that determines the speed (rate) at which the overall reaction proceeds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Threshold energy is the sum of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal energy and external energy of reactants",
            "b) Activation energy and external energy of reactants",
            "c) Activation energy and internal energy of reactants",
            "d) Activation energy and thermal energy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Threshold energy is the sum of activation energy and internal energy of reactants. The threshold energy for the production of a particle is the minimum kinetic energy a pair of traveling particles must have when they collide.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Temperature dependence of reaction rates can be studied by plotting a graph between ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concentration of reactants and temperature",
            "b) Concentration of products and temperature",
            "c) Rate constant and temperature",
            "d) Rate of catalysis and temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Temperature dependence of reaction rates can be studied by plotting a graph between rate constant and temperature for different reactions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "The ratio of the rate constant of a reaction at two temperatures differing by __________0C is called temperature coefficient of reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio of the rate constant of a reaction at two temperatures differing by 100C is called temperature coefficient of reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "According to Arrhenius equation, rate constant(k) is proportional to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activation Energy (E)",
            "b) eE",
            "c) e1/E",
            "d) e-E"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Arrhenius equation, k = Ae-Ea/RT. So, rate constant(k) is proportional to e-E.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "How does half life period of a first order reaction vary with temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It increases",
            "b) It decreases",
            "c) It remains the same",
            "d) Both increases as well as decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Half-life period of a first order reaction is directly proportional to the rate constant. So, it increases with increase in temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "How many times the rate of reaction increases at 200C for a reaction having the activation energies in the presence and absence of catalyst as 50 kJ/mol and 75 kJ/mol?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000",
            "b) 10000",
            "c) 30000",
            "d) 50000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rate of reaction will increase 28,592 times, i.e. 30,000 times.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used to determine the order of the reaction in which two or more reactants take part?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integration method",
            "b) Half life period method",
            "c) Graphical method",
            "d) Ostwald’s isolation method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ostwald’s isolation method is used to determine the order of the reaction in which two or more reactants take part. Kinetic isolation conditions were identified that enabled determination of the reaction order for interfacial charge recombination.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is satisfactory only for a simple homogeneous reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integration method",
            "b) Half life period method",
            "c) Graphical method",
            "d) Ostwald’s isolation method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Integration method is satisfactory only for simple homogeneous reaction and lead to wrong conclusion for complex reactions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "A zero order reaction is one ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) In which rate is independent of reactants concentration",
            "b) In which one of the reactant is in large excess",
            "c) Whose rate is not affected by time",
            "d) Whose rate increases with time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A zero order reaction is one in which rate is independent of reactants concentration. It only depends upon the rate constant.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a category of catalysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homogeneous",
            "b) Heterogeneous",
            "c) Artificial",
            "d) Enzymatic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The four categories of catalysis are: homogeneous, heterogeneous, auto and enzymatic. Artificial is not a category of catalysis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of homogeneous catalysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enzyme catalysis",
            "b) Hardening of animal and vegetable oils",
            "c) Haber’s process",
            "d) Cracking of heavy oils for a synthesis of gasoline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Enzyme catalysis is an example of homogeneous catalysis. All the other options are not examples of homogeneous catalysis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as catalysis for Williamson’s etherification process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HCl",
            "b) NaCl",
            "c) KMnO4",
            "d) H2SO4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: H2SO4 act as catalysis for Williamson’s etherification process. The Williamson ether synthesis is an organic reaction, forming an ether from an organohalide and a deprotonated alcohol.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermediate compound formation theory fails to explain the action of promoters",
            "b) Intermediate compound formation theory fails to explain the function of a catalyst in homogeneous reactions",
            "c) Intermediate compound formation theory fails to explain the action of catalytic poisons",
            "d) Intermediate compound formation theory fails to explain the function of catalyst in heterogeneous reactions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Intermediate compound formation theory explains the function of a catalyst in homogeneous reactions. All the other options are correct. But it fails to explain the action of promoters, action of catalytic poisons and function of catalyst in heterogeneous reactions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement about the adsorption theory from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The surface of the solid catalyst possess some isolated active centres having residual affinity",
            "b) Due to these centres, the molecules of the gaseous reactants get adsorbed in unimolecular thick layer",
            "c) The adsorbed reactants get activated and then react",
            "d) The energy required for activation is more than that required for uncatalysed reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The energy required for activation is less than that required for uncatalysed reaction, and hence the reaction goes faster. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Which of the following step is the rate determining step of contact theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diffusion of reactants to surface",
            "b) Adsorption of reactants at the surface",
            "c) Chemical reaction at the surface",
            "d) Desorption of products from the surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: No definite intermediate compound formation takes place in contact theory. The contact hypothesis has been described as one of the best ways to improve relations among groups that are experiencing conflict.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the adsorption theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The catalyst  is more efficient in finely divided state",
            "b) Action of promoters is not explained",
            "c) Enhanced activity of a rough surfaced catalyst is explained",
            "d) Specific action of catalyst is explained"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chemical reaction at the surface is the slowest and rate determining step of contact theory. The contact hypothesis has been described as one of the best ways to improve relations among groups that are experiencing conflict.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "The factor which determines the activity of a heterogeneous catalyst is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Total surface area only",
            "b) The number of active sites per unit amount of catalyst only",
            "c) Method of preparation, prior treatment only",
            "d) Total surface area, number of active sites and method of preparation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Action of promoters and catalytic poisons is also explained. All the other options are correct. The catalyst is more efficient in the finely divided state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "What is the optimum temperature for Haber’s process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4500C",
            "b) 450C",
            "c) 1500C",
            "d) 3000C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors which determine the activity of a heterogeneous catalyst are – Total surface area, the number of active sites per unit amount of catalyst and method of preparation, prior treatment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is used for the manufacturing of acetic acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bosch’s process",
            "b) Deacon’s process",
            "c) Vinegar process",
            "d) Chamber process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The optimum temperature for Haber’s process is  4500C. Haber’s process is an industrial process for producing ammonia from nitrogen and hydrogen, using an iron catalyst at high temperature and pressure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Which of the following process is used for the preparation of sulphuric acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ostwald’s process",
            "b) Bergius process",
            "c) Deacon’s process",
            "d) Chamber process"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vinegar process is used for the manufacturing of acetic acid. The term “vinegar” actually refers to the two-step process of fermentation from carbohydrate to alcohol to acetic acid.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "What does Gibb’s phase rule state?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P+F=C-1",
            "b) P+F=C+1",
            "c) P+F=C-2",
            "d) P+F=C+2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The above phase rule is a formula that gives the condition for finding the number of phases in a system. This phase rule can be applied to both condensed as well as normal systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "What is the point at which all the three phases of a system exist?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triple point",
            "b) Sublimation point",
            "c) Vapor point",
            "d) Eutectic point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since at the triple point, the degree of freedom is zero (that is invariant reaction takes place at that point), therefore according to phase rule, F=C-P+2. Substituting the known values, we get P=3 (all states).  "
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "For water system, the number of phases at the triple point is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since at the triple point, the degree of freedom is zero, while applying the formula F=C-P+2, we get the number of phases as three because C=1, F=0 (since water system forms only single component). "
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Liquid phase exists for all compositions above _________ region.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eutectic region",
            "b) Equilibrium region",
            "c) Isometric region",
            "d) Sublimation region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a phase region above the eutectic point, both the solid and liquid phases exist together where the region is bi variant and this region is called isometric region. Here the region has 2 degrees of freedom."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Select the wrong statements from the following statements with respect to a phase diagram.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gives information about concentration",
            "b) Gives information about solubility",
            "c) Gives information on melting and boiling points",
            "d) Gives information on relative concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A phase diagram gives information only on the concentration of species, their solubility rate, degree of freedom and other physical properties. It does not explain about transformation rates and relative concentration (relative concentration=total concentration/equilibrium concentration)."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Select a non-homogeneous system from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salt solution",
            "b) Sugar solution",
            "c) Glucose in water",
            "d) Saturated solution of NaCl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A homogeneous mixture is one which is miscible completely with one another. In any saturated solution, when the amount of solute reaches more than a critical point, then the solution becomes heterogeneous."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Select the odd statement with respect to a phase reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saturated solution",
            "b) Equilibrium solution",
            "c) Concentric solution",
            "d) Amorphous solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A terminal solution, an intermediate solution, an equilibrium solution and concentric solutions, are the ones which take part in a phase reaction. On the other hand, a saturated solution is involved in the Lever system."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the formula for condense phase rule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F=C-P+2",
            "b) F=C-P+1",
            "c) F=C+P-2",
            "d) F=C+P-1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a condensed phase rule system, the phases are represented in three dimension which is not suitable for graphic purposes and hence the pressure is considered to be zero (this is helpful in drawing 2D images). Hence the formula reduces to F=C-P+2."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Under what condition, will we get a stable phase diagram?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solid + Liquid",
            "b) Solid + Vapor",
            "c) Liquid + vapor",
            "d) Liquid + Solid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Weiss law (which suits only for phase components), concentration at equilibrium is C=T/P. therefore in this case, C=1/1=1. This law is also called as Gibbs relativity law."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Which of the following equilibriums can phase rule be applies to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isometric",
            "b) Isobaric",
            "c) Isometric and Isobaric",
            "d) Mechanical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since phase rule can be applied to factors like solubility, concentration, reversibility of reaction, temperature, pressure, molecular weight, atomic weight, strength of molecules etc (since these parameters are applicable for isometric and isobaric states), phase rule can be applied to both isometric and isobaric equilibriums."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "What kind of particles can phase rule be applied to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro",
            "b) Nano",
            "c) Pico",
            "d) Heavy particles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since the factors like solubility, concentration, reversibility of reaction, temperature, pressure, molecular weight, atomic weight, strength of molecules etc becomes negligible for microscopic particles, phase rule identifies only heavy particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "What kind of behavior can phase rule identify?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Molecular behavior",
            "b) Linear behavior",
            "c) Curvic behavior",
            "d) Atomic behavior"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a general phase relation between temperature and concentration of the component of various systems, the general graph will show a proportionate relation between the two factors and hence phase rule identifies linear behavior."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "For Gibbs free energy along a system path for a transformation from state 1 to state 2, the reaction kinetics can be expressed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rate = C exp(-ΔG1/RT)",
            "b) Rate = C exp(-ΔG2/RT)",
            "c) Rate = G/RT",
            "d) Rate = RT/G"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the above problem, we can see that the reactions coordinate increases as the energy increases up to certain point above equilibrium and then it gradually decreases. This system represents a system at stable point of time. Thus according to energy phase relation, the rate of reaction is Rate = C exp(-ΔG1/RT)."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "According to Gibbs phase rule for a 2-component system under condensed rule, what observation can be made within the equilibrium phase?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T can be varied independently",
            "b) Varying a T value fixes the equilibrium compositions",
            "c) Neither T nor concentration can be varied respectively",
            "d) 2 phases cannot coexist"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During invariant position of the system (equilibrium state), sometimes due to increase in colligative properties of materials, the equilibrium faces a shift slightly. In this case, the equilibrium can be brought back by varying T values."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "If the following conditions result in the formation of a regular solution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ω = 0",
            "b) Ω > 0",
            "c) Ω < 0",
            "d) Ω = 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that as the resistance increases, conductance decreases. This happens at higher temperature and pressure. Thus a regular solution will be formed only when conductivity of the solution is high. Thus the required condition is Ω < 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "With respect to the general phase diagram of two component system. Identify the type of solution formed at the eutectic point.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regular solution",
            "b) Steady state solution",
            "c) Invariant solution",
            "d) Transition solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From the general phase diagram, the concentration of the first component with respect to the other decreases till certain point (eutectic point) and then increases gradually such that the other component’s concentration increases together. Thus this is an example of regularity and hence a regular solution is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "With respect to the phase diagram of copper zinc system. There happens a phase transition at a particular point.  There happens an equilibrium shift consequently. At which point will zinc reach its maximum concentration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Some point between transition and shift",
            "b) After transition",
            "c) Before shift",
            "d) At the end of both transition and shift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: We know that all the transitions (equilibrium and phase transitions) take place within the range 200 to 400 which is the normal equilibrium range. According to Gibbs phase rule, zinc will reach its maximum concentration after equilibrium point that is at the eutectic point."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "In the general phase diagram of water component system, the region that separates solid and liquid is called _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fusion curve",
            "b) Sublimation curve",
            "c) Metastable curve",
            "d) Critical curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In a water component system, sometimes the water may not undergo transition between solid to liquid instead directly gets converted from solid to vapor. This is a stable state where a small variation in composition or temperature may destroy the steadiness. This point is called sublimated curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "What is the number of phases and components in an aqueous solution of glucose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2, 1",
            "b) 3, 2",
            "c) 1, 3",
            "d) 1, 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since we have two solids and one gaseous component in the above reaction, we have 3 phases. Also since under equilibrium, the gaseous component may evaporate, we have only two components.    "
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "What is the number of components in a nonreactive system of KCl-NaCl-H2O?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since we have one solid component and two gaseous components (n gaseous components contribute to one phase and n solid components contribute to n phases), we have 2 phases. Since the gaseous components may evaporate, we have only one component."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "What is the number of components present in a reactive system of NaCl-KBr-H20?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since we have a solid mixed in a liquid, we have two components. Since the above solution is homogeneous, we have only one phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "What is the degree of freedom for a water system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Here we have two solids and two gases, so the number of phases is two. Also the number of species is 4 (i.e N=4) and the number of reactions is one (i.e E=1). Therefore, the number of components is C = N-E = 4-1 = 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Calculate the degree of freedom for an aqueous solution of glucose.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since it is a nonreactive system, we should also take the ions into consideration (sodium ions, potassium ions, chlorine ions) and also the individual components (NaCl, KCl, H20). Hence N=6. Also E=3. Therefore the number of components are C = N-E = 6-3 = 3."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Calculate the degree of freedom for a saturated solution of sodium chloride.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since it is a reactive system, we have N=9 (taking all the ions into consideration along with individual species) and also we have E=5 (considering all the neutral reactions). Therefore C = N – E = 9-5 = 4."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "If a system has 7 solid species and 2 gaseous species, what is the number of phases present in the system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 7",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  We know that n gaseous components contribute to one phase and n solid components contribute to n phases. Therefore, we have 7+1 = 8 phases in the given system."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "If a system has n number of gaseous components, then what is the number of phases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 1",
            "c) n",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  We know that n gaseous components contribute to one phase and n solid components contribute to n phases. Therefore, we have only one phase in the given system."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "What is the formula for the Degree of Freedom for a condensed phase rule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) F=C-P+2",
            "b) F=C-P+1",
            "c) F=C+P+2",
            "d) F=C+P+1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that the number of phases and components in the above reaction is 3 and 2 respectively. Since it is a one component system, F = C-P+2 = 2-3+2 = 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Calculate the number of phases in a mixture of water and oil.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since for a condensed phase rule, the pressure is accounted as atmospheric pressure so that we can represent the system in 3D. Hence the formula reduces for condensed phase rule."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "Calculate the number of phases in a saturated solution of NaCl and water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Though the system is a mixture of two liquids, they are immiscible and hence they should be considered as two different phases. Hence the number of phases is 2."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Calculate the number of phases in an unsaturated solution of NaCl and water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: We know that salt is soluble in water. So normally the number of phases is one. But under saturated condition, salt becomes insoluble in water and so the number of phases is 2 (as they form heterogeneous mixture)."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Calculate the number of phases in Mohr salt.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the salt is completely miscible in water, it forms a homogeneous mixture and hence it has only one phase (miscible liquids form only one phase and only one component)."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "What are the factors that affect phase rule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravity",
            "b) Electrical force",
            "c) Magnetic force",
            "d) Concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mohr salt is (NH4)2Fe(SO4)2•6H2O. Since it is a single component (though it has many species), it has only one phase (a component with n species has only one compound)."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Calculate the number of phases in the transformation of rhombic to monoclinic sulphur.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since phase rule is a property of a system, it only depends on factors like concentration, degree of freedom, solubility, equilibrium temperature, equilibrium pressure etc. (only stable factors are considered)."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "With respect to one component system, what is the mixture present at the triple point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Ice",
            "c) Water vapor",
            "d) Water, ice, vapor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since at the triple point, all the states of water are in equilibrium, all the three states will stay together. At this point where the three phases exist is invariant where F=0."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect about the triple point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The point at which the solid, liquid and gaseous phases for a substance co-exist",
            "b) The triple point exists for a substance at a specific temperature and pressure",
            "c) The triple point exists at a single temperature and is not related with pressure",
            "d) The system must be closed so that no vapor can escape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The triple point for a pure substance occurs in a closed system at a particular temperature and pressure (i.e. one cannot be varied with the other). Hence the triple point is dependent on both the factors. "
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "What does a horizontal arrest in a cooling system refer to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuous cooling",
            "b) Invariant reaction",
            "c) Variant reaction",
            "d) Bi variant reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Horizontal arrest refers to the equilibrium state of the system where the degree of freedom is 0 (as all the phases co-exist) and hence this state is referred to as invariant reaction (unique point)."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Calculate the degree of freedom for sublimation curve.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Does not exist",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer a\nExplanation: Since in the sublimation curve, super cooled liquid exists along with Vapor and liquid states, this condition will not be applicable to normal Gibbs formula which states F = C-P+2."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "Calculate the number of phases at the sublimation curve.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since in a sublimation state, all the phases exist together (solid, liquid, vapor and super cooled liquid), they contribute to individual species and hence the number of phases is four."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Under what condition is one component system converted to two component systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease the temperature",
            "b) Add a miscible liquid",
            "c) Add an immiscible liquid",
            "d) Decrease the pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: We know that two immiscible liquids form a heterogeneous mixture. Similarly, if a miscible liquid is added to the one component system, then under high temperature and pressure, it can be converted into two component systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Under what condition is two component systems converted to one component system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease the temperature",
            "b) Add a miscible liquid",
            "c) Add an immiscible liquid",
            "d) Decrease the pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that two miscible liquids form a homogeneous mixture. Similarly, if an immiscible liquid is added to the two component systems, then under high temperature and pressure, it can be converted into one component system."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Calculate the degree of freedom for decomposition of potassium permanganate.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of components in this system is three.  Also the number of phase in this reaction is three. Therefore the degree of freedom is given by F = C-P+2. Therefore F=2."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Calculate the degree of freedom for decomposition of charcoal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: In this reaction, the number of phases is 3 (solid, liquid, gas). The number of components is also 3. Therefore the degree of freedom is given by F = C-P+2. Therefore F=2."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "What is the definition of a lower critical temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The minimum temperature at which equilibrium is achieved",
            "b) The lowest temperature at which two components will attain vapor state",
            "c) The lowest temperature at which two components sublimates",
            "d) The lowest temperature at which two components form a mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lower critical solution temperature is the lowest temperature at which two components are insoluble and attains equilibrium. Conversely, the upper critical solution temperature is the highest temperature at which two components are soluble as single phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": " With reference to a two component system, a vapor line indicates ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A region where the temperature and pressure remains stable",
            "b) A region where the solubility remains constant",
            "c) An area below which components do not mingle",
            "d) An area above which both the components mingle to form a single mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A vapor line is another name for an isotherm. It represents constant temperature and constant pressure relation at which the equilibrium is obtained. A  vapor line helps in finding out equilibrium concentrations."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "With reference to a two component system, an isobar indicates _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) A region where the temperature remains constant",
            "b) An area below  phase end products remains",
            "c) An area above which only the liquid vapors remains",
            "d) A region where the composition lies in equilibrium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An isobar is a line that indicates a region where the composition remains constant and in the equilibrium state. In a two component solid-liquid system, it is drawn vertically covering a wide range of temperatures."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements is not true for a system that has reached the eutectic temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The system is a open system",
            "b) The system is a miscible fluid",
            "c) Components lie in liquid state",
            "d) A region between sublimation and eutectic curve lies stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The eutectic temperature is achieved by heating a liquid in the point where the density of the liquid state is equal to the density of the vapor state. Here, the interface between the liquid and vapor vanishes resulting in a miscible fluid. This can only occur in a closed system (otherwise the vapor would escape into the surroundings)."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "What does the term “ metastable” indicate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A place where the composition of the system remains constant",
            "b) A place where the pressure remains constant with low value",
            "c) An area below which a vapor- liquid mixture is obtained",
            "d) A region where the temperature remains constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A metastable is a line that indicates a place where the temperature remains constant. In a two component system it is drawn horizontally covering a wide range of compositions."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Which of the following statements are correct about the equilibrium point on a two component system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All the compounds are liquid",
            "b) The boiling point of the mixture is less than the boiling points of the individual compounds",
            "c) The degree of freedom is 0",
            "d) Invariant reaction takes place"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Eutectic point on a phase diagram is a point at which the mixture boils at a temperature lower than that of the pure substances. The substance attains equilibrium state."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "During metastable state, the size of the particle_________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Won’t change",
            "d) Not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since for a system to be in equilibrium condition, its size automatically increases by Mond’s effect which is why the particle’s size increases during metastable state due to changes in molecular size."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not responsible for phase deposition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Container wall",
            "b) Grain size",
            "c) Stacking effect",
            "d) Disjoints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under equilibrium conditions, the molecules adhere to the center of the container and under non-equilibrium conditions, the vapors are let out through the walls of the container hence the container wall has no role to play in the reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Where does the particle growth occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Movement of grains",
            "b) Movement of equilibrium liquid",
            "c) Equilibrium mixture",
            "d) Non equilibrium mixture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During diffusion process in the transformation of solid to vapor state, the molecules move from regions of higher concentration to regions of lower concentrations and hence growth takes place n a controlled way."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Overall transformation rate changes with temperature as follows under what condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreases",
            "b) Increases then decreases",
            "c) Follows a linear path",
            "d) Increases with temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to the phase graph, at the solidus region, the temperature is high. As the melting point increases, the temperature decreases and vice versa (applicable to all component systems)."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "For the T-C relation in phenol, there happens a regular sharpening in concentration of phenol. What will happen if the equilibrium conditions are varied at a particular point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The curve remains unchanged",
            "b) The curve decreases",
            "c) The curve increases",
            "d) The curve inverts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: We know that both the equilibrium points are achieved at the same concentration and hence there is a regular increase. If the equilibrium conditions are varied, then the steadiness vanishes and hence the curve will show an abnormal increase in its concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "In the general phase diagram of Ferric chloride – water system, what causes reduction in water content in ferric chloride at each step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in moisture content",
            "b) Reduction in concentration",
            "c) Reduction in equilibrium shift",
            "d) Increase in temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since for each transition from one phase to another for a component, the moisture content decreases due to increase in temperature. Hence the water concentration in ferric chloride decreases as the temperature increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "The mechanism of diffusion of small atomic radius compared to the parent material would be described by __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Substitutional diffusion",
            "b) Interstitial diffusion",
            "c) Vacancy diffusion",
            "d) Drift"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During equilibrium process, metastable curve appears and due to variation in equilibrium composition, the curve disappears. To fix this equilibrium back to form, there takes place diffusion between interstitial atoms called interstitial diffusion."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "What happens during a non-steady state diffusion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The composition behavior does not change with time",
            "b) The composition behavior changes with time",
            "c) The diffusion can be described by Mond’s Second Law",
            "d) Zero composition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Only during a steady state reaction (invariant reaction), the composite and other parameters like concentration, temperature, pressure, solubility etc can be determined. Hence under non- equilibrium conditions, all the above parameters are negligible and hence there is zero composition. "
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "The driving force of the diffusion process in phase diagram is __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The slope in Gibbs free energy",
            "b) The slope in solubility",
            "c) The slope in temperature",
            "d) The slope in pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the driving force (parameter defining force) is determined only by a small change in chemical composition with respect to temperature, the slope in the chemical composition will determine the driving force."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "In the mixture of propanol and iso propanol, identify the component at the meeting point of these two components.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propanol",
            "b) Propane",
            "c) Propane-2-ol",
            "d) Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When two different components are made to show phase relation, together, then the component which is formed at the eutectic region is a mixture of their metastable components. Thus here it is Propane-2-ol."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "What are the limits of phase rule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cannot determine the presence of more the one phase in a system",
            "b) Cannot determine solubility",
            "c) Cannot determine composition",
            "d) Can determine temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Since phase rule focusses only on one equilibrium state of the system, the presence of even tiny traces of multiple phases cannot be identified using phase rule which is the main drawback of this rule. This drawback is solved by Lever rule."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "In the mixture of liquid and vapor compositions, identify the type of component present in between the two components (at equilibrium point).",
        "Options": [
            "a) Regular solution",
            "b) Equilibrium solution",
            "c) Transition solution",
            "d) Steady state solution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since phase rule cannot determine multiple phases in a single system, regular solution is not obtained. Similarly, equilibrium solution is also not obtained (according to Weiss law). Thus a steady solution is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "What is the efficiency of phase rule over Lever rule?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 75%",
            "d) 85%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: According to Weiss law (which suits only for phase components), concentration is given by temperature/pressure. Thus in this case, concentration is equal to 20/2=10."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The reactions which are caused by heat and in absence of light is called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photochemical reactions",
            "b) Dark reactions",
            "c) Reversible reaction",
            "d) Reversible photochemical reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reactions which are caused by heat and in absence of light are called thermal or dark reactions. A reaction that takes place by absorption of light radiations of a specific wavelength is called photochemical reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "In photochemical reactions, absorption of _____ radiations takes place.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ultraviolet and visible",
            "b) radio",
            "c) only visible",
            "d) visible and x-rays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Absorption of visible and ultraviolet radiations can only take place in a photochemical reaction. Wavelength of absprbed radiations ranges from 2000 – 8000 Å. "
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "Ozone is formed by ______ dissociation of molecular oxygen into individual oxygen atoms.",
        "Options": [
            "a) photochemical",
            "b) thermochemical",
            "c) thermal",
            "d) ionic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In photochemical reactions, presence of light is the primary requirement for the reaction to take place. It involves absorption of light radiations."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an example of photochemical reaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photosynthesis",
            "b) Decomposition of ammonia",
            "c) Formation of NaOH",
            "d) Decomposition of HCl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Molecular oxygen undergoes photochemical dissociation into individual oxygen atoms. These oxygen atoms are reacted with molecular oxygen to form ozone. "
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the principle laws of photochemistry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grothus-Draper and Stark-Einstein law",
            "b) Raoult’s and Dalton’s law",
            "c) Raoult’s and Henry’s law",
            "d) Lambert’s and Beer’s law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Photosynthesis is an example of photochemical reaction. In photosynthesis, light energy is captured by the chlorophyll present in the thylakoids of the chloroplast for the production of photons. Water is splitted by photons from light energy and it enables ATP production that drives the entire process."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Mercaptans can be produced by photochemical addition of ______ to alpha olefins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydrogen sulphide",
            "b) sulphur",
            "c) hydrogen",
            "d) paraffins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two fundamental principles of photochemistry are there. They are Grothus-Draper law and Stark-Einstein law."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "Vision is initiated by a photochemical reaction of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodopsin",
            "b) Hydrogen Chloride",
            "c) Mercapton",
            "d) Enzymes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mercaptans can be produced by photochemical addition of hydrogen sulfide to alpha olefins. In this method, there is a provision for increasing the total conversion of reactants to mercaptans by including carbon disulfide in the reaction mixture."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "Medicine bottles are often made with darkened glass  _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) to prevent the drug from photodegradation",
            "b) to allow the photodegradation of drug",
            "c) to reduce the cost",
            "d) to allow oxidation of drug"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vision is initiated by a photochemical reaction of rhodopsin. It is the primary photoreceptor molecule of vision."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "In _____ reactions, molecules absorbing light do not themselves react but induce other molecules to react.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photosensitized",
            "b) Thermal",
            "c) Irreversible",
            "d) Dark"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Medicine bottles are often made with darkened glass to prevent the drugs from photodegradation. Generally, brown color is used because of its ability to prevent UV light from degrading the potentially photosensitive contents through photochemical reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "__________ is also known as the Principle of Photochemical Activation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grothus–Draper law",
            "b) Lambert’s law",
            "c) Draper law",
            "d) Stark law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Grothus–Draper law is also known as the Principle of Photochemical Activation. This law states that only that light which is absorbed by a system is responsible for doing a photochemical change. "
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "When a beam of light is allowed to pass through a transparent medium, the rate of decrease of intensity with the thickness of medium is __________ to the intensity of the light.",
        "Options": [
            "a) inversely proportional",
            "b) directly proportional",
            "c) equal",
            "d) not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yes, the absorbed radiation does not necessarily cause a chemical reaction. If the environment is not conducive for the molecules to react, then the light energy will remain unused or in some cases may be re-emitted as heat or light. "
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "The intensity of a beam of monochromatic light ___________ with the increase in the concentration of the absorbing substance arithmetically.",
        "Options": [
            "a) decrease exponentially",
            "b) increase exponentially",
            "c) decrease linearly",
            "d) increase linearly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  As per Lambert’s law, when a beam of light passes through a transparent medium, the rate of decrease of intensity with the thickness of medium is directly proportional to the intensity of the light. Mathematically, it may be stated as follows: -dI/t=kI."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "__________ is also known as Principle of Quantum Activation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lambert’s law",
            "b) Beer’s law",
            "c) Stark-Einstein law",
            "d) Stark law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As per Beer’s Law, the intensity of incident light decreases exponentially with the increase in concentration of the absorbing substance arithmetically. Mathematically, it is shown as follows: I = Io/ekc. "
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Beer-Lambert law is applicable if ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) temperature changes",
            "b) dilute solution is used",
            "c) non-monochromatic radiation is used",
            "d) temperature varies linearly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Stark-Einstein law is also known as the Principle of Quantum Activation. It states that in a primary photochemical process, only one molecule is activated for every photo of light absorbed by the chemical system."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "When light falls on a cell containing a reaction mixture __________ component of light is responsible for producing chemical reaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) absorbed",
            "b) adsorbed",
            "c) transmitted",
            "d) reflected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When a molecule absorbs a photon, it is not necessary that only one molecule should react. It may or may not react or may cause the reaction of many molecules through a chain mechanism."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Grothus – Draper law is __________ in nature.",
        "Options": [
            "a) purely qualitative",
            "b) quantitative",
            "c) qualitative and quantitative",
            "d) non-acceptable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Beer-Lambert law is not applicable if temperature changes during measurements. It is also not applicable if non-monochromatic radiation is used. It is applicable only to dilute solutions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Stark-Einstein studied the __________ aspects of photochemical reactions by application of quantum theory of light.",
        "Options": [
            "a) qualitative",
            "b) quantitative",
            "c) geometrical",
            "d) qualitative and quantitative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When light falls on a cell containing a reaction mixture, some light is absorbed and the remaining light is transmitted. Transmitted light is chemically ineffective whereas absorbed component of light is capable of producing chemical reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "To express the relationship between the number of molecules reacting with the number of photons absorbed, the concept of _____ was introduced.",
        "Options": [
            "a) quantum efficiency",
            "b) photon analysis",
            "c) quantum mechanism",
            "d) photon degradation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The concept of quantum efficiency was introduced to express the relationship between a number of molecules reacting with the number of photons absorbed. It is defined as the number of molecules of the substance undergoing photochemical change per quantum of radiation absorbed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Classification of photochemical reaction on the basis of quantum efficiency can be done into ______ categories.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Photochemical reactions can be divided into three categories on the basis of quantum efficiency i.e., the reactions in which quantum yield is “a small integer like 1, 2” OR “less than 1” OR “a very high value”."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "Quantum efficiency is given by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) nNhc/qλ",
            "b) nq/Nhcλ",
            "c) qλ/nNhc",
            "d) ncλ/Nhq"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Quantum efficiency=Number of molecules reacting in a given time/Number of quanta of light absorbed in the same time.  Hence, Quantum efficiency is given by nNhc/qλ."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "If a reaction obeys Einstein law, quantum yield is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) more than 1",
            "c) less than 1",
            "d) 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a reaction obeys Einstein law, one molecule is decomposed per photon. Quantum efficiency=Number of molecules reacting in a given time/Number of quanta of light absorbed in the same time. So, quantum yield is 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "When two or more molecules are decomposed per photon, the reaction has ______ quantum yield.",
        "Options": [
            "a) high",
            "b) low",
            "c) unpredictable",
            "d) variable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When two or more molecules are decomposed per photon, the reaction has greater than one quantum yield. So, the reaction has high quantum yield.\nQuantum efficiency = Number of molecules reacting in a given time/Number of quanta of light absorbed in the same time."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "When the number of molecules decomposed is less than one per photon, the reaction has ______ quantum yield.",
        "Options": [
            "a) low",
            "b) high",
            "c) unpredictable",
            "d) variable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When the number of molecules decomposed is less than one per photon, the reaction has less than one quantum yield. So, the reaction has low quantum yield.\nQuantum efficiency=Number of molecules reacting in a given time/Number of quanta of light absorbed in the same time. "
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Decomposition of HI has quantum yield = _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HI + hv→ H + I ……………….. Primary reaction                                                                     \t            H + HI → H2 + I\nI + I → I2 …………….. Secondary reaction\nOverall reaction: 2HI + hv → H2 + I2                                                                                                                          the overall reaction shows that 2 HI molecules are decomposed by 1 photon. So, quantum yield=2."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the condition for high and low quantum yield?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The reactivity of the molecules should be temperature dependent",
            "b) All the reactant molecules should be in the different energy state",
            "c) The molecules in the activated state should be largely unstable and decompose to form the products",
            "d) quantum field=1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The molecules in the activated state should be largely unstable and decompose to form the products. The reactivity of the molecules should not be independent on temperature. All the reactant molecules should be initially in the same energy state."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "In photochemistry of photosynthesis, NADPH stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide Phosphate",
            "b) Nicotinamide Amine Dinucleotide Phosphate",
            "c) Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide Phosphatic hydrogen",
            "d) Nicotinamide Amine Dinucleotide Phosphatic hydrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In photochemistry of photosynthesis, NADPH stands for Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide Phosphate. It is generated in light dependent reaction. It acts as a reducing agent in light independent reaction in Calvin cylce to reduce carbon dioxide. "
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "In photosynthesis, energy of sun is converted into chemical energy in the form of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATP and NADPH",
            "b) ADP and NADPH",
            "c) ATP and NADP",
            "d) ADP and NADP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In photosynthesis, energy of sun is converted into chemical energy in the form of ATP and NADPH. NADPH stands for Nicotinamide Adenine Dinucleotide Phosphate. ATP stands for Adenosine Triphosphate. "
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "In photosynthesis, ATP stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adenosine Triphosphate",
            "b) Amine Triphosphate",
            "c) Amine tri poly phosphate",
            "d) Ammonium Triphosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In photosynthesis, ATP stands for Adenosine Triphosphate. It is generated in light dependent reaction alongwith NADPH. It acts as a reducing agent in light independent reaction in the Calvin cycle to reduce carbon dioxide. "
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of a photoautotroph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) plants",
            "c) cyanobacteria",
            "d) human beings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In photosynthesis, photochemical reaction drives the entire process. Electrons in the pigment are excited by light energy which is the initial reaction in photosynthesis. So, photosynthesis is a photochemical process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "In photosynthesis, RuBP stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ribulose Bisphosphate",
            "b) Ribulose urea Biphosphate",
            "c) Ribulose phosphate",
            "d) Ribulose biurea phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Generally, most of the plants, algae and bacteria perform photosynthesis. Such organisms are called photoautotroph. They can make food on their own by using carbon dioxide and light. Human beings cannot create food on their own. "
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "In photosynthesis, carbon dioxide is converted into sugar by which process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbon fixation",
            "b) carbon reduction",
            "c) sugar fixation",
            "d) photolysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: RuBP stand for Ribulose Bisphosphate. It forms a six carbon compound by combining with carbon dioxide in presence of enzyme. "
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Which of the following nutrients is not used in cellular respiration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbohydrates",
            "b) amino acids",
            "c) fatty acids",
            "d) fiber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Not all organisms can carry out photosynthesis by using carbon dioxide as a source of carbon atoms. Photoheterotrophs use organic compounds as a source of carbon atoms to carry out photosynthesis. "
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the stage in photosynthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) absorption of light",
            "b) generation of ATP",
            "c) carbon fixation",
            "d) phosphorousfixation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In photosynthesis, carbon dioxide is converted into sugar by carbon fixation process. Energy from sunlight is captured to convert carbon dioxide into carbohydrates. "
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Which vitamin is important for vision?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vitamin A",
            "b) Vitamin B",
            "c) Vitamin C",
            "d) Vitamin D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vitamin A is important for vision. It is also known as retinol. It is required by the retina of the eye. "
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Retina is made up of which type of cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rods and cones",
            "b) Rids and cones",
            "c) Rods and coans",
            "d) Rods and rhodospin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cis-retinal can absorb light at a specific wavelength. By absorbing visible light, it undergoes isomerization and cis-retinal is converted into trans-retinal. "
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Retina is made up of rods and cones",
            "b) Cones are lesser in number as compared to rods",
            "c) Rods are more sensitive than cones",
            "d) Cones are responsible for vision in dim light"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Retina is made up of two types of cells. They are rods and cones. They are light sensitive photoreceptor cells. "
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Rhodospin is a ______ pigment in the rod cells of retina.",
        "Options": [
            "a) red",
            "b) yellow",
            "c) green",
            "d) black"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Retina is made up of two types of cells. They are rods and cones. Rods are more sensitive than cones. Cones are fewer in numbers than rods. Rods are responsible for vision in dim light. "
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Rhodospin is a combination of opsin and _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11-cis-retinal",
            "b) 10-cis-retinal",
            "c) 11-trans-retinal",
            "d) 10-trans-retinal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rhodospin is a red pigment in the rod cells of the retina. It is extremely sensitive to light. So, it works only in low light. "
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rods are found at the periphery of the retina",
            "b) Cones are at the centre of the retina",
            "c) Rods has high resolution compared to cones",
            "d) Cones have high resolution compared to rods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rhodospin is a combination of opsin and 11-cis-retinal. Opsin is a protein and it is colorless. 11-cis-retinal is highly conjugated aldehyde. "
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "Which scientist first discovered that rod cells contain rhodospin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Franz Boll",
            "b) Benjamin Franklin",
            "c) Robert Lewis",
            "d) Andrew Boll"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rods are found at the periphery of retina whereas cones are found at the centre of the retina. Cones have high resolution as compared to rods. "
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "A disorder in which rod cells in the retina lose their ability to respond to light is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Color blindness",
            "b) Night blindness",
            "c) Day blindness",
            "d) Retina blindness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some animals do not possess both rods and cones. Owls have rods and can see only in dim light. Pigeons have cones and can see only in bright light. "
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "A polymer is any substance made up of many repeating units called ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resins",
            "b) Plastic",
            "c) Mers",
            "d) Blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A polymer is any substance made up of many repeating units, building blocks called mers. Polymers are made up of many many molecules all strung together to form really long chains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Small molecules which combine to form polymer are called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Resins",
            "b) Monomers",
            "c) Plastic",
            "d) Blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Small molecules which combine with each other to form polymer are called monomers. Polymers are made up of many many molecules all strung together to form really long chains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following options.",
        "Options": [
            "a) When in form ready for further working, polymers are called resins",
            "b) The chemical process leading to the formation of polymer is known as polymerisation",
            "c) The number of monomeric units contained in the polymer is called the degree of polymerisation",
            "d) Due to their small size, polymers are also called micro-molecules"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to their large size, polymers are also called macro-molecules. All the other options are correct. When in form ready for further working, polymers are called resins. The chemical process leading to the formation of polymer is known as polymerisation and the number of monomeric units contained in polymer is called degree of polymerisation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "The optimum DP  value of cellulose is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150",
            "b) 250",
            "c) 400",
            "d) 500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Below threshold degree of polymerisation, the polymer does not possess any strength and exist either as liquid resin or friable powder. The number of monomeric units contained in the polymer is called degree of polymerisation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "The functionality of ethylene glycol is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The optimum DP  value of cellulose is 250. The number of monomeric units contained in the polymer is called degree of polymerisation (DP).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Which of the following polymer is not classified under the category of configuration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syndiotactic",
            "b) Atactic",
            "c) Cross-linked",
            "d) Isotactic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The functionality of ethylene glycol is 2. It is a colorless, odorless, viscous dihydroxy alcohol and  has a sweet taste, but is poisonous if ingested.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of semi-crystalline polymer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDPE",
            "b) Nylon",
            "c) Polyesters",
            "d) LDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cross-linked polymer is not classified under the category of configuration. Syndiotactic, atactic and isotactic are classified under the category of configuration. Tacticity is the relative stereochemistry of adjacent chiral centers within a macromolecule.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Styrene acrylonitrile is an example of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Co-polymer",
            "b) Homopolymer",
            "c) Linear polymer",
            "d) Amorphous polymer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LDPE is not an example of a semi-crystalline polymer. It is an example of a branched amorphous polymer. All the other options are examples of semi-crystalline polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Which of the following polymer is not classified under the category of end use?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fibers",
            "b) Adhesives",
            "c) Elastomers",
            "d) Synthetic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Styrene acrylonitrile resin is a copolymer plastic consisting of styrene and acrylonitrile. It is also known as SAN. It is widely used in place of polystyrene.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermosets are formed by condensation polymerisation reactions",
            "b) Thermosets have 3-D, cross-linked network structure",
            "c) Thermosets soften on heating and stiffen on cooling",
            "d) Thermosets are generally insoluble in any solvent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Synthetic polymer is not classified under the category of end use. It is classified under the category of origin. Fibers, adhesives and elastomers are classified under the category of end use.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not an example of thermoplastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyvinyl chloride",
            "b) Nylon",
            "c) Polyesters",
            "d) Epoxy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thermosets do not soften on heating. All the other options are correct. Thermosets are formed by condensation polymerisation reactions, have 3-D, cross-linked network structure and are generally insoluble in any solvent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "The weight average molecular weight for PP given its degree of polymerisation as 10,000 will be ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3,00,000 gm/mol",
            "b) 4,20,000 gm/mol",
            "c) 6,70,000 gm/mol",
            "d) 8,40,000 gm/mol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Epoxy is not an example of thermoplastic. It is an example of a thermoset polymer. Polyvinyl chloride, nylon and polyesters are examples of thermoplastic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "The cryoscopy refers to ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Osmotic pressure measurement",
            "b) Elevation in boiling point measurement",
            "c) Freezing point depression measurement",
            "d) Increase in solubility measurement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The weight average molecular weight for PP given its degree of polymerisation as 10,000 will be 4,20,000 gm/mol.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Which of the following technique is used to measure the number of conjugated double bonds and aromatic conjugation within the various molecules?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fourier transform infrared",
            "b) Differential scanning calorimetry",
            "c) U/V Visible spectroscopy",
            "d) Thermo gravimetric analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: UV/ Visible spectroscopy is used to measure the number of conjugated double bonds and aromatic conjugation within the various molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy is used to study ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quantitative determination of additives in polymers",
            "b) Curing and degradation behaviour of cross-linked polymers",
            "c) Determination of volatilities of plasticizers",
            "d) Analysis of structural imperfections on the surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy is used to study the curing and degradation behaviour of cross-linked polymers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "Atomic force microscopy comes under the category of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spectral analysis",
            "b) Thermal analysis",
            "c) Mechanical testing",
            "d) Morphological analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Atomic force microscopy comes under the category of morphological analysis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of the following is useful for determination of volatilities of plasticizers and other additives?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermo gravimetric analysis",
            "b) Differential scanning calorimetry",
            "c) Scanning electron microscopy",
            "d) Atomic force microscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thermo gravimetric analysis is useful for determination of volatilities of plasticizers and other additives.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "Differential scanning calorimetry is useful for determining the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melting temperature, glass transition temperature, heat of fusion etc",
            "b) Volatilities of plasticizers and other additives",
            "c) Quantitative determination of additives in polymers",
            "d) Structural imperfections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Differential scanning calorimetry is useful for determining the melting temperature, glass transition temperature, heat of fusion etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Differential scanning calorimetry comes under the category of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spectral analysis",
            "b) Morphological analysis",
            "c) Thermal analysis",
            "d) Geological analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Differential scanning calorimetry comes under the category of thermal analysis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as a criterion in quality control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) X-ray diffraction",
            "b) Mechanical testing",
            "c) Wetting properties",
            "d) Spectral analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mechanical testing is used as a criterion in quality control. It shows whether a material or part is suitable for its intended application by measuring properties such as elasticity, hardness, fracture toughness, impact resistance, and the fatigue limit.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "The study of fracture surfaces of polymeric material is done using ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atomic force microscopy",
            "b) X-ray diffraction",
            "c) Thermo gravimetric analysis",
            "d) Scanning electron microscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The study of fracture surfaces of polymeric material is done using scanning electron microscopy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "A hydrophobic surface with low free surface energy gives a ____________ with water.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low contact angle",
            "b) High contact angle",
            "c) Zero contact angle",
            "d) Extremely low contact angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A hydrophobic surface with low free surface energy gives a high contact angle with water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "The physical mixture of two or more polymers that are not linked by covalent bonds is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polymerisation",
            "b) Dendrimer",
            "c) Polyblend",
            "d) Multiblend"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The physical mixture of two or more polymers that are not linked by covalent bonds is called polyblend or polymer blend. They are blended together to create a new material with different physical properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Polymers are dissolved in common solvent to give ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical blends",
            "b) Solution-cast blends",
            "c) Latex blends",
            "d) Chemical blends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polymers are dissolved in common solvent to give solution-cast blends. If the blend is made of two polymers, two glass transition temperatures will be observed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "For amorphous and semi-crystalline polymers, mixing leads to the formation of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical blends",
            "b) Solution-cast blends",
            "c) Latex blends",
            "d) Chemical blends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For amorphous and semi-crystalline polymers, mixing leads to the formation of mechanical blends. The macroscopically uniform properties are usually caused by sufficiently strong interactions between the component polymers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "The immiscible blends exhibit ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excellent mechanical properties",
            "b) Poor mechanical properties",
            "c) Poor chemical properties",
            "d) Intermediate chemical properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The immiscible blends exhibit poor mechanical properties. This is by far the most populous group. If the blend is made of two polymers, two glass transition temperatures will be observed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Cross-linked polymers are swollen with a different monomer, which results in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical blends",
            "b) Solution-cast blends",
            "c) Latex blends",
            "d) Chemical blends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cross-linked polymers is swollen with a different monomer, which results in chemical blends. They have different chemical properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect option from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immiscible blends are usually opaque",
            "b) Immiscible blends exhibit a single glass transition temperature (Tg) intermediate between those of individual components",
            "c) Miscible blends are usually clear",
            "d) Immiscible blends exhibit separate Tg’s characteristics of each component"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Miscible blends exhibit a single glass transition temperature (Tg) intermediate between those of individual components. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "Fine dispersions of polymers in water are mixed and coagulated to give ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical blends",
            "b) Solution-cast blends",
            "c) Latex blends",
            "d) Chemical blends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: (PPO + PS) polyblend is commercially available engineering plastic Noryl (General Electric). The use of the term polymer alloy for a polymer blend is discouraged, as the former term includes multi-phase co-polymers but excludes incompatible polymer blends.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "The blend is said to be synergistic for the mechanical property if the term (I) in the empirical formula is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero",
            "b) Positive",
            "c) Negative",
            "d) Imaginary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fine dispersions of polymers in water are mixed and coagulated to give latex blends. The use of the term polymer alloy for a polymer blend is discouraged, as the former term includes multi-phase co-polymers but excludes incompatible polymer blends.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "The blend is said to be additive for the mechanical property if the term (I) in the empirical formula is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Imaginary",
            "b) Positive",
            "c) Negative",
            "d) Zero"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The blend is said to be synergistic for the mechanical property if the term (I) in the empirical formula is positive. For amorphous and semi-crystalline polymers, mixing leads to the formation of mechanical blends.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Which of the following scientists won the noble prize for their work in polymer stereochemistry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kurt Alder and Richard Abegg",
            "b) Peter Agre and Agricola",
            "c) Zeigler and Natta",
            "d) Friedrich Accum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ziegler and Natta shared the noble prize in 1963 for their work in stereochemistry of polymers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "A tactic dyad has a segment of the polymer chain consisting of _________ monomeric units.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A tactic dyad has a segment of the polymer chain consisting of two monomeric units. Dyad means two, triad means three.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "The polymer in which alternate chiral centres have the same configuration is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syndiotactic",
            "b) Atactic",
            "c) Isotactic",
            "d) Multitactic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The polymer in which alternate chiral centres have the same configuration is called syndiotactic, in which the repeating units have alternating stereo chemical configurations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "The tendency for a polymer to adopt crystalline morphology increases with __________ stereo regularity.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decreasing",
            "b) Increasing",
            "c) First increasing then decreasing",
            "d) First decreasing then increasing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tendency for a polymer to adopt crystalline morphology increases with increasing stereo regularity, regardless of the type of stereochemistry.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "The configuration of the isotactic dyad is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectus",
            "b) Racemic",
            "c) Chiral",
            "d) Meso"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The configuration of the isotactic dyad is meso. Isotactic denotes a polymer in which all the repeating units have the same stereo chemical configuration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "When each chiral centre has the same configuration, the polymer is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atactic",
            "b) Syndiotactic",
            "c) Isotactic",
            "d) Multitactic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When each chiral centre has the same configuration, the polymer is called isotactic. It denotes a polymer in which all the repeating units have the same stereochemical configuration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "Atactic polymer is that in which?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alternate chiral centres have the same configuration",
            "b) Every third chiral centre has the same configuration",
            "c) Each chiral centre has the same configuration",
            "d) A complete random distribution of configuration is there"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Atactic polymer is that in which a complete random distribution of configuration is there. Atactic polypropylene has little order in the polymer backbone and is amorphous.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "The Greek meaning of Dendron is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stem",
            "b) Branch",
            "c) Tree",
            "d) Root"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Greek meaning of Dendron is a tree. Synonymous terms for dendrimer include arborols and cascade molecules.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the other name for dendrimers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dendritic",
            "b) Starburst",
            "c) Cascade polymers",
            "d) Deluge polymers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Dendrimers are also known as dendritic, starburst and cascade polymers. Synonymous terms for dendrimer include arborols and cascade molecules. Deluge is not used with dendrimers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a component of dendrimer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Central core",
            "b) Stem",
            "c) Interior dendritic structure",
            "d) Exterior surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dendrimer has three components,i.e. central core, interior dendritic structure and the exterior surface. No stem is present in the dendrimer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "As dendrimers have high surface functionality, so they tend to be _________ soluble than linear polymers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) More",
            "b) Less",
            "c) Equally",
            "d) Very less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dendrimers resemble star polymers except that each leg of the star exhibits repetitive branching in the manner of a tree. Dendritic molecules are characterized by structural perfection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Due to lack of chain entanglement, dendrimers usually have low ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solubility",
            "b) Boiling point",
            "c) Viscosity",
            "d) Conductivity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: As dendrimers have high surface functionality, so they tend to be more soluble than linear polymers. The properties of dendrimers are dominated by the functional groups on the molecular surface, however, there are examples of dendrimers with internal functionality.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "The molecular dimensions of dendrimers lie in the range of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-100 nm",
            "b) 100-500 nm",
            "c) 600-800 nm",
            "d) 800-1000 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Due to the lack of chain entanglement, dendrimers usually have low viscosity. The properties of dendrimers are dominated by the functional groups on the molecular surface, however, there are examples of dendrimers with internal functionality.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a potential application of dendrimer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viscosity modifier",
            "b) Molecular sensors",
            "c) Drug delivery system",
            "d) Temperature modifier"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The molecular dimensions of dendrimers lie in the range of 1-100 nm. So, dendrimers can be used as a solubilizing agent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "There is a limit to the size of dendrimer segments because of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low viscosity",
            "b) High solubility",
            "c) Steric congestion",
            "d) Cross-linked structure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Temperature modifier is not a potential application of dendrimer. All the other options including viscosity modifier, molecular sensors and drug delivery system are potential applications of a dendrimer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Which type of polymer will be formed if the substituent group is –C6H5?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polythene",
            "b) Polypropylene",
            "c) Polystyrene",
            "d) Polyvinyl chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polystyrene will be formed if the substituent group is –C6H5. It is a synthetic aromatic polymer made from the monomer styrene. Polystyrene can be solid or foamed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition polymerisation requires the presence of double bond in monomer",
            "b) No by-product is formed in addition polymerisation",
            "c) In addition polymerisation, growth of chain is at one active centre",
            "d) In addition polymerisation, polymer MW rises steadily throughout the reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In addition polymerisation, high MW polymer is formed at once. All the other options are correct. Addition polymerisation requires the presence of a double bond in monomer and no by-product is formed. In addition polymerisation, growth of chain is at one active centre.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Condensation polymerisation requires two reactive functional groups to be present at both ends of the monomer",
            "b) No by-product is formed in condensation polymerisation",
            "c) In condensation polymerisation, growth of chain occurs at minimum of the two active centres",
            "d) In condensation polymerisation, polymer MW rises steadily throughout the reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Generally a by-product is formed in condensation polymerisation. All the other options are correct.\nCondensation polymerisation requires two reactive functional groups to be present at both ends of the monomer and growth of chain occurs at a minimum of the two active centres. In condensation polymerisation, polymer MW rises steadily throughout the reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "The Ziegler Natta catalyst is formed between _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triethyl aluminium and titanium halide",
            "b) Triethyl aluminium and silver halide",
            "c) Triethyl aluminium and platinum halide",
            "d) Triethyl aluminium and carbon halide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Ziegler Natta catalyst is formed between triethyl aluminium and titanium halide. It is named after Karl Ziegler and Giulio Natta, used in the synthesis of polymers of 1-alkenes (alpha-olefins).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "The co-polymers having branched structures in which the monomer segments on the backbone and branches differ are called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alternate",
            "b) Graft",
            "c) Random",
            "d) Block"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The co-polymers having branched structures in which the monomer segments on the backbone and branches differ are called graft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as an initiator in free-radical polymerisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grignard reagent",
            "b) Lewis acids",
            "c) Benzoyl peroxide",
            "d) Potassium amide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Benzoyl peroxide act as an initiator in free-radical polymerisation. Benzoyl peroxide is used as an acne treatment, for bleaching flour, hair and teeth, for cross-linking polyester resins, and for many other purposes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as a catalyst in anionic polymerisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Grignard reagent",
            "b) Lewis acids",
            "c) Benzoyl peroxide",
            "d) AIBN"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Grignard reagent act as a catalyst in anionic polymerisation. The Grignard reaction is an organo-metallic chemical reaction in which alkyl, vinyl, or aryl-magnesium halides, CH3MgI (Grignard reagents) add to a carbonyl group in an aldehyde or ketone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "The temperature at which the ionic polymerisation is carried out is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000C",
            "b) 500C",
            "c) -1000C",
            "d) 00C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperature at which the ionic polymerisation is carried out is 00C. Ionic polymerization is a chain-growth polymerization in which active centers are ions or ion pairs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Which of the following monomer cannot be polymerised by radical polymerisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Butadiene",
            "b) Isobutylene",
            "c) Vinyl chloride",
            "d) Acrylates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radical polymerisation is not sensitive to changes in the polarity. Free radical polymerization is a method of polymerization by which a polymer forms by the successive addition of free radical building blocks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "The polymerisation in which propagating centers do not undergo either transfer or termination reactions is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition polymerisation",
            "b) Co-polymerisation",
            "c) Living polymerisation",
            "d) Dead polymerisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Isobutylene monomer can be polymerised by cationic polymerisation. Butadiene, vinyl chloride and acrylates can be polymerised by radical polymerization.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "In esterification, the nucleophile is _________ and the leaving group is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol, ester",
            "b) Ester, alcohol",
            "c) Water, alcohol",
            "d) Alcohol, water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The polymerisation in which propagating centers do not undergo either transfer or termination reactions is called living polymerisation. Polymerization is a process of reacting monomer molecules together in a chemical reaction to form polymer chains or three-dimensional networks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "The reverse of esterification is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrolysis",
            "b) Condensation",
            "c) Polymerisation",
            "d) Centrifugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In esterification, the nucleophile is alcohol and the leaving group is water. Esterification is the general name for a chemical reaction in which two reactants (typically an alcohol and an acid) form an ester as the reaction product.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for making cold drink bottles, magnetic recording tapes and housings for coffee machines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ethylene glycol",
            "b) Polyethylene terephthalate",
            "c) Hexamethylene diamine",
            "d) Styrene butadiene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reverse of esterification is hydrolysis. Hydrolysis is a reaction involving the breaking of a bond in a molecule using water. The reaction mainly occurs between an ion and water molecules and often changes the pH of a solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "The thermoplastic is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cross-linked",
            "b) Insoluble",
            "c) Amorphous",
            "d) Held by a covalent bond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thermoplastics are linear or branched, soluble in suitable solvents, amorphous or semi-crystalline and held together by weak vander waal’s force or hydrogen bonds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of thermoplastic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nylon",
            "b) Polyester",
            "c) PVC",
            "d) Vulcanised rubber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The examples of thermoplastic are nylon, polyester, PVC,PE, PP, PVA etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Polythene is prepared by the process of __________________ polymerisation of ethylene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Addition",
            "b) Condensation",
            "c) Living",
            "d) Free-radical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polythene is prepared by the process of addition polymerisation of ethylene. Polythene is of low strength, hardness and rigidity, but has a high ductility and impact strength as well as low friction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "LDPE is prepared by polymerising ethylene at a pressure of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100-200 atmospheres",
            "b) 1000-5000 atmospheres",
            "c) 10-100 atmospheres",
            "d) 2-10 atmospheres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: None.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "The crystallinity of LDPE is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 30%",
            "c) 55%",
            "d) 80-90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The crystallinity of LDPE is low (55%). LDPE is defined by a density range of 0.910–0.940 g/cm3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) LDPE is chemically inert and has excellent chemical resistance",
            "b) LDPE is tough and flexible",
            "c) LDPE is used for making films in general packaging, carrier bags etc",
            "d) LDPE has high rigidity and is suitable for load bearing applications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: LDPE has low rigidity and is not suitable for load bearing applications. All other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "The ethylene is polymerised under in the presence of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zeigler Natta catalyst",
            "b) Supported metal oxide catalyst",
            "c) Lewis acids catalyst",
            "d) Friedel crafts catalyst"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: LDPE is not suitable for the manufacture of pipes for distribution of gas because it is permeable to gas molecules. LDPE is widely used for manufacturing various containers, dispensing bottles, wash bottles etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The softening temperature of HDPE is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200C",
            "b) 850C",
            "c) 1350C",
            "d) 1500C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ethylene is polymerised under 6-7 atmospheric pressure at 60-700C in the presence of Zeigler Natta catalyst.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) HDPE has excellent electrical insulation properties",
            "b) HDPE is free from odour and toxicity",
            "c) HDPE can be used for domestic water and gas piping",
            "d) HDPE possess lower tensile strength compared to LDPE"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The softening temperature of HDPE is 1350C. HDPE is known for its large strength-to-density ratio.The density of HDPE can range from 0.93 to 0.97 g/cm3 or 970 kg/m3.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as a catalyst in the preparation of PVC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lewis acid",
            "b) Benzoyl peroxide",
            "c) Potassium amide",
            "d) Grignard reagent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Benzoyl peroxide act as a catalyst in the preparation of PVC. The product of the polymerization process is unmodified PVC.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PVC is colourless, odourless and non-inflammable",
            "b) PVC has poor oil resistance and resistance to weathering",
            "c) PVC is used for making bottles for consumable liquids",
            "d) PVC has superior chemical resistance but is soluble in ethyl chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PVC has excellent oil resistance and resistance to weathering. It is colorless, odourless and non-inflammable and is used for making bottles for consumable liquids. PVC has poor oil resistance and resistance to weathering.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "Plasticized PVC is not used for making ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Baby-pants",
            "b) Bathroom curtaining",
            "c) Pipes for drainage",
            "d) Garden hose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The C-Cl dipole makes PVC a polymeric polar molecule.PVC has excellent oil resistance and resistance to weathering. It is colorless, odourless and non-inflammable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "Which of the following is also known as lucite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Teflon",
            "b) Polyvinyl acetate",
            "c) Polystyrene",
            "d) Perspex"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plasticised PVC is not used for making pipes for drainage. It is used for making baby-pants, bathroom curtaining and garden hose.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for making chewing gums?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perspex",
            "b) Polyvinyl acetate",
            "c) Teflon",
            "d) Polystyrene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Perspex is also known as lucite. It is a solid transparent plastic made of polymethyl methacrylate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the Teflon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has high density of the order 2.1 to 2.3 gm/cm3",
            "b) It has excellent electrical insulation properties",
            "c) It has high coefficient of friction",
            "d) It is dense and chemically inert"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polyvinyl acetate is used for making chewing gums. It is also used in handicrafts, envelope and wallpaper adhesives.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of Teflon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coatings of frying pans",
            "b) Combs and brush handles",
            "c) Audio cassettes",
            "d) Optical fibres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Teflon has very low coefficient of friction. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "Polystyrene is prepared by ___________ polymerisation of styrene.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Condensation",
            "b) Free radical",
            "c) Anionic",
            "d) Cationic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coatings of frying pans, non-lubricating bearings, wire and cable insulation etc are some of the applications of Teflon. it is also used as liners in hose assembly.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "The softening temperature of polystyrene is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-20 0C",
            "b) 30-50 0C",
            "c) 80-100 0C",
            "d) 120-150 0C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Polystyrene is prepared by free radical polymerisation of styrene in the presence of benzoyl peroxide as catalyst.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of polystyrene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insulators for motors",
            "b) Dome-shaped covers for solar collectors",
            "c) Laminates for printed circuitry",
            "d) Containers for talcum powder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The softening temperature of polystyrene is 80-100 0C. Polystyrene is a vinyl polymer. Structurally, it is a long hydrocarbon chain, with a phenyl group attached to every other carbon atom.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "The neighbouring polymeric chains in thermosets are held together by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vander Waal’s force",
            "b) Hydrogen bond",
            "c) Covalent bond",
            "d) Electrovalent bond"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The neighbouring polymeric chains in thermosets are held together by covalent bonds. A covalent bond is bond by the sharing of electrons and has good strength.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thermosets have 3-dimensional, cross-linked network structure",
            "b) Thermosets cannot be remoulded, reused or reclaimed",
            "c) Thermosets are hard, strong and brittle",
            "d) Thermosets are soluble in suitable solvents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thermosets are insoluble in any solvent. They have a 3-D cross-linked network structure and cannot be remoulded, reused or reclaimed. They are hard, strong and brittle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of thermosets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epoxy",
            "b) Teflon",
            "c) Vulcanised rubber",
            "d) Bakelite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Epoxy, vulcanised rubber, Bakelite are some of the examples of thermosets. Teflon is not an example of thermosets. PTFE (Teflon) is best known for its use in coating non-stick frying pans and other cookware.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "The condensation product of phenol and formaldehyde is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phenolic resins",
            "b) Urea formaldehyde resins",
            "c) Polyvinyl chloride",
            "d) Polystyrene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The condensation product of phenol and formaldehyde is known as phenolic resins or phenoplasts or PF resins. Phenoplasts include the expanded plastics obtained by introducing a blowing agent (foaming agent).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is not true for the formation of Bakelite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excess of phenol",
            "b) Excess of formaldehyde",
            "c) Acid catalyst",
            "d) Heat and curing agent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Excess of formaldehyde is not required for the formation of Bakelite. Excess of phenol is required in the formation of Bakelite and it also requires an acid catalyst and heat and curing agent.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is not true for the formation of Resite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excess of formaldehyde",
            "b) Base catalyst",
            "c) Acid catalyst",
            "d) Neutral or acidic conditions and heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acid catalyst is not used for the formation of the Resite. It requires a base catalyst and excess of formaldehyde. It also requires neutral or acidic conditions of heat.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phenolic resins are hard, rigid and strong",
            "b) Phenolic resins have good abrasion resistance",
            "c) Phenolic resins are usually dark coloured, pinkish brown",
            "d) Phenolic resins have poor chemical resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phenolic resins have good chemical resistance. All the other options are correct. Phenolic resins are hard, rigid and strong and have good abrasion resistance. They are usually dark coloured, pinkish brown.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of phenolic resins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finishing of cotton textiles",
            "b) Distributor heads of car",
            "c) Domestic plugs and switches",
            "d) Adhesives for grinding wheels"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Distributor heads of car, domestic plugs and switches, adhesives for grinding wheels, etc are some of the applications of phenolic resins. It also includes the expanded plastics obtained by introducing a blowing agent (foaming agent).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement about the Urea formaldehyde resins from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are clear and colorless",
            "b) They have good adhesive characteristics",
            "c) They have low hardness and tensile strength than PF resins",
            "d) They have excellent abrasion resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Urea formaldehyde resins are used as adhesives for plywood and furniture. These resins are used in adhesives, finishes, particle board, MDF, and molded objects. UF and related amino resins are considered a class of thermosetting resins of which urea-formaldehyde resins make up 80% produced globally.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the essential structural requirement of an elastomer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long flexible chains",
            "b) Weak intermolecular forces",
            "c) Rigidity in structure",
            "d) Occasional cross-linking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Elastomers are a long flexible chain; they are not rigid in nature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "Natural rubber is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poly isoprene",
            "b) Ethylene glycol",
            "c) Butadiene",
            "d) Acrylonitrile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Natural rubber is poly (cis) isoprene. Malaysia is one of the leading producers of rubber.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "The structural formula of isoprene is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-benzyl-1,3-butadiene",
            "b) 2-methyl-1,3-butadiene",
            "c) 3-benzyl-1,2-butadiene",
            "d) 3-methyl-1,2-butadiene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The structural formula of isoprene is 2-methyl-1,3-butadiene. It is a common organic compound with the formula CH2=C(CH3)-CH=CH2. In its pure form, it is a colorless volatile liquid. Isoprene is produced by many plants.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Raw rubber is weak and have low tensile strength",
            "b) Raw rubber is attacked by oxidizing agent",
            "c) In organic solvents, it undergoes swelling and disintegration",
            "d) Raw rubber is durable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Raw rubber is not durable due to its oxidation in air. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "The temperature at which raw rubber is heated for the vulcanisation process is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-10 0C",
            "b) 10-50 0C",
            "c) 50-100 0C",
            "d) 100-140 0C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperature at which raw rubber is heated for the vulcanisation process is 100-140 0C. A typical vulcanization temperature for a passenger tire is 10 minutes at 177 °C.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "In the vulcanisation process, the raw rubber is heated with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen",
            "b) Sulphur",
            "c) Carbon",
            "d) Calcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the vulcanisation process, the raw rubber is heated with sulphur. It is a chemical process for converting natural rubber or related polymers into more durable materials via the addition of sulphur or other equivalent curatives or accelerators. These additives modify the polymer by forming cross-links (bridges) between individual polymer chains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vulcanised rubber has excellent resilience",
            "b) Vulcanised rubber has only slight tackiness",
            "c) Vulcanised rubber has high elasticity",
            "d) Vulcanised rubber has tensile strength 10 times more than raw rubber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The amount of sulphur added determines the extent of the stiffness of vulcanised rubber. This sulphur modify the polymer by forming cross-links (bridges) between individual polymer chains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "The tensile strength(kg/cm 2) of vulcanised rubber is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200",
            "b) 2000",
            "c) 500",
            "d) 5000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vulcanised rubber has low elasticity and decreases with the extent of vulcanisation. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "The percentage of butadiene and styrene in Buna-S is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50% each",
            "b) 60% and 40% respectively",
            "c) 80% and 20% respectively",
            "d) 75% and 25% respectively"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tensile strength of vulcanised rubber is 2000 kg/cm 2. Cross-linking introduced by vulcanization prevents the polymer chains from moving independently.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as a catalyst in the preparation of Buna-S?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benzoyl peroxide",
            "b) Hydrogen peroxide",
            "c) Cumene hydroperoxide",
            "d) Acrylonitrile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cumene hydroperoxide act as a catalyst in the preparation of Buna-S (Butadiene styrene).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the SBR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It has low load bearing capacity",
            "b) It has high abrasion resistance",
            "c) It swells in oils and solvents",
            "d) It has low oxidation resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: SBR has high load bearing capacity, high abrasion resistance, swells in oil and solvent and has low oxidation resistance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of SBR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conveyor belts for food",
            "b) Lining of tanks",
            "c) Oil-resistance foam",
            "d) Printing rollers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lining of tanks, adhesives, gaskets, motor tyres, etc are some of the applications of SBR.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the best resistance to oils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Natural rubber",
            "b) Neoprene",
            "c) Nitrile rubber",
            "d) Styrene rubber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Buna-N is prepared by the co-polymerisation of butadiene and acrylonitrile in the emulsion system. Buna-N is nitrile rubber used in the automotive and aeronautical industry to make fuel and oil handling hoses.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of neoprene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conveyor belts",
            "b) Wire and cable insulation",
            "c) Adhesives",
            "d) Printing rollers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nitrile rubber has the best resistance to oils among the following options. All the other options have lower resistance to oils.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "The major constituent of butyl rubber is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isobutylene",
            "b) Isoprene",
            "c) Chloroprene",
            "d) Acrylonitrile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Conveyor belts, adhesives, wire and cable insulation, shoe-soles, etc are some of the applications of neoprene. Printing rollers is not an application of neoprene.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Which of the following act as a catalyst in the preparation of butyl rubber?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cumene hydroperoxide",
            "b) Anhydrous AlCl3",
            "c) Lewis base",
            "d) Grignard reagent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In butyl rubber, isobutylene constitutes (95-99) % and isoprene constitutes (1-5) %.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "The solvent used in the preparation of butyl rubber is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methyl iodide",
            "b) Methyl halide",
            "c) Methyl chloride",
            "d) Methyl sulphide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Anhydrous AlCl3 acts as a catalyst in the preparation of butyl rubber. Butyl rubber is a synthetic rubber, a co-polymer of isobutylene with isoprene.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "The tensile strength of the fiber is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very Low",
            "b) Low",
            "c) High",
            "d) Intermediate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The tensile strength of the fiber is high and depends upon the strength of the chemical bonds of the polymer chains.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of bonding maintains the alignment of chains of the polyester?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vander Waal’s force",
            "b) Dipole-dipole attraction",
            "c) Hydrogen bonding",
            "d) Covalent bonding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dipole-dipole attraction are induced due to the dipole formed by the alignment of negative and positive charges and hence this type of bonding maintains the alignment of chains of the polyester.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Nylon-66, PET and PAN all have Tg around ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 0C",
            "b) 200 0C",
            "c) 300 0C",
            "d) 500 0C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nylon-66, PET and PAN all have Tg around 100 0C. The glass-transition temperature Tg of a material characterizes the range of temperatures over which this glass transition occurs. It is always lower than the melting temperature, of the crystalline state of the material, if one exists.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Hydrogen bonding is responsible for maintaining the alignment of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stereoregular chains of isotactic polypropylene",
            "b) Polyesters",
            "c) Polyacrylonitrile",
            "d) Polyamides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Hydrogen bonding is responsible for maintaining the alignment of polyamides and polyurethanes. Polyamides are polymer of a type made by the linkage of an amino group of one molecule and a carboxylic acid group of another.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Nylon-6 can be prepared by ring opening polymerisation of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amino caproic acid",
            "b) Caprolactum",
            "c) Adipic acid",
            "d) Terephthalic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nylon-6 can be prepared by ring opening polymerisation of caprolactum. Caprolactum has 6 carbons and hence, Nylon-6.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the third step for the synthesis of nylon-6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conversion of cyclohexane into cyclohexanone",
            "b) Ring opening polymerisation of caprolactum",
            "c) Conversion of cyclohexanone-oxime into caprolactum",
            "d) Conversion of cyclohexanone into cyclohexanone-oxime"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Conversion of cyclohexane into cyclohexanone is the initial step. Then the second step is the conversion of cyclohexanone into cyclohexanone-oxime and then the conversion of cyclohexanone-oxime into caprolactum is the third step for the synthesis of nylon-6. Ring opening polymerisation of caprolactum is the last step.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "The cyclohexanone is converted into cyclohexanone-oxime by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Treatment with hydroxylamine",
            "b) Oxidation",
            "c) Reduction",
            "d) Backmann rearrangement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cyclohexanone is converted into cyclohexanone-oxime by treatment with hydroxylamine because hydroxylamine act as a catalyst for this reaction. This is the second step for the synthesis of Nylon-6.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Nylon-6,6 is made by the condensation polymerisation of hexamethylene diamine and adipic acid in the molar ratio of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 : 3",
            "b) 1 : 2",
            "c) 3 : 5",
            "d) 1 : 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nylon-6, 6 is made by the condensation polymerisation of hexamethylene diamine and adipic acid in the molar ratio of 1 : 1. Equivalent amounts of hexamethylene diamine and adipic acid are combined with water in a reactor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "The nylon-6, 6 have high crystallinity which imparts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low strength",
            "b) Low meting point",
            "c) Toughness and elasticity",
            "d) Retention to poor mechanical properties"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The nylon-6, 6 have high crystallinity which imparts high strength, high melting point, elasticity, toughness and retention to good mechanical properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of nylon-6, 6?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Durable hair combs",
            "b) Adhesives",
            "c) Tyre cords",
            "d) Medicine and pharmacy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Durable hair combs, tyre cords, medicine and pharmacy are some of the applications of nylon-6, 6.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Nylon-6, 6 have application in medicine and pharmacy because of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elasticity",
            "b) Toughness",
            "c) Good hydrocarbon resistance",
            "d) Sterilisability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nylon-6, 6 have applications in medicine and pharmacy because of sterilisability.  It is also used as an engineering material in bearings and gears due to its good abrasion resistance and self-lubricating properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "The other name for dacron is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyethylene terephthalate",
            "b) Polyacrylonitrile",
            "c) Polyamidenitrile",
            "d) Polyethylene caprolactum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The other name for dacron is polyethylene terephthalate. It is the most common thermoplastic polymer resin of the polyester family and is used in fibers for clothing, containers for liquids and foods.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "PET is prepared by heating dimethyl terephthalate and ethylene glycol in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acidic medium",
            "b) Basic medium",
            "c) Neutral medium",
            "d) Water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PET is prepared by heating dimethyl terephthalate and ethylene glycol in a basic medium at moderate pressure (2.7–5.5 bar) and high temperature (220–260 °C).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Terephthalic acid is converted into its dimethyl ester by treating it with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methyl chloride",
            "b) Hydroxylamine",
            "c) Methyl alcohol",
            "d) Ethylene glycol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Terephthalic acid is converted into its dimethyl ester by treating it with methyl alcohol. At high temperature, TPA crystals constantly dissolve and reform which increases the release of 4-formylbenzoic acid in solution where oxidation can be completed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of dacron?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic recording tapes",
            "b) Wide-necked jars for coffee",
            "c) Car heater",
            "d) Window shades"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blends of terylene fibers with wool have better crease and wrinkle resistance, they are more durable, higher strength, do not shrink and are not attacked by moths. Terylene polyester staple fiber is being used in staple-fibre form in blends with both natural and other synthetic fibers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "Acrylonitrile is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vinyl chloride",
            "b) Methyl alcohol",
            "c) Methyl chloride",
            "d) Vinyl cyanide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Magnetic recording tapes, wide-necked jars for coffee, car heater are some of the applications of dacron.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orlon is the trade name of polyacrylonitrile",
            "b) Orlon fibers are quick drying and resistant to water",
            "c) Orlon fibers are less resistant to acid, gases than nylon",
            "d) Orlon fibers are used for manufacturing window shades"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Acrylonitrile is a vinyl cyanide. It is an organic compound with the formula CH2CHCN and is  colorless volatile liquid, although commercial samples can be yellow due to impurities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "Ion-exchange resin is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Low molecular weight",
            "c) Organic polymer with porous structure",
            "d) Soluble"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Ion-exchange resins are cross-linked, insoluble, high molecular weight, organic polymers with a porous structure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "Which of the following ion get released from the cation exchange column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) H+",
            "b) Na+",
            "c) K+",
            "d) Ca+2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Only H+ ion get released from the cation exchange column.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "Which of the following ion get released from the anion exchange column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO3-2",
            "b) OH–",
            "c) Cl–",
            "d) SO4-2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Only OH– ion get released from the anion exchange column.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "Ion-free water coming out from the exchanger is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Potable water",
            "b) Disinfected water",
            "c) Coagulated water",
            "d) Demineralised water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ion-free water coming out from the exchanger is known as demineralised water as it is free from all the mineral impurities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is incorrect about the demineralised water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is as pure as distilled water",
            "b) It is very good for use in high pressure boilers",
            "c) It is fit for domestic use",
            "d) It can be made either by distillation or by using cation and anion exchangers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Demineralised water is not recommended for domestic use such as drinking purposes. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "The exhausted cation exchange column is regenerated by passing a solution of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dil. HCl",
            "b) Dil. NaCl",
            "c) Conc. HCl",
            "d) Conc. NaCl"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The exhausted cation exchange column is regenerated by passing a solution of dil. HCl. Dil HCl is also known as brine solution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "The exhausted anion exchange column is regenerated by passing a solution of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dil. KOH",
            "b) Conc. KOH",
            "c) Conc. NaOH",
            "d) Dil. NaOH"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By passing a solution of dil. NaOH, the exhausted anion exchange column is regenerated.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "In ion-exchange process, the capital cost is _________ and the operational expenses are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low, high",
            "b) High, low",
            "c) High, high",
            "d) Low, low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The raw water used for ion-exchange process should be non-turbid and free from impurities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "The residual hardness in ion-exchange process is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-2 ppm",
            "b) 5-10 ppm",
            "c) 10-15 ppm",
            "d) 20-30 ppm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In ion-exchange process, the capital cost is very high and the operational expenses are also high.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Silicones are called inorganic polymers due to absence of _________________in the main backbone chain.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen atom",
            "b) Oxygen atom",
            "c) Carbon atom",
            "d) Hydrogen atom"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Silicones are called inorganic polymers due to the absence of carbon atoms in the main backbone chain. Carbon compounds are the basis of organic chemistry.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Silicones resemble inorganic polymers in having high % of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ionic character of Si-O bond",
            "b) Organic groups on silicon atoms",
            "c) Controlled hydrolysis",
            "d) Solubility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Silicones resemble inorganic polymers in having high % of ionic character of Si-O bond. The bond between silicon and oxygen molecule is very ionic in nature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "The catalyst used in the preparation of poly-siloxanes is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benzoyl peroxide",
            "b) Grignard reagent",
            "c) Cumene hydroperoxide",
            "d) Lewis acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The catalyst used in the preparation of poly-siloxanes is Grignard reagent. The Grignard reaction is an organometallic chemical reaction in which alkyl, vinyl, or aryl-magnesium halides, CH3MgI (Grignard reagents) add to a carbonyl group in an aldehyde or ketone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Which of the following is tri-functional?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dimethyl silicon chloride",
            "b) Trimethyl silicon chloride",
            "c) Tetramethyl silicon chloride",
            "d) Momethyl silicon chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Momethyl silicon chloride is tri-functional and gives cross-linking to the final polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Which of the following gives linear chain silicones on polymerisation by controlled hydrolysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dimethyl silicon chloride",
            "b) Trimethyl silicon chloride",
            "c) Tetramethyl silicon chloride",
            "d) Momethyl silicon chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dimethyl silicon chloride gives linear chain silicones on polymerisation by controlled hydrolysis. All the other options does not give such type of reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "Which of the following is mono-functional?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dimethyl silicon chloride",
            "b) Trimethyl silicon chloride",
            "c) Tetramethyl silicon chloride",
            "d) Momethyl silicon chloride"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trimethyl silicon chloride is mono-functional and hence, a chain-stopper.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "On increasing the temperature, the viscosity of polysiloxanes ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remain constant",
            "d) First increases then decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The proportion of momethyl silicon chloride used in polymerisation determines the amount of cross-linking that can be obtained. It is made on an industrial scale as the principal precursor to dimethyl silicone and polysilane compounds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "The bond energy of Si-O bond is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 37 kJ/mol",
            "b) 115 kJ/mol",
            "c) 248 kJ/mol",
            "d) 502 kJ/mol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The viscosity of polysiloxanes does not change appreciably with a change in temperature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not combine with fiber to give composites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metals",
            "b) Ceramics",
            "c) Non-metals",
            "d) Polymers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Composites are obtained from metals, ceramics and polymers by adding fibers to them. Non-metals do not contribute to the formation of composites.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a property of matrix materials which are modified by adding particulate fillers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improved performance at elevated temperature",
            "b) Decrease in surface hardness",
            "c) Modification in electrical conductivity",
            "d) Improved abrasion resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Improved performance at elevated temperature, decrease in surface hardness, modification in electrical conductivity, improved abrasion resistance are some of the properties of matrix materials which are modified by adding particulate fillers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "What is the aspect ratio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length to diameter ratio",
            "b) Length to depth ratio",
            "c) Depth to length ratio",
            "d) Diameter to length ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aspect ratio is defined as length to diameter ratio. The aspect ratio is expressed as two numbers separated by a colon (x:y). The values x and y do not represent actual length and diameter but, rather, the relationship between length and diameter.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of composite is not classified under the category of number of layers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unidirectional fibre reinforced",
            "b) Laminar",
            "c) Sandwich panels",
            "d) Glass-fibre reinforced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glass-fiber reinforced composite is not classified under the category of number of layers. All the other options are classified under this category.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laminar composites consist of 2-D sheets that are stacked and subsequently cemented together",
            "b) Sandwich panels consist of two stronger outer sheets separated by a layer of less dense core material",
            "c) Core material should be heavy-weight and low corrosion resistance",
            "d) The stiffness of the sandwich panel increases as the core thickness increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The matrix phase controls the environmental resistance of the composites. Since Polymer Matrix Composites combine a resin system and reinforcing fibers, the properties of the resulting composite material will combine something of the properties of the resin on its own with that of the fibers on their own.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "One of the most popular types of core material used is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metal foam",
            "b) Honeycomb",
            "c) Glass",
            "d) Plastic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Core material should be light-weight and high corrosion resistance. All the other options are correct. Laminar composites consist of 2-D sheets that are stacked and subsequently cemented together. Sandwich panels consist of two stronger outer sheets separated by a layer of less dense core material and the stiffness of the sandwich panel increases as the core thickness increases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "The flexural stiffness of the sandwich panel is proportional to the _____________ of core thickness.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Square",
            "b) Square root",
            "c) Inverse",
            "d) Cube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the most popular types of core material used is a honeycomb structure. Rest all options are not used widely as core material should be light-weight and high corrosion resistance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of a sandwich panel?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fabrication of wings of aircrafts",
            "b) Design of ships, boat hulls",
            "c) Conveyor belts",
            "d) Fabrication of roofs, floors and walls of buildings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The flexural stiffness of the sandwich panel is proportional to the cube of core thickness. It increases with the thickness of the core material.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "When fibers are used as a dispersed phase for the reinforcement of matrices, the resultant composites are known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass-fiber reinforced",
            "b) Carbon-fiber reinforced",
            "c) Wood-fiber reinforced",
            "d) Unidirectional-fiber reinforced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fabrication of wings of aircrafts, design of ships, boat hulls and fabrication of roofs, floors and walls of buildings are some of the applications of sandwich panel. Conveyor belts are not the application of sandwich panel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of glass-fiber reinforced composites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low density",
            "b) Low impact resistance",
            "c) High tensile strength",
            "d) Excellent chemical and corrosion resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When fibers are used as a dispersed phase for the reinforcement of matrices, the resultant composites are known as glass-fiber reinforced. Glass-fiber reinforced composites should have low density, high impact resistance, high tensile strength and excellent chemical and corrosion resistance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an application of glass-fiber reinforced composites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adhesives",
            "b) Conveyor belts",
            "c) Design of ships",
            "d) Automotive parts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glass-fiber reinforced composites should have low density, high impact resistance, high tensile strength and excellent chemical and corrosion resistance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as reinforcement in advanced polymer matrix composite?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glass-fiber reinforced",
            "b) Carbon-fiber reinforced",
            "c) Wood-fiber reinforced",
            "d) Unidirectional-fiber reinforced"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Automotive parts, storage tanks, plastic pipes etc are some of the applications of glass-fiber reinforced composites.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of composites?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy to manufacture and durable",
            "b) Excellent thermal, mechanical and chemical properties",
            "c) Heavy-weight and non-versatile",
            "d) Economical and tailor made"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carbon-fiber reinforced is used as reinforcement in advanced polymer matrix composite, which requires retention of desired properties.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "The substances which are capable of uniting two other materials together by adhering strongly to the surface of both are called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organic conducting polymers",
            "b) Biodegradable polymers",
            "c) Adhesives",
            "d) Composites"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The substances which are capable of uniting two other materials together by adhering strongly to the surface of both are called adhesives. Adhesives may be found naturally or produced synthetically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Two surfaces are rapidly, economically and easily joined to each other by adhesives",
            "b) The process of applying adhesives requires highly specialized workers or high heat",
            "c) Adhesives bonding requires less after-finishing",
            "d) Bonding by adhesives gives smoother finished surfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of applying adhesives does not require highly specialized workers or high heat. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "Corrosion of metals at the joints is minimized by joining dissimilar metals with adhesives because ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct metal to metal contact is avoided",
            "b) Adhesive act as a lubricator at the joints",
            "c) Metals are covered with adhesives",
            "d) Adhesives prevent the exposure to environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Corrosion of metals at the joints is minimized by joining dissimilar metals with adhesives because direct metal to metal contact is avoided so galvanic action is reduced.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Adhesives joints are leak-proof for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Solids only",
            "b) Liquids only",
            "c) Gases only",
            "d) Both liquids and gases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adhesives joints are leak-proof for liquids and gases. There is no leaking of solids.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "The strength of adhesive joint is _____________ than mechanical joint obtained by welding or riveting.",
        "Options": [
            "a) More",
            "b) Less",
            "c) Equals to",
            "d) Very less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Joining of labels to plastic cans or bottles is not possible without the use of adhesives. Adhesives are typically organized by the method of adhesion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "On increasing the temperature, the strength of adhesive ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Remain same",
            "b) Increases",
            "c) Decreases",
            "d) First increases than decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The strength of adhesive joint is less than mechanical joint obtained by welding or riveting. Mechanical joints are permanent and stronger as they are joined with the help of nuts and bolts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "The bond energy of a metallic bond is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600-1200 kJ/mol",
            "b) 60 kJ/mol",
            "c) 20 kJ/mol",
            "d) 100-350 kJ/mol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On increasing the temperature, the strength of adhesive decreases due to relative weakness in bonding large objects with a small bonding surface area and greater difficulty in separating objects during testing.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of thermosetting synthetic resins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Epoxy",
            "b) Acrylic polyester",
            "c) Cellulose derivatives",
            "d) Silicones"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bond energy of a metallic bond is 100-350 kJ/mol. Metallic bonding is the force of attraction between valence electrons and metal ions. Therefore, it is very strong in nature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Which of the following adhesive is prone to brittle failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acrylic polyester",
            "b) PF resin",
            "c) UF resin",
            "d) Epoxy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Epoxy, silicones, acrylic polyester, polyurethane etc are some of the examples of thermosetting synthetic resins.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "The epoxy resins are the _______________ products of epichlorohydrin and bisphenol.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Free radical",
            "b) Addition",
            "c) Ion-exchange",
            "d) Condensation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PF resins are prone to brittle failure due to its tough structure.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as curtain-wall sealants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyurethane",
            "b) Silicones",
            "c) Polyvinyls",
            "d) Cellulose derivatives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The epoxy resins are the condensation products of epichlorohydrin and bisphenol. They are formed by the condensation reaction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "Emulsion adhesives are based on ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyurethane",
            "b) Collodion",
            "c) Urea-formaldehyde",
            "d) Polyvinyl acetate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Epoxies are used in a wide diversity of applications because of their strength, durability and great versatility. Epoxy resins are low molecular weight pre-polymers or higher molecular weight polymers which normally contain at least two epoxide groups. The epoxide group is also sometimes referred to as a glycidyl or oxirane group.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "Collodion is a mixture of cellulose nitrate with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol",
            "b) Ketone",
            "c) Carboxylic acid",
            "d) Phenol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although expensive, silicones are used as curtain-wall sealants because of their excellent aging characteristics.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used for making rechargeable batteries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polypyrrole",
            "b) Polyester",
            "c) Polyaniline",
            "d) Polyacrylonitrile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Polyaniline is used for making rechargeable batteries in the shape of flat buttons or as laminated rolled films.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "The advantage of using conducting polymers in place metals is their ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost",
            "b) Light-weight",
            "c) Thermal conductivity",
            "d) Solubility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The advantage of using conducting polymers in place metals is their light-weight and they do not corrode.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "During the polymerisation of polyaniline, the sequence of the colour change is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Green >> copper tint >> blue green >> light blue",
            "b) Light blue >> blue green >> copper tint >> green",
            "c) Copper tint >> blue green >> green >> light blue",
            "d) Blue green >> green >> light blue >> copper tint"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During the polymerisation of polyaniline, the sequence of the colour change is Light blue >> blue green >> copper tint >> green.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "The precipitate is dried under vacuum at 60-80 0C for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 hour",
            "b) 2 hours",
            "c) 5 hours",
            "d) 8 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The precipitate is dried under vacuum at 60-80 0C for 8hours for complete dehydration process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "The color of emeraldine salt which is obtained is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copper tint",
            "b) Blue green",
            "c) Green",
            "d) Light blue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The color of emeraldine salt which is obtained is green. The emeraldine salt form of polyaniline is highly electrically conducting.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "The final washings of the salt is done with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distilled water",
            "b) Diethyl ether",
            "c) Methanol",
            "d) Acetone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The final washings of the salt is done with diethyl ether for cleaning it completely.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not true for intrinsically conducting polymers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low conductivities",
            "b) Poor mechanical strength",
            "c) Improcessability",
            "d) Good storage stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Conducting polymers having conjugation is a type of intrinsically conducting polymers. They do not conduct extrinsically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conductive element filled polymer possess good bulk conductivity",
            "b) Conductive element filled polymer are generally high in cost",
            "c) Conductive element filled polymer are light in weight",
            "d) Conductive element filled polymer are mechanically durable and strong"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Intrinsically conducting polymers have poor storage stability leading to its loss in conductivity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of conducting polymers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rechargeable batteries",
            "b) Analytical sensors",
            "c) Electronics",
            "d) Adhesives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Conductive element filled polymer are generally low in cost. All the other options are correct.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Bakelite is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gel",
            "b) Gas",
            "c) Solid",
            "d) Liquid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rechargeable batteries, analytical sensors, electronics are some of the applications of conducting polymers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not required for the biodegradation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro-organism",
            "b) Environment conditions",
            "c) Adhesives",
            "d) Substrate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three essential conditions for the biodegradable process, micro-organism, environment and substrate. Micro-organisims biodegrade the substrate in the presence of a suitable environment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Biodegradation will be more for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) More molecular weights and high crystallinity",
            "b) Low molecular weights and high crystallinity",
            "c) More molecular weights and less crystallinity",
            "d) Low molecular weights and less crystallinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Greater the hydrophilicity of the polymers, larger is the rate of biodegradation. Biodegradation increases with more hydrophilicity. Hydrophilicity means having an affinity for water; readily absorbing or dissolving in water.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of a natural biodegradable polymer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collagen",
            "b) Polyvinyl alcohol",
            "c) Lignin",
            "d) Natural rubber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Biodegradation will be more for low molecular weights and less crystallinity. Low molecular weight compound can easily be broken into pieces by micro-organisms and hence improve the rate of biodegradation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of synthetic biodegradable polymer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polyvinyl alcohol",
            "b) Poly gamma-glutamic acid",
            "c) Polyanhydrides",
            "d) PHBV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Collagen, natural rubber, lignin etc are some of the examples of natural biodegradable polymer. Polyvinyl alcohol is not an example of a natural biodegradable polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "PHB is used in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agricultural applications",
            "b) Medical applications",
            "c) Manufacture of shampoo bottles",
            "d) Adhesives"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polyvinyl alcohol, polyanhydrides and PBV are examples of the synthetic biodegradable polymer. Poly gamma-glutamic acid is not an example of a synthetic biodegradable polymer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Select the incorrect statement from the following option.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Biodegradable polymers are not suitable candidates in the recycling of commingled plastics",
            "b) Biodegradable polymers are very expensive",
            "c) Biodegradable polymers are an attractive option for addressing the solid waste and marine pollution",
            "d) Biodegradable polymers are easily available"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Biodegradable polymers do not need to be land-filled, they will re-enter normal geo-chemical cycles over time. They are easily decomposed in the natural environment and does not require any external agent.\n"
    }
]